<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Judicium discretionis, or, A just and necessary apology, for the peoples judgement of private discretion exhibited against the arrogant pretences and imperious suggestions of Tannerus, Valentia, Bellarmine, with other advocates of the papal tyranny, and the tendred to the consideration of all those, who would secure themselves against antichristian impostures and delusions.</title>
            <author>Wilson, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1667</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 262 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 81 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66595</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2946</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R39122</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18216553</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18216553</idno>
            <idno type="VID">107190</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66595)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 107190)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1138:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Judicium discretionis, or, A just and necessary apology, for the peoples judgement of private discretion exhibited against the arrogant pretences and imperious suggestions of Tannerus, Valentia, Bellarmine, with other advocates of the papal tyranny, and the tendred to the consideration of all those, who would secure themselves against antichristian impostures and delusions.</title>
                  <author>Wilson, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[48], 111 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Elizabeth Calvert ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1667.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Wilson by Wing and NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [48].</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographic references.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:107190:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Judicium Diſcretionis:</hi> OR A juſt and neceſſary APOLOGY, FOR The Peoples <hi>Judgement</hi> OF PRIVATE DISCRETION, EXHIBITED Againſt the arrogant <hi>Pretences</hi> and imperious <hi>Suggeſtions</hi> of <hi>Tannerus, Valentia, Bellarmine,</hi> with other Advocates of the <hi>Papal</hi> Tyranny; <hi>AND</hi> Tendred to the conſideration of all thoſe, who would ſecure themſelves againſt <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> impoſtures and deluſions.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Baſil.</hi> t. <hi>2.</hi> Moral. Reg. <hi>72.</hi> p. <hi>372.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Elizabeth Calvert,</hi> at the <hi>Black ſpread Eagle</hi> in <hi>Duck-lane.</hi> 1667.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:107190:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:107190:2"/>
            <head>To all ſuch in theſe Nations as are true hearted to the Proteſtant Intereſt, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally thoſe of the <hi>Laity.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIRS,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>MONGST all the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies which at this day are agitated with ſo much heat and vigour, in this li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigious and unquiet world, there is ſcarcely any of greater uſe, or higher importance than that which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns the <hi>liberty</hi> and <hi>power</hi> of the People, in judging and trying the inſtructions, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertions and decrees of their Teachers. What <hi>Luther</hi> ſaid of Juſtification, I may ſay of this; it is <hi>doctrina ſtantis &amp; cadentis Eccleſiae,</hi> of ſuch influence upon the welfare, life, and being of the Church,
<pb facs="tcp:107190:3"/>that it cannot be ſecured without it. And yet there are few, if any, that have in our Language treated ſingly, and fully concerning it. I ſhall therefore, towards a ſupply of that defect, diſcourſe a while upon it, and endeavour from <hi>Scripture</hi>-grounds, to evince and clear up the juſt extent and bounds thereof, that ſo Teachers may neither be affronted by their People, nor People oppreſſed by their Teachers, but both the one and the other may quietly enjoy the freedom and priviledge proper to their <hi>ſphaere</hi> and ſtation. And in order thereunto ſhall, before I go any further, deſire you to take notice, that there is a four-fold <hi>judgment</hi> in matters of Religion. 1. A <hi>judgment</hi> of ſupreme <hi>legiſlation</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion;</hi> which is peculiar unto God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, the great Maker and Lord of the Univerſe, whoſe Prerogative it is, to give Laws unto the conſciences of men, and preſcribe the rule, matter, order and manner of his own Worſhip and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and to render unto every one ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as he does more or leſs conform thereunto. 2. A <hi>judgment</hi> of civil <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection</hi> and <hi>moderation;</hi> and this pertains to the Magiſtrate, whoſe office it is, not
<pb facs="tcp:107190:3"/>only to protect the Church from the rage and violence of perſecutors, but alſo to ſee that all Officers and Members thereof, do keep their reſpective places, and perform their ſeveral duties, that ſo Religion may flouriſh, and the work of God may go on and proſper. 3. A <hi>judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of miniſterial <hi>direction</hi> and <hi>inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction;</hi> which belongs unto the Paſtors of the Church, who both as they ſit in council, and alſo in the courſe of their ordinary miniſtery, are to aſſert and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the truth, teach their people out of the <hi>holy Scriptures</hi> the good knowledge of God, admoniſh the ſcandalous, caſt out the obſtinate, and reſtore the peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to their former communion and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges. 4. A <hi>judgement</hi> of private <hi>exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination</hi> and <hi>diſcretion;</hi> and this belongs to every individual Chriſtian, who for the certain information of his own judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the full ſatisfaction of his conſcience, both may and ought to try by the Word, not only the doctrins of particular Paſtors, but likewiſe the decrees of Councils, and ſo far as he finds them agreeable thereunto, he is to receive them, and ſo far as they are otherwiſe he is to reject them. It is the laſt of theſe that
<pb facs="tcp:107190:4"/>falls under our preſent conſideration; concerning which, Writers diſcourſe va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly, according as their principles and intereſts lead them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Jewiſh Rabbi's,</hi> as they labour under lamentable blindneſs and ſottiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in other particulars, ſo they do in this; they are ſo far from allowing their people the liberty belonging to them, that they do moſt cruelly and unmerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully tyrannize over them, holding them in no leſs bondage than the ſevere <hi>Egy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptians</hi> did their afflicted Anceſtors in times paſt. Inſtead of permitting them the exerciſe of private, rational, ſelf-directive <hi>diſcretion,</hi> which there is all the reaſon in the world they ſhould allow them, they tie them up cloſely to their mouthes, ſtrictly charging them to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve them, and that without the leaſt heſitancy or ſcruple, let them ſay what they will. Nay, ſuch is their pride and arrogancy, that they will have them to reverence and obſerve all their doctrins and precepts, how abſurd or ſtrange ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they are, as if they were no leſs than ſo many rays and beams of divine light, darted down from the very face of God himſelf. Even in our <hi>Saviour</hi>'s time they
<pb facs="tcp:107190:4"/>were got to ſuch height of ſpirit, that (as the <hi>Scripture</hi> it ſelf ſhews) they am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitiouſly affected the title of <hi>Rabbi,</hi> and bound <hi>heavy burthens,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 23.4, 7.</note> 
               <hi>and grievous to be born, and laid them upon mens ſhoulders.</hi> And as if this were not ſufficient, they have ſince that time proceeded (in a way proportionable to their defection from God and his truth) to greater lordlineſs and oppreſſion. <hi>R. Abhuhabh</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Menoras Hammaor p. <hi>23.</hi> col. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>That what ever they teach and ſpeak in their my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical and allegorical explications, the people are bound no leſs firmly and certainly to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve them, quam legi Moſes, than the very law of Moſes.</hi> And, <hi>That if they find any thing that ſeems to them hyperbolical, or quite contrary to nature, or too high for their apprehenſions, they muſt aſcribe the fault to their own defective vnderſtandings, non autem verbis ipſorum, and not to their words.</hi> And he likewiſe ſaith, that <hi>all their words are the words of the living God;</hi> that <hi>not one of them ſhall fall to the ground in vain;</hi> that <hi>the people ſtand bound to believe all things that are writ by them, or in their name;</hi> that <hi>they muſt not in the leaſt reflect on them, either in word or thought;</hi> and that <hi>he that does it ſhall not eſcape puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> Whereby it appears, that they
<pb facs="tcp:107190:5"/>challenge an abſolute, uncontrollable power over their people; that they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire them to ſhew the ſame reſpect to their Aſſertions, that they are to give to the <hi>Scriptures</hi> themſelves; that if they deliver any thing that ſeems ſtrange or harſh, they muſt not for all that offer to ſuſpect them, or cenſure their Doctrine; and, that if they do it, they hold they ſhall be puniſhed for it. And <hi>R. Selomoh Jarchi</hi> writing upon thoſe words of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Thou ſhalt obſerve to do according to all that they ſhall inform thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 17.10.</note> thus gloſſes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them; <hi>Thou muſt not decline from that which they ſhall tell thee, though they ſay, de manu tuâ dextrâ quod ſiniſtra ſit, et de manu ſiniſtrà quod dextra ſit; of the right hand that it is the left, and of the left, that it is the right.</hi> He looked upon their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority over the people as ſuch, that though they ſhould ſpeak things never ſo incredible and ridiculous, yet they might not either gainſay them, or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold their aſſent.<note place="margin">Auctor Ik<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>karim <hi>l. 3.</hi>
               </note> Indeed one of his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows who would ſeem milder than the reſt, endeavours ſomewhat to mollifie the expreſſion, but whiles he is doing it, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the ſame proud blood running in his own veins, he affirms little leſs him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.
<pb facs="tcp:107190:5"/>For, ſaith he, <hi>If it happen that a private perſon know more than the wiſe men, and do better underſtand the Truth than ſome of them, yet the conſtitution of more ought to ſtand, Ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> fas erit diſſentire ab iis, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall it be lawfull for him to deſſent from them, ſo as to do any thing of his own opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</hi> In the judgement then of ſuch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, as pretend to greater ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berneſs and moderation than the reſt, a private man though never ſo far above them in abilities, may not diſſent from them, let them ſay what they will, nor do any thing of his own opinion, though he have never ſo good reaſon for it, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they be pleaſed to allow of it. And <hi>Guil. Vorſtius</hi> tells of their <hi>Rabbines</hi> that they hold that <hi>their decrees</hi> do,<note place="margin">Not. in Maim. de fund. leg. <hi>c. 6. p. 77.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>non mino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri jure, with no leſs right bind their peoples Conſciences to obedience, than the Precepts of the written Law;</hi> that <hi>they muſt reverence them as they reverence God himſelf;</hi> that <hi>he who diſputes againſt them contends with the Holy Spirit;</hi> that <hi>he who takes up a ſtrife with them, is as he who takes up a ſtrife againſt the holy Ghoſt,</hi> that <hi>he who thinks evilly of them, is as he who thinks evilly of the holy Spirit.</hi> And that they may the better deterr the people from either con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temning
<pb facs="tcp:107190:6"/>or violating their Precepts, they do, <hi>anathematis fulmine ferire, excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate ſuch as they finde guilty thereof;</hi> nay they do <hi>fuſtigare ſine aeſtimatione &amp; nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro, beat them till they dye.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Buxt. Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nag. Jud. c. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>62.</hi>
               </note> If you deſire more inſtances of this nature, turn to the Authors quoted in the Margent,<note place="margin">Hoornb. cont. Jud. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi> p. <hi>99.</hi> Guil. Vor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtius ubi ſup. p. <hi>76, 77.</hi>
               </note> and they will plentifully ſupply you. This you'l ſay is ſevere dealing, and ſuch as can neither conſiſt with the neceſſary liberty of Religion or reaſon; and yet ſuch is the miſerable blindneſs and ſlavery of their deluded people,<note place="margin">Vid. Buxt. Synag. Jud. c. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>65.</hi>
               </note> that they readily ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to them. <hi>Luther</hi> in a Treatiſe which he wrote of the <hi>authority</hi> and <hi>faithfulneſs</hi> of the <hi>Rabbi's</hi> and their writings, informs us that the <hi>Jews</hi> ſay they ought to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve them, although (as you heard be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) they affirm the <hi>left</hi> hand is the <hi>right,</hi> and the <hi>right,</hi> the <hi>left.</hi> And for proof hereof, he tells us of three <hi>Jews</hi> that being in his Company fell into diſcourſe with him, and as often as he urged them with a Text of Scripture, ſo often they reply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>quod Rabbinis ipſorum credere teneren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, that they were bound to believe their Rabbi's; and that as for the Bible they were free from it.</hi> And thus do their <hi>Rabbi's</hi> and they moſt impiouſly and wretchedly
<pb facs="tcp:107190:6"/>combine together to undo and ruine each other. For on the one hand, ſuch is the height and imperiouſneſs of the <hi>Rabbi's</hi> that they challenge an abſolute Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Lordſhip over their poor peoples Faith and Conſciences, ſo as to teach or require what they will, without being either contradicted or diſobeyed. And on the other hand, ſuch is the ſlavery and baſeneſs of the people, that they proſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute themſelves to the wills of their <hi>Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi's,</hi> ſuffering them quietly to exerciſe over them what power they pleaſe. And their <hi>Rabbi's</hi> having brought them to this paſs, whither cannot they lead them? what may they not do with them? when the <hi>Philiſtims</hi> had bored out <hi>Sampſons</hi> Eyes, they lead him and did with him what they pleaſed. And after the ſame manner deal theſe proud Uſurpers with their poor people: They firſt put out their eyes, by taking from them all li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of private <hi>diſcretion,</hi> and having got them into that condition, they do at pleaſure make a prey of them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſame domination that the <hi>Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Rabbi's</hi> challenge and exerciſe over their people, the ſame the <hi>Mahometan Muphti's</hi> challenge and exerciſe over
<pb facs="tcp:107190:7"/>theirs. They will by no means endure them to diſpute any thing that is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn'd them, but will have them to look upon their bare word as ſufficient War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, for their Faith and practice. This <hi>Mahomet</hi> himſelf laid a Foundation to; for being conſcious of the weakneſs of the grounds he proceeded on, he ſtrictly forbad all Expoſtulations, and Reaſonings about the Religion he preſcribed,<note place="margin">Azoar <hi>13.</hi> Ed. <hi>1.</hi> lat. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring he would have it received without any <hi>ſcruple</hi> or <hi>examination</hi> whatſoever. This our Writers do every where make mention, and complain of, as a piece of higheſt inſolency, uſurpation, and tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. The learned <hi>Grotius</hi> in that excellent Book which he wrote in defence of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De verit. l. <hi>6.</hi> p. <hi>303.</hi>
               </note> gives this account of his Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, That <hi>it is wholly framed for ſhedding of blood; and that it challenges aſsent, nullâ inquirendi libertate, without any liberty at all of enquiry.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Treatiſe of Relig. part <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi> p. <hi>350.</hi>
               </note> And <hi>Amyrald</hi> in a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of the like nature ſpeaks to the ſame purpoſe. <hi>There is nothing</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>he hath ſo ſtrictly forbidden as to diſpute conterning his Law.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Turcop. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi> p. <hi>34.</hi>
               </note> Nay, ſuch (as Dr. <hi>Sutclive</hi> ſhews out of <hi>Zigabenus</hi>) was his impatiency of contradiction that he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded his Vaſſals to deſtroy the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,
<pb facs="tcp:107190:7"/>
               <hi>Ubicun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> in ipſos inciderint, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they ſhould light on them.</hi> And to incourage them to the work, he told them that it was meritorious, and ſuch as ſhould be recompenced with ample reward. And when ſome of his Diſciples, wondered he ſhould deliver ſuch harſh Doctrine, he anſwered, <hi>Se non cum Spiritu, ſed gladio veniſse, that he came not with the Spirit but the Sword; and that therefore thoſe were to be deſtroyed that would not admit of his Law.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Specul. hiſt. l. <hi>23.6.43.</hi>
               </note> And anſwerable hereunto is that which we have in <hi>Vincentius Bellovacenſis,</hi> who acquaints us how he cauſed an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient man that was a Jew to be murdered, <hi>Quod ſe ab eo reprehenſum audiviſset, for that he heard he had ſaid ſomewhat by way of reproof of him.</hi> This is no other than barbarous, nay beaſtly Tyranny; and yet ſuch is the reverence that his blinde Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelytes bear to him and his <hi>Alcoran,</hi> though a bundle of the groſſeſt Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſe and Vanity, that ever impudent folly heaped up together, that they will not hear talk of having any Queſtions or Controverſies raiſed about it, or any part of it; but looking upon it as the genuine and undoubted ſuggeſtions of the Angel <hi>Gabriel,</hi> who they fondly imagine held
<pb facs="tcp:107190:8"/>familiar converſe with him, cloſe with it and obſerve it without any reaſonings or Jealouſies at all concerning it. Were it worth the while to turn to other Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, I might multiply paſſages out of them to the ſame purpoſe; but theſe few I have here recited may ſerve to intimate to you what condition the <hi>Mahometans</hi> keep their people in, as to the buſineſs under debate. They are ſo far from al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing them a liberty of private exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation (which yet their doctrine, of any other that layes claim to Scripture, or any part of it, ſhould for the abſurdity and folly that attends it, admit of) that they utterly decry and forbid it, nay per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute it with greateſt rage and violence, preſently taking away the lives of ſuch as offer to raiſe the leaſt doubts or ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples about it. And hereby it is (as <hi>Voe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> obſerves) that they uphold their <hi>Empire,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Diſput. part <hi>2.</hi> de Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hammed. p. <hi>668.</hi>
               </note> and keep their people from <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking</hi> them, which they could never do, if they allowed them the free exerciſe of that <hi>power</hi> and <hi>liberty</hi> which belongs to them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The ſame courſe that the <hi>Jewiſh Rabbi's,</hi> and <hi>Mahometan Muphti's</hi> take with their people, the ſame the <hi>Popiſh
<pb facs="tcp:107190:8"/>Clergy</hi> take with theirs. Under colour of preventing popular oppoſitions and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſions, they deny them all <hi>power</hi> in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Religion</hi> ſave that of <hi>aſsent</hi> and <hi>obedience,</hi> telling them it belongs to the Church in her Repreſentative to judge and determine what Doctrines are found and what are not, what is to be done in the ſervice of God, and what is not to be done; and that they are to ſtand wholly to her judgement, acquieſce in her ſentence, and cloſe with her Decrees how corrupt or unreaſonable ſoever they may ſeem to be, without either contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction or cenſure. They hold that their <hi>Prelates</hi> and <hi>Prieſts</hi> aſſembled in Council are the Church; and that they ſit not there as <hi>Doctors</hi> to teach and perſwade, but as <hi>Praetors</hi> or Judges to appoint and eſtabliſh; and that whatever they define and determine, ought to be believed and obſerved without any further examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or tryall, ſcruple or doubting. Nay they look upon their Authority and wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to be ſuch that they hold it no leſs than preſumption and impiety to call in queſtion what is agreed upon and preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by them. That you may not think we father upon them thoſe opinions they
<pb facs="tcp:107190:9"/>never held (as they uſe to deal with us) I ſhall ſhew you out of their own appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Authors what they teach in this matter. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> tells us that though Infidels and ſuch as are out of the Church, may examine and try thoſe things which are delivered by them that preach the Goſpel to them, yet thoſe who are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Church, and underſtand the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and priviledges of it, may not do it.<note place="margin">t. x. de verb. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>10.</hi> Col. <hi>155.</hi> imp. Pariſ. <hi>1620.</hi>
               </note> Take his own words; they are in anſwer to our objection from the <hi>Berae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. Though</hi> Paul (ſaith he) <hi>was an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, and could not preach falſe Doctrine, yet this appeared not in the beginning to the Beraeans, neither ſtood they bound preſently to believe, untill they firſt ſaw Miracles, or other probable, reaſons of believing; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when</hi> Paul <hi>proved Chriſt to them out of the Oracles of the Prophets, they deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedly ſearched the Scriptures whether thoſe things were ſo; but Chriſtians who know that the Church cannot erre in explicating the Doctrine of Faith, tenentur eam reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere, &amp; non dubitare an haec it a ſe habeant, ſtand bound to receive it, and not to doubt whether theſe things are ſo.</hi> So that in his judgement, as ſoon as a man comes to know the Church, and underſtand who are
<pb facs="tcp:107190:9"/>the Paſtors of it, he muſt then queſtion no further, but muſt ſtand to their judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and receive their dictates even in matters of faith, without either trial or doubting. Though he may enquire after the Church, and doubt till he know it, yet when he hath once found it, he muſt do ſo no more; he muſt then turn his trying and doubting into aſſenting and obeying. But <hi>Bellarmine</hi> is not herein alone; <hi>Valentia</hi> ſpeaks to the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.<note place="margin">Anal. fid. Cath. l. <hi>8.</hi> c. <hi>7.</hi> p. <hi>90.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Then</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>do we ſufficiently un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the ſpirit of the doctrine, when we perceive it to be propounded by the lawful Paſtors of the Church, eſpecially if a Council aſſent. Here, whoſoever does not acquieſce, but going further arrogates to himſelf judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment over his Judges, and queſtions whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thoſe things are truths, which are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined by ſuch as are ſet over us in the Church, by whom the holy Ghoſt would have us to be taught: non exequitur ſed tranſgreditur ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perbè ac contumaciter, he does not obſerve, but proudly and contumaciouſly tranſgreſs the method of proving ſpirits preſcribed by the divine Law.</hi> Whereby you ſee he looks upon the power of judging as pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar to the Paſtors of the Church, in whoſe ſentence he will have us to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieſce,
<pb facs="tcp:107190:10"/>and from which he thinks it is ſo far from being lawful to depart, as that he teaches, we may not without guilt of vain and ſinful arrogancy ſo much as take upon us to call it in queſtion, or paſs cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure upon it. This indeed is high and ſtately doctrin, and yet as if this were not ſufficiently correſpondent and uniform to the <hi>Roman</hi> pride and greatneſs,<note place="margin">Colloq. Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisb. ſeſſ. <hi>9.</hi> p. <hi>280.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerus</hi> goes further, and tells us, that the people are ſo far under the <hi>government</hi> of their ſuperiours, that <hi>if they erre in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fining of any doubt, vi talis regiminis errare poſsunt, imo debent They may by virtue of the ſaid government erre with them, nay, they ought to do it.</hi> Upon the recital whereof, I may well break forth into the <hi>Prophet</hi>'s pathetical exclamation, and ſay, <hi>Be astoniſhed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 2.12.</note> 
               <hi>O ye heavents, at this!</hi> How ſad is it that ever Chriſtian tongue ſhould utter ſuch abſurd and poiſonous doctrin! What ſons of meekneſs and tenderneſs do theſe men ſometimes ſeem to be, and yet what ſlaves and vaſſals would they make of the people? though they have ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional powers and diſcerning ſenſes, yet they muſt not uſe them. The gods of the Heathens have eyes and <hi>cannot</hi> ſee,<note place="margin">Pſal. 115.5.</note> ears and <hi>cannot</hi> hear, mouthes and <hi>cannot</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:107190:10"/>ſpeak: but its far otherwiſe with them; they have eyes and <hi>muſt</hi> not ſee, ears and <hi>muſt</hi> not hear, mouthes and <hi>muſt</hi> not ſpeak, but muſt acquieſce in the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and ſentence of their Maſters, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out enquiring or buſying themſelves any further.<note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.16.</note> Though a filly <hi>Aſs</hi> may in ſome caſes reply upon her Maſter, rebuke and condemn him, yet may not they in any caſe reply upon them, or in the leaſt call in queſtion what is taught, impoſed or done by them, but muſt ſtoop down under the burden that is laid upon them, without any exceptions or debates whatſoever. And ſuch as is the doctrin of theſe men, ſuch is their proof. They holy Ghoſt in the Hiſtory of God's dealing with <hi>Job,</hi> ſaith, <hi>The oxen were plowing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 1.14. <hi>Aquin,</hi> 22. <hi>q.</hi> 2. <hi>a</hi> 6.</note> 
               <hi>and the aſſes feeding beſides them;</hi> from whence, for want of better evidence, they infer, that there are two <hi>ſorts</hi> of perſons in the Church, <hi>Majores</hi> and <hi>Minores;</hi> that is to ſay, the <hi>Clergy</hi> and the <hi>Laity;</hi> and that the latter, in matters to be believed, are to depend upon the former. According to which rate of arguing, I know no party ingaged in a cauſe ſo deſperate, that may not even from Scripture fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh themſelves with ſufficient ſtrength.
<pb facs="tcp:107190:11"/>If this kind of reaſoning may be allowed, I ſee not but the Curate, following the <hi>vulgar Latin,</hi> might from that of <hi>Jeremy, Paveant illi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 17.18.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; non paveam ego,</hi> fairly enough infer, that the <hi>Pariſhioners</hi> were to <hi>pave</hi> the <hi>Chancel,</hi> and not <hi>he.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Notwithſtanding the harſhneſs of this doctrin, againſt the peoples judgment of private <hi>diſcretion,</hi> and the ridiculouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the proof alledged for it, yet are there ſome even amongſt us, and ſuch too as would be thought to be none of the worſt Proteſtants, who ſtand up for it and urge it. The Biſhop of <hi>Edinburgh</hi> determins,<note place="margin">Epiſt. to the Paſtors of the Church of <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </note> that <hi>where a man hath not a Law, his own judgment is the rule of his Conſcience; but where there is a Law, the Law muſt be the rule.</hi> Wherein he aſſerts theſe two errors; the one is, that men may make Laws, and bind burdens where Chriſt hath not done it; which as it is contrary to Proteſtant doctrin,<note place="margin">Confeſſ. Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil. art. <hi>10.</hi> p. <hi>137.</hi> Chamier. Panſt. t. <hi>3.</hi> l. <hi>15.</hi> c. <hi>8.</hi> ſect. <hi>6.</hi> p. <hi>325.</hi>
               </note> ſo it is inconſiſtent with, and deſtructive of our Chriſtian liberty. The other is, That the Laws of men do preponderate and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſede the authority of conſcience, ſo that we muſt not appeal from them to it, but from it to them, which amounts to no leſs than plain blaſphemy, and leads to
<pb facs="tcp:107190:11"/>no other than down right atheiſm. True Religion teaches, that <hi>all fleſh muſt be ſilent before the Lord;</hi> that the conſcience is God's Vice-gerent, deputed by him to rule in the ſoul, and that the dictates thereof are ſacred and inviolable; but this man hath found out other kind of doctrin: he will have the authority of humane Laws to be ſuperiour to that of conſcience, and that the former is not to ſtoop unto the latter, but the latter unto the former; which indeed is a good device to propagate <hi>Heatheniſm, Turciſm,</hi> and ſuch like prevailing impoſtures, but not true piety and holineſs, which though ſometimes they have <hi>Kings</hi> for <hi>nurſing fathers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa 49.23.</note> 
               <hi>and Queens for nurſing mothers</hi> to them, yet for the moſt part they have the powers and laws of the earth againſt them. Notwithſtanding the Archbiſhop of St. <hi>Andrews</hi> ſteers his courſe the ſame way, and tells us, that <hi>in things indifferent,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sermon at <hi>Perth</hi> Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly.</note> 
               <hi>we muſt always eſteem that to be beſt, and moſt ſeemly, which ſeemeth ſo in the eye of publick authority; neither is it for private men to control publick judgment. As they cannot make publick conſtitutions, ſo they may not control nor diſobey them, being once made. Indeed authority ought to lock well
<pb facs="tcp:107190:12"/>to this, that it preſcribe nothing but rightly, appoint no rites nor orders in the Church, but ſuch as may ſet formard godlineſs and piety. Yet put the caſe that ſome be otherwiſe eſtabliſhed, they muſt be obeyed by ſuch as are members of that Church, as long as they have the force of a conſtitution, &amp;c. But thou wilt ſay, My conſcience ſuffers me not to obey, for I am perſuaded that ſuch things are not rigth, nor appointed; I anſwer thee, in matters of this nature and quality, the ſentence of thy ſuperiours ought to direct thee, and that is ſufficient ground to thy conſcience for obeying.</hi> In things then of indifferency, whether we have eyes or no, we muſt make no uſe of them, but muſt ſee with thoſe of authority. We muſt not, like creatures that have reaſon, weigh things in the ballance of our own judgments, but like ſuch as are utterly deſtitute of it, take them upon the recommendation of ſuch as are over us. And if (which is no un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſual thing) it fall out, that they either through ignorance, partiality, prejudice, or the like, appoint ſuch orders, as are not onely againſt conſcience, (which through mis-ifformation may erre) but likewiſe the holy <hi>Scriptures,</hi> yet we muſt obey, ſatisfying our ſelves with this, that
<pb facs="tcp:107190:12"/>it is authority that does enjoyn them. This, one would think, were doctrin too groſs, to gain advocates in a place of ſuch light as <hi>England</hi> is; and yet Dr. <hi>Covel</hi> and Dr. <hi>Burgeſs</hi> own it, and plead for it: they ſay, <hi>The precept of the ſuperiour binds more than the conſcience of the inferiour can;</hi>
               <note place="margin">See Dr. <hi>Ames Freſh ſuit, p.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 7. <hi>p.</hi> 79.</note> 
               <hi>and that the ſubject having the command of the King or Biſhop for his warrant, ought not to examine, but onely to perform what he ſeeth commanded.</hi> From hence you may learn how much theſe men eſteem of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of ſuperiours, and how little of the dictates of conſcience, though never ſo well inſtructed and informed. In thoſe things wherein the authority of ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours does not interpoſe it ſelf, by deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining, commanding, forbidding, or ſuch like acts, it hath ſome power; but in thoſe things wherein it does interpoſe, it hath none at all, but muſt filently ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieſce. If ſuperiours fay, that light is darkneſs, or darkneſs is light; that good is evil, or evil is good; we muſt, though conſcience tell us quite otherwiſe, aſſent and believe. If they forbid us to do what conſcience ſaith, God hath commanded, or command us to do what Conſcience ſaith, he hath forbidden, we muſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb facs="tcp:107190:13"/>the leaſt ſcruple or reluctancy obey them, looking upon this as ſufficient warrant to us, that what we omit or do is by their appointment. And what reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, faith, worſhip, or courſe of life is ſo bad, that this doctrine, if reduced to practice, will not lead a man to? nay, to maintain ſuch kind of doctrin, what is it leſs than to juſtifie all the cruelty and wickedneſs that hath been done at the appointment of higher powers, whether Civil or Eccleſiaſtical, ever ſince they had an exiſtence in the world? Nay, what is it but to condemn the <hi>generation of the juſt,</hi> and throw dirt in the face of the bleſſed Martyrs, and faithful ſervants of God in all ages, who out of the entire zeal they have born to him, and the reſpect they have had to their own conſciences, have ſtill, as occaſion hath been offered, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the unjuſt commands of the Rulers under whom they have lived, and denied their obedience to them? For thoſe I here deal with, to pretend they give this power to Rulers only in thins indifferent and lawful,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Stil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling fleel's Iren. p. <hi>119.</hi>
               </note> does (as a good Author ſhews) avail little, whiles in the mean time they make them the ſole Judges of what is indifferent and what is not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different,
<pb facs="tcp:107190:13"/>of what is lawful and what is not lawful. What difference (as to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence) is there betwixt ſaying, Rulers may enjoyn us to worſhip an Idol, and it belongs onely to Rulers to judge what is an Idol? none at all. The ſame doctrin that teaches it belongs onely to Rulers to judge what is indifferent and what is not indifferent, what is lawful and what is not lawful, and that we are bound to ſtand to their appointment; teaches in effect, that if they enjoyn us to worſhip an Idol, we we muſt do it. And therefore it is ſad, that men who pretend reſpect to the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant</hi> intereſt, ſhould allow of, much more that they ſhould broach doctrin of ſuch ill influence and tendency. But they are not without their followers. How or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary is it at this day for men in all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies and places we fall into, as ſoon as ever we begin to ſpeak of matters of Religion, eſpecially thoſe which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern Worſhip and Diſcipline, preſently to refer us to the Church, and tell us, that the Church requires and forbids us to do ſo and ſo, and to ask who muſt be Judge, you or the Church, and what, will you be wiſer than the Church, and will you not obey the Church? And fuch is their
<pb facs="tcp:107190:14"/>blind zeal, that though this be all the ſtrength they have to urge, yet if we will not thereupon comply with them, they forhtwith exclaim againſt us, as proud, wilfull, ſchiſmatical, ſeditious, nay repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and reproach us as people unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to live. This is ſo common, that I believe there are few that read theſe lines, but they know what I ſay to be truch. Now what unreaſonable dealing is this, how contrary to the Scriptures, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuitable to the Religion we do profeſs? That in <hi>Italy, Spain,</hi> and ſuch like pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where <hi>Antichriſt</hi> bears ſway, they ſhould make ſuch language the keeping of their Song, is not much to be mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel'd at but that the people of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> which God hath made a <hi>Tabor</hi> of Goſpel light and glory, ſhould be guilty of ſo much folly and baſeneſs, is a thing more remarkable, and ſuch, as if Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence prevent not, may prove a buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of very bad conſequence. It's to be feared that thoſe amongſt us who ſo zealouſly cry up implicit Faith, and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to our own Church, will if the ſcales turn do it to another. I ſpeak not this to detract in the leaſt from the juſt Authority of the Church, or to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh
<pb facs="tcp:107190:14"/>either the reverence or obedience belonging to her, but to obviate the fooliſh, vain, ſervile diſpoſition of ſome, who think they connot ſufficiently evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence themſelves to be true Sons of the Church, unleſs they aſcribe to her ſuch a tranſcendent, magiſterial, uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trollable power as <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> never in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted her with. As men ſhould take care that they withhold not from her any reſpect that <hi>Jeſus</hi> Chriſt hath appointed them to give her, ſo they ſhould like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe take care, that they give her no more than what he hath allowed her. The ſame <hi>Apoſtle</hi> that commands us to <hi>obey them that have the rule over us,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 13.17. 1 Cor. 4.6.</note> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids us to <hi>think of men above that which is written.</hi> We muſt neither ſo honour God as to withhold or diminiſh the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect due to men, nor ſo reſpect men, as to withhold or diminiſh the honour due to God, but following the advice of our <hi>Saviour,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 22.21.</note> we muſt <hi>give unto God the things that are Gods, and unto</hi> Men <hi>the things that are mens.</hi> But.</p>
            <p n="5">5. All <hi>Orthodox, Proteſtant</hi> Writers who adhere to the <hi>Scripture,</hi> and are ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere to the reformed Intereſt, deliver o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kinde of Doctrine, teaching that
<pb facs="tcp:107190:15"/>the people are nto ſuch Idiots as thoſe before mentioned would make them, nor ſo little concern'd in the buſineſs of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, but that they have belonging to them a Judgement of private <hi>diſcretion,</hi> by virtue where of they have power of examining and trying whatever is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded to them by their Leaders for their inſtruction, edification or uſe. As they allow unto Magiſtrates a judgement of <hi>civil inſpection,</hi> by virtue whereof they ought to ſee that all things in the Church be done <hi>decently and in order;</hi> and unto Paſtors a Judgement of <hi>mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterial direction,</hi> by virtue whereof they may meet together, debate and decree ſuch things as are conducible to the more acceptable, and ſucceſsfull carrying on of the work of Chriſt, ſo (becauſe both Magiſtrates and Miniſters are but ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate Jdges, bound up to the ſentence of God ſet down in his Word, from which it is poſſible they may erre) they allow unto all Chriſtians a Judgement of <hi>private diſcretion,</hi> by virtue whereof they not only may, but ought (as they tender their own ſaſety) to bring the Conſtitutions and Decrees of fuch as are over them to the common Rule, and
<pb facs="tcp:107190:15"/>try them thereby, e're they cloſe with them. To this purpoſe writes <hi>Luther.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Oper. t.</hi> 2. p. 375.</note> 
               <hi>The ſheep</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ought to judge, utrum Praelati vocem Chriſti, vel alienorum propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, whether the Prelates ſpeak the voice of Chriſt or of Strangers.</hi> And, <hi>that Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, in which the veice of the Goſpel ſounds, hath not only power and command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of judging of every Opinion, but even every pious man ought to do it, and that ſub periculo ſalutis, under the peril of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</hi> He did not only think that Churches taken conjunctly had power of judging the Doctrines of their reſpective Prelates and Paſtors, but hkewiſe that every private Chriſtian had power to do it, nay ſood bound to do it, and that under the higheſt penalty, even the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture of Salvation. And with him agree multitudes more of the moſt learned, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox and holy men that ever engaged in the defence of the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> cauſe. <hi>It cencerns all the godly</hi> (ſaith Dr. <hi>Whita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker</hi>) <hi>that they take heed to themſelves,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Part <hi>1.</hi> cont. <hi>1.</hi> q. <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>8.</hi> p. <hi>359.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>et quamvis doctrinam diligenter examinant, and diligently examine every Doctrine, leſt they cloſe with thoſe things that are falſe for thoſe which are true.</hi> And, <hi>every man ought to lean upon his own Faith, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend
<pb facs="tcp:107190:16"/>upon his own judgement, non ex cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſquam hominis nutu, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> arbitrio, not the ſuggeſtion and arbitrement of any men whatſoever.</hi> And, <hi>unuſquiſque ſibi judex eſse debet, every one ought to judge for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</hi> The common Queſtion that ſtill occurrs in all our debates, and which ever and anon we are put to anſwer, is who muſt be judge? Why, here you have a clear and peremptory ſolution; Every man muſt judge for himſelf. Though private men may not aſcend either into the Magiſtrates Throne, or into the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters Chair, ſo as authoritatively to judge or give ſentence for others, yet they may and ought to do it for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. To the ſame purpoſe ſpeaks <hi>Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellus:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theſ. Salm. de ſum. jud. <hi>ſect. 48. p. 110.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>It is</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>verily lawfull, and ever will be lawfull, unicui<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> fideli, for eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the faithfull by a tacit ſenſe of the minde and internal Judgement, to ſee and judge whether the ſentence given in Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Judicatories be juſt, and uttered ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Law of God, or whether it be given contrary, beſides, or againſt the Scripture.</hi> The Law of God is the <hi>Cyno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure</hi> which not only ſingle perſons, but whole Synods, how wiſe, grave, pious, or eminent ſoever they are, muſt have
<pb facs="tcp:107190:16"/>their eye upon, and ſteer their courſe by; and when they have made decrees, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate men muſt take them under tryall, and ſee whether they have kept to it, or not; if they have, then they muſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve and follow them, if otherwiſe, they muſt forſake and leave them, chooſing rather to poſſeſs and enjoy the Truth with a few, nay alone, than to lye under the evil of Error and Deception, with the greateſt multitudes. To theſe, that I may not weary you with teſtimonies in ſo plain a caſe, I ſhall only add ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of that which the Author a little before mentioned hath ſaid on this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; who hath in a few words ſpoken the deſign and ſcope of the following Diſcourſe. <hi>If</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>it be ſaid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Stil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingſt. Iren.</hi> p. 118, 119.</note> 
               <hi>that men are bound to be ruled by their Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours in determining what things are law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and what not; to this it is anſwered: Firſt, no true Proteſtant can ſwear blinde obedience to Church Governours in all things. It is the higheſt uſurpation to rob men of the liberty of their judgements. That which we plead for againſt the Papiſts, is, that all men have eyes in their heads as well as the Pope; that every one hath a judicium pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatae diſcretion is, which is the rule of practice
<pb facs="tcp:107190:17"/>as to himſelf; and though we freely allow a Miniſterial power under Chriſt in the government of the Church, yet that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends not to an obligation upon men to go againſt the dictates of their own Reaſon and Conſcience. Their power is only di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rective and declarative, and in matters of duty can binde no more than Reaſon and evidence brought from Scripture by them, doth. — The plea of an Erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous Conſcience takes not off the Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to follow the dictates of it; for as a man is bound to lay it down ſuppoſing it er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous, ſo he is bound not to go againſt it, while it is not layd down. Again, if men, are bound to ſubmit to Governours in the determination of lawfull things, what plea could our Reformers have to withdraw themſelves from the Popes Yoak. — Let men turn and winde themſelves which way they will, by the very ſame arguments that any will prove ſeparation from the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>lawfull, becauſe ſhe required un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull things, as conditions of her commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, it will be proved lawfull not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form to any ſuſpected or unlawfull practice, required by any Church-governours upon the ſame terms, if the thing ſo required be after ſerious and ſober enquiry judged unwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable
<pb facs="tcp:107190:17"/>by a mans own Conſcience.</hi> In his Judgement then, men are not to ſubject themſelves to their Governours in all things they pleaſe to determine and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point, but to conſult their own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, and follow the dictates there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, which he looks upon as a point ſo eſſential to true Religion, that he takes him to be no true Proteſtant that do's renounce it; and withall declares it to be the higheſt uſurpation that Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours can be guilty of, to deny their people liberty of it. And yet he obſerves there are ſome even amongſt our ſelves that think they have no liberty of this nature; againſt whom he alledges the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of our worthy Reformers, whoſe withdrawing from the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> cannot be juſtified, unleſs ſuch a liberty be acknowledged. If you would yet further ſee what our Writers ſay con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this matter, you may conſult their diſcourſes againſt the Papiſts <hi>de in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretatione Scripturae, fide implicitâ, voto obedientiae,</hi> and ſuch like ſubjects.</p>
            <p>And thus I have given you ſome ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the different apprehenſions of men touching the preſent caſe, whereby you ſee that ſuch as are the enemies of the
<pb facs="tcp:107190:18"/>Truth, and be addicted to domination and oppreſſion, are altogether impatient of the peoples having any judgement of private <hi>diſcretion,</hi> nay reproach and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute it, as a thing intollerable, and not to be endured. But the more wiſe, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox and ſober party are wholly for it, as an undoubted right, ſetled upon them by Chriſt himſelf, which none may take from them without manifeſt injury both to him and them. Now becauſe the opinions and reſolutions of men, are no authentick determination of the matter, I ſhall therefore have recourſe to the <hi>Scripture,</hi> wherein the Holy Ghoſt hath ſet down the liberty and power both of Miniſters and People, and diſtinguiſhed their ſeveral Rights and Priviledges; and in particular I ſhall inſiſt upon thoſe words of <hi>Paul, Prove all things;</hi> from whence I ſhall endeavour to evince a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the forementioned enemies of the Truth, but more eſpecially the <hi>Papiſts</hi> and ſuch amongſt us as comply with them, that though the people have not publick power of judging for others, as Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters have, yet they have a private pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of judging for themſelves, which none ought to withhold or deny them the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:107190:18"/>
            <p>But that you may not think that what I alledge in the following diſcourſe in behalf of the peoples judgement of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate <hi>diſcretion</hi> do's only extend unto, and concern what is delivered by their Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, know that the ſame arguments that ſerve to prove a liberty in them of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Doctrines of their Teachers, ſerve likewiſe <hi>(mutatis mutandis)</hi> to prove a liberty in them of judging the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of the Civil Powers under whom they live. As the authority of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer is ſubordinate and limited, ſo is that of the latter; and as the former are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to errors and miſtakes, ſo likewiſe are the latter, and therefore as the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in defence and purſuance of their own ſafety, are to judge of the Doctrines of the one, ſo they are alſo to judge of the Commands of the other. Though the Powers over them be never ſo lawfull, wiſe, great, yet in matters of Religion they muſt not reſt upon their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, nor take what they deliver upon truſt, but muſt bring it to the Word, and with all boldneſs and freedom exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine it thereby, eſteeming of it accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as they finde it more or leſs agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able thereunto. This kinde of doctrine
<pb facs="tcp:107190:19"/>I know the fawning Paraſites of the times (that care not how high they aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend in extolling the power of Rulers, ſo they may but inſinuate themſelves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to favour, and drive on their own pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate intereſts) will look upon as little better than fanatical and ſeditious; but I hope all true Proteſtants have other kinde of apprehenſions of it. I am ſure it is ſuch doctrine as the faithfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God (who were as great ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of diſloyalty as any of thoſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy flatterers that at this day declaim the moſt againſt it) have in all Ages con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly both maintain'd and practiſed. Herein let the <hi>reverend</hi> and <hi>learned Dave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> ſerve for a witneſs.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Praelection. in</hi> Coloſſ. 3.23. <hi>p.</hi> 255.</note> 
               <hi>Subjects</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ought not, neither may they, judge of the decrees of Superiours, judicio authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis, by a judgement of authority, but they both may and ought to judge of the ſame, ſo far as concerns themſelves, judicio diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis, by a judgement of diſoretion. And</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>this is confirmeà omnium piorum exemplo, by the example of all the godly;</hi> and he inſtances in <hi>Daniel,</hi> the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and the <hi>Martyrs</hi> in Q. <hi>Maries</hi> dayes, <hi>who,</hi> he tells us, <hi>rightly judged that they ought not to believe thoſe things which were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded
<pb facs="tcp:107190:19"/>to them to be believed, nor do thoſe things which were commanded to be done.</hi> And the truth is, the liberty and exerciſe of ſuch a judgement is of ſuch uſe to the directing of the people in their duty, that it muſt needs be acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not only to be lawfull, but indiſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſably neceſſary. For, if Rulers; be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to miſtake, and to enjoyn unlawfull things, and people when they do it, muſt (as all confeſs that are not down-right Atheiſts) diſobey them, they muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity have liberty to judge of what nature that is which they do enjoyn them. For how is it poſſible, they ſhould be able to diſtinguiſh betwixt lawfull and unlawfull, cloſe with the one and avoyd the other, except they be allowed the uſe of their own <hi>diſcretion</hi> to adviſe and direct them in it? Suppoſe Rulers do with <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 3.5.19.</note> command them one while to worſhip <hi>God</hi> another while, an <hi>Image,</hi> how ſhall they do to know they muſt obey them in the one, and not in the other, unleſs they may have liberty to take both to the Rule, and try them thereby. Upon which and ſuch like grounds, I believe there is ſcarcely any Prince in the World truly pious, but he is
<pb facs="tcp:107190:20"/>content with all his heart to allow his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſuch a liberty. <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> though an Heathen <hi>Monarch,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 3.28.</note> after he had duely weigh'd things, was ſo far from being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed with <hi>Shadrach, Meſhech,</hi> and <hi>Abed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nego,</hi> for either cenſuring or diſobeying his decree (though done in the face of his whole <hi>Empire</hi>) that he himſelf <hi>bleſſes</hi> God upon that account, and <hi>commends</hi> them for it.</p>
            <p>To conclude, you underſtand, Sirs, the preſent ſtate and condition whereſh we are. The skies you ſee gather blackneſs round about, and look angrily upon us on every ſide. The cloud that a while a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go was but the bigneſs of a <hi>mans hand,</hi> hath now overſpread the whole face of the Heavens, and arm'd them with ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance againſt us. As if all thoſe ſore Judgements God hath of late years in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted upon us were too ſmall a Scourge for the chaſtening of ſuch a wicked and provoking people, he now threatens us with the invaſion of Forreigh Powers, which how far they may prevail, and what violence and ſeverity they may exerciſe both upon the outward and the inner man, he only knows. Many prudent, holy men (who as the Scripture it ſelf ſhews,
<pb facs="tcp:107190:20"/>are the fitteſt of all other to be conſulted in a caſe of this nature) having diligently obſerved and conſidered the aſpect and motion of the Starrs ingaged in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Conjunction,<note place="margin">Gen. 18.17. Prov. 25.14. Pſal. 22.3. Hoſ. 14.9. Mic. 6.9.</note> do preſage from them great and ſore tryalls. It concerns you therefore to <hi>awake</hi> out of ſleep, run to the <hi>Tower</hi> of <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 6.13.</note> and there arm your ſelves with ſpiritual <hi>armour</hi> from top to toe, that ſo you may be able to hold out againſt the ſharp aſſaults wherewith you are like to be exerciſed. However God is pleaſed to deal with you, be ſure you preſerve your Conſciences inviolate and pure, ſuffering neither force, nor flatteries to raviſh or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>file them. And in order thereunto, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that you keep cloſe unto the Word of God as it is contained in the holy <hi>Scriptures,</hi> conſtantly aſſert and maintain the authority, ſufficiency, perſpicuity and other excellencies belonging to it, and (in complyance with the deſign of this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe) examine and try all matters of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion thereby. <hi>Epict. Arrian.</hi> tells us that the greateſt and firſt work of a Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 20.79.</note> 
               <hi>to examine and try what is before him, and to admit nothing without proof.</hi> And the like I may ſay of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb facs="tcp:107190:21"/>Chriſtian; One of his firſt and greateſt works, in order to his neceſſary inſtruction, and the building of him up in Faith and Holineſs, is to bring all thoſe things he hath to do with in the buſineſs of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion to the Word, and examine them thereby, taking diligent care that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive nothing till he have firſt made tryal of it. Nay, if it be the duty of a Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher to be thus cautious in his underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings, it is much more the duty of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian to be ſo in his; by how much the undertakings of the one are of greater concernment than thoſe of the other, by ſo much it behoves the latter to be more cautious than the former. What's the reaſon wherefore ſo many are upon all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions ſeduced and lead aſide? It is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they take not this courſe; it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they receive things upon truſt, and venture on them before they have by due tryall found out what they are. The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon wherefore men embrace ſo many un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſound Doctrines, and betake themſelves to ſuch wilde, impious, pernicious practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, is becauſe they do not ſit in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon them, and make proof of them; but following the irregular motions of their own miſguided inclinations, give up
<pb facs="tcp:107190:21"/>themſelves e're they underſtand what they do. What was the reaſon that ſo many followed ſuch ſilly Creatures as <hi>Theudas, Judas</hi> of <hi>Galilee,</hi> and the like Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducers?<note place="margin">Acts 5.36, 37.</note> It was becauſe they did not take them to the Touch-ſtone of the Word, which would ſoon have ſhew'd they were but counterfeit Coyn, and not what they pretended to be. What's the reaſon that ſo many fall in with <hi>Heatheniſh, Popiſh</hi> wayes, but becauſe they neglect to bring them to the Scripture, which would teach them better? And indeed its juſt with God, if, when he hath given men light to walk by, they will not make uſe of it, but ſtill follow the bent of their own hearts, to deliver them up to Impoſtures and deluſions, as the juſt recompenſe of their folly and wilfulneſs. And if we look into the method of his proceedings, as they are ſet down in his Word, we ſhall finde, he frequently do's do it. Thus he dealt with the <hi>Heathens;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1.28.</note> when they <hi>did not like to retain him in their knewledge, he gave them over</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which our Tranſlation renders <hi>a reprobate minde,</hi> but it properly ſignifies a minde void of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that is diſabled from examining of things; ſuch as <hi>Nebuchadnezzars</hi> was,
<pb facs="tcp:107190:22"/>when God had taken his <hi>underſtanding</hi> from him.<note place="margin">Dan. 4.34.</note> Behold here the <hi>goodneſs</hi> and <hi>ſeverity</hi> of God <hi>goodneſs,</hi> in offering the knowledge of himſelf to them; <hi>ſeverity</hi> in puniſhing them thus for the contempt of it. Becauſe they employed not their mindes in the ſearch and ſtudy of the Truth, but like ungratefull wretches, deſpiſed and made light of it, therefore he ſmote them as he did the men of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> with blindneſs,<note place="margin">Gen. 19.11.</note> leaving them to grope for that way which otherwiſe they might have had eyes to have ſeen. Thus likewiſe he dealt with the <hi>Jews, he blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their eyes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 12.40.</note> 
               <hi>and hardened their hearts, that they ſhould not ſee with their eyes, nor under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand with their heart.</hi> They were a people exceeding dear to him, inſomuch that he favoured and priviledged them above all people in the World. He intruſted them with his holy Oracles, and the great things of his Law, with the various advantages attending thereon, which had they faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully improved, they might have injoyed to this day; but they made light of them, trampled them under foot, and profan'd them. And what is the iſſue of it? why, in juſt indignation he tears them away from them, and ſhuts them up in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;
<pb facs="tcp:107190:22"/>ſince which time they have been the moſt fooliſh, ſottiſh people in the World. And after the ſame manner he deals with thoſe that live under the Rule of <hi>Antichriſt;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Theſſ. 2.10, 11.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe they receive not the Truth</hi> (offered to them) <hi>in the love of it, therefore he ſends them ſtrong deluſions, giving them up to believe lyes.</hi> He hath by his good providence vouchſafed them his Word to be a Rule and Directory to them, and hath charged them to keep cloſe to it as the beſt Guide they can poſſibly follow; but they have neglected and forſaken it, and therefore he hath given them up to believe <hi>Monkiſh</hi> Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, and <hi>childiſh</hi> fables, whereby their Teachers do lamentably beguile them, and lead them into perdition. From theſe inſtances it appears what a dangerous thing it is for any people, how dean ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they are to God, to neglect his Word. It do's no leſs than expoſe them to the danger of dereliction, and ruine. As therefore you deſire to enjoy his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, and the continuance of the means of grace wherewith he hath bleſſed you, prize it at an high rate, be diligent in the ſtudy of it, and try all by it; chooſing rather to undergo all the hardſhip and
<pb facs="tcp:107190:23"/>miſery imaginable, than to ſwerve in the leaſt from it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Grindal,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zanch. vol. <hi>3.</hi> t. <hi>8.</hi> p. <hi>305.</hi>
               </note> Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards of <hi>York,</hi> writing to <hi>Zanchy,</hi> tells him, <hi>It is the property of a true Teacher to be tenacious of that faithfull Word, which is profitable for Doctrine, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> à veritate ne la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum quidem unguem diſcedere, and not to depart an hairs breadth from it.</hi> A good leſſon for the <hi>Adiaphoriſts</hi> and <hi>Latitudina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> of our preſent times, who think if they can but ſecure the Foundation, they need not trouble themſelves about leſſer matters. Beware how you comply with ſuch, or joyn with them in their ſinfull practices. As it is the duty of Teachers to be tenacious of the Word, ſo it is your duty likewiſe, and therefore ſee that you keep cloſe to it, ſuffering your ſelves by no means to be drawn from it. Though you be tempted with ſmiles and frowns, promiſes and threatnings, rewards and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, yet be not moved, do not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake it, but ſtoutly and conſtantly perſiſt in the defence of it. Make it to appear that you have higher ſpirits, and nobler prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples than natural generation could help you to; that you can trample upon the pride and glory of the World, and look
<pb facs="tcp:107190:23"/>Priſons, Gibbets, and Flames in the face. Let <hi>Atheiſts</hi> and <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſee you have ſuch a God, and ſuch a Religion, as you take to be worth the ſuffering for; that <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> ſpent not all her Martyrs at once; that by a myſtical and happy tranſanima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the ſouls of thoſe deceaſed Worthies, who ſacrificed their lives in the witneſs of the Truth many years ago, do live in you; and that notwithſtanding all the ſlaughters which <hi>Antichriſt</hi> that ravenous and inſatiable Wolf, hath made among the Saints in theſe Nations, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable Neutrality of the preſent age, wherein we live, there are yet thoſe who (if the Truth need further teſtimony) can finde in their hearts to part with their Liberties, Eſtates, Lives, and all that is near and dear unto them, in the behalf of it. Be not diſmayed with any of thoſe things that may befall you. Though you ſee the wayes of God (like the waters of <hi>Dimon</hi>) running down <hi>with blood,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 15.9.</note> yet be not moved, but ſtand your ground, and remain faithfull. Think it not below you to go to Heaven the ſame way that your dear Lord hath done before you. Be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling not only to conform to him in his works, but alſo in his ſufferings. You
<pb facs="tcp:107190:24"/>have many a time with delight read of the patience, cheerfulneſs, and conſtancy of the faithfull Servants of God in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times; let your carriage in your approaching tryalls be ſuch, that thoſe who ſhall come after you, may have oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion with the like delight to read of yours. Leaving theſe things to your ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious conſideration, I ſhall cloſe with that ſaying wherewith Dr. <hi>Holland</hi> uſed to take leave of his Friends, <hi>Commendo vos amori Dei, &amp; odio Papiſmi: I commend you to the love of God, and the hatred of Popery.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:107190:24"/>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:107190:25"/>
            <head>
               <hi>ERRATA,</hi> in the Margent.</head>
            <p>PAge 7, and 10. for <hi>t.</hi> 3. r. <hi>t.</hi> 1. p. 14. for <hi>Inſt.</hi> r. <hi>Hiſt.</hi> p. 19. for <hi>Luk.</hi> r. <hi>Luc,</hi> p. 90. for p. 166. r. <hi>col.</hi> 410.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>In the Book.</head>
               <p>Page 14. l. 28. for <hi>Scriptures</hi> r. <hi>Scripture,</hi> p. 38. l. 15. for <hi>pretatum</hi> r. <hi>praelatum,</hi> p. 44. l. 20. in ſome Copies, for <hi>perfecta exiſtent</hi> r. <hi>profecta exſtent,</hi> and l. 22. for <hi>Edeſus</hi> r. <hi>Edeſius,</hi> p. 68. l. 12. for 13 r. 14. p. 80. l. 27. for <hi>equi</hi> r. <hi>aequi,</hi> p. 91. l. 16. add <hi>it.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:107190:25"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 THES. 5.21.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Prove all things.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the preceding <hi>Verſe</hi> the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle diſſwades the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> from <hi>deſpiſing</hi> of <hi>propheſyings.</hi> For the better underſtanding whereof, you are to note, that in the Church of <hi>Theſſalonica</hi> there were two ſorts of perſons, both of which laboured under an unhappy extreme, as to the preaching of the Word, here called <hi>prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſying.</hi> The one through the unskilfulneſs, and vanity of ſome in preaching, took up ſuch a prejudice againſt it, that they deſpiſed all preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. The other being acted by an indiſcreet, miſguided zeal, were ſo far from deſpiſing all preaching, that without any diſcrimination or exception, they allowed and embraced all. We have ſufficient exemplifications hereof amongſt our ſelves; divers from the inſufficiency, and ſcandalouſneſs of ſome that are employed in preaching, take up ſuch a prejudice againſt it,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:107190:26"/>that they turn Seekers, Ranters, Atheiſts, and whatever Satan the common Impoſtor (who is ready to improve all advantages and opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of promoting his own intereſt) will have them to be. Others through a ſtrange credulity and facility, are ſo affected when they ſee men make ſpecious pretences of Piety and Holineſs, and hear them deliver things in the Name of God, with ſeeming zeal and affection, that they preſently conclude whatever they deliver is ſound and good, and worthy their approbation and acceptance. And thus, as the former through a raſh and obſtinate prejudice turn their backs upon the common means of Salvation, ſo theſe through an indiſcreet and prepoſterous zeal run themſelves into miſerable deluſions. Thus it was amongſt the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> ſome cried through prejudice, others through zeal, ſome liked No preaching, others liked all. Now <hi>Paul</hi> being aware of theſe ſad Exorbitancies and Confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, endeavours to reduce and fettle them in a mean betwixt theſe two extreams: He would neither have them to like all, nor diſlike all; neither receive all, nor reject all, but to <hi>prove all,</hi> and then receive what was good, and reject what was bad. The words imply as much as if he had ſaid, My Brethren, I ſee you are va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly affected towards preaching: ſome out of prejudice undervalue it, others out of zeal over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>value it; ſome ſo deſpiſe it that they will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive nothing, others ſo affect it that they will receive anything. Now there is danger in both theſe; the one leads to Atheiſm, the other to Error: let it be your care therefore to avoid
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:107190:26"/>both. See that you neither contemptuouſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe all, nor credulouſly receive all, but like prudent and ſober Chriſtians, bring all to the common Standard of the Word, prove it there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, and what you find contrary to it, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand and reject, and what you finde agreeable to it, that allow and follow.</p>
            <p>Having thus briefly given you an account of the occaſion of the Words, I ſhall, as the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>theſis</hi> I intend to inſiſt on, and make out to you, raiſe from them this Obſervation:</p>
            <q>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> That it is the duty of Chriſtians to prove all thoſe things, which in the diſpenſation of the Goſpel are delivered to them.</q>
            <p>Though it be reaſonable, that they ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Miniſters of Chriſt, and entertain them with reſpect anſwerable to the authority they are ſent by, and the nature of the Meſſage they bring along with them, yet they muſt not look upon them as infallible, but as ſubject to errors and miſtakes, and therefore muſt hear them with judgement and caution. Though they be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo able, pious, conſcientious, uſefull in the Church, dear to them, yet they muſt not take what they deliver upon their credit, or autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, but muſt bring it to the Word, and make proof of it thereby. This courſe God hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed as the means both of their ſatisfaction and ſafety, and therefore they muſt neither upon one account nor other neglect it, but with all care and faithfulneſs cloſe with it and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low it.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:107190:27"/>
            <p>The <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Writers tell us,<note place="margin">Perk. Aboth. <hi>cap. 5.</hi>
               </note> there ſate at the feet of their <hi>Rabbi's</hi> four ſorts of Hearers; ſome of which had <hi>conditionem Spongiae,</hi> others <hi>Clepſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drae,</hi> others <hi>ſacci foecinacei,</hi> and others <hi>Cribri.</hi> Some were like to a <hi>Sponge</hi> ſucking in all they heard, without any diſcretion or diſtinction: Others were like the <hi>Hour-glaſs,</hi> letting out at one ear, what they took in at the other; others were like the <hi>Wine-ſack</hi> letting out the Wine, and keeping in the dreggs. And others were like the <hi>rieing ſieve,</hi> letting out the courſer ſeed, and keeping in the Corn. Of which four ſorts the laſt is only to be approved of; for we muſt neither receive all, nor let go all, neither retain that which is bad, nor let go that which is good, but judging all, we muſt retain that which is good, and let go that which is bad, which is the very thing the Apoſtle aims at here, when he ſaith, <hi>prove all things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the more methodical proſecuting of this point, I ſhall branch it forth into ſeveral parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, which I ſhall explicate and diſcuſs by themſelves; and I ſhall ſhew,</p>
            <p n="1">1. What is meant by <hi>proving.</hi> The Scripture mentions two kindes of <hi>proving,</hi> the one belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to God as the Efficient, the other unto man. It is only the latter of them that I have now to to deal with; and of it we have three ſorts. 1. Such as imports the <hi>demonſtration,</hi> or <hi>confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> of a matter in queſtion. And this kind of proving <hi>Paul</hi> uſed when he <hi>ſhewed by the Scriptures that Jeſus was Chriſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 18.28</note> Though he were an Apoſtle, a man of rare abilities, and ſingular faithfulneſs, yet he thought it not ſufficient
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:107190:27"/>barely to aſſert the authority of Chriſt, but he betakes himſelf to the Scripture, and from thence he fetches arguments whereby he clearly and unanſwerably proves him to be the Meſſias. 2. Such as imports <hi>approbation</hi> and <hi>allowance.</hi> And this kinde of proving <hi>Paul</hi> would have the <hi>Corinthians</hi> to uſe in the choice of the Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 16.3.</note> whom they were to intruſt with the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of the Contributions, which they were to make towards the relief of their diſtreſſed Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren at <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> That they might not throw away by their indiſcretion, what they gathered by their Charity, he wills them to deliver it into the hands of ſuch as upon mature conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, they ſhould approve of, as fit for the undertaking and management of ſuch a Charge. But it is not either of theſe kindes of proving that he means when he injoyns the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> to <hi>prove all things;</hi> for as he never intended to put them upon the making good of all things delivered to them, ſo neither was it his minde that they ſhould approve or allow of them, but that they ſhould upon a fair and equal weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them, have liberty to take what was good, and leave what was bad. 3. Such as imports <hi>examination</hi> and <hi>tryall.</hi> And this kind of proving it is that <hi>Paul</hi> means, when he ſaith, <hi>prove all things.</hi> He would not have men to blindfold or hoodwinck themſelves, or ſit down under a lazy, implicit Faith, cloſing with things meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon the credit of their Leaders, but to make uſe of their eyes, and by due proof ſatisfie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of the lawfulneſs of them before they enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain them. The word in the original is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:107190:28"/>which imports ſuch a kind of proving as a man makes uſe of, when he inquires and ſearches in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a thing to finde out the nature of it. The Holy Ghoſt ſometimes uſes it as <hi>Verbum juridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum,</hi> nothing the proceſs of ſuch as are in Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, in trying of <hi>Candidates,</hi> or ſuch as are to be choſen into places of truſt, whether they are fit for them. Thus <hi>Paul,</hi> who is very frequent in the uſe of the word, ſpeaking to <hi>Timothy,</hi> concerning <hi>Deacons,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 3.10.</note> ſaith <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>they muſt firſt be proved.</hi> He would not have him to receive into Church Offices all ſuch as ſhould think themſelves fit, but whom he himſelf upon due examination and tryall ſhould think fit. Sometimes he uſes it as <hi>Verbum aurificum,</hi> noting the method of Goldſmiths, whoſe manner is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to prove and try their Gold, both by the Fire and the Touch-ſtone, that ſo they may diſcover the nature and value of it. One while they bring it to the Fire, and thereby finde out the droſs; another while to the Touch-ſtone, and ſo diſcover what is counterfeit. And this kinde of prudent circumſpection and caution, the Apoſtle would have the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> and all Chriſtians to uſe in matters of Religion. He would not have them to take things upon truſt, to think that all is gold that gliſters, that all is ſound that is recommended to them as ſuch, or that at the firſt view ſeems to be ſuch, but he would have them to bring it to the Fire and Touch-ſtone of the ſacred and unerring Word, and then cloſe with it or reject it ſo far as upon due tryall they ſhall finde cauſe.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:107190:28"/>
            <p n="2">2. What thoſe things be which are to be <hi>proved;</hi> and thoſe are <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>all things</hi> whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever. For though that which the Apoſtle here delivers were occaſioned by the contemptuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſome, and the credulity of others among the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> towards preaching, yet his words are univerſal and general, and therefore (there being the ſame reaſon for proving of other things, as well as preaching) they are not to be look'd upon as referring only unto preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but as extending unto all other wayes, whereby Teachers may recommend any thing to their people, for their belief and practice: which way ſoever it is that they deal with them, whatſoever it is that they deliver to them, they muſt make proof of it ere they embrace it. They muſt prove the Faith they would have them to profeſs, the Worſhip they would have them to obſerve, the Diſcipline they would have them to cloſe with, the courſe of life they would have them to follow, with all the particular Doctrines they would have them aſſent to, and the ſeveral Duties they would have them per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> would perſwade us,<note place="margin">t. <hi>3.</hi> de Verb. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> that the Apoſtle by <hi>all things</hi> intends only <hi>doctrinam du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biam,</hi> ſuch Doctrine as is doubtfull and uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain; which he would have us to think the Doctrine of lawfull Paſtors is not, but <hi>apertè bona, manifeſtly good.</hi> Anſw. 1. Did ever man, that knew what the terms, Doctrine, and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor, meant, aſſert a groſſer untruth? Is all the Doctrine of lawfull Paſtors good, and manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly good? What did he think of the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees?</hi> did he not teach a little before,<note place="margin">l. 3. <hi>c.</hi> 5.</note> that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:107190:29"/>they were lawfull Paſtors?<note place="margin">l. 3. <hi>c.</hi> 5.</note> And was all their Doctrine good, and manifeſtly good? Do's not our Saviour the ableſt in the World to judge, lay it to their charge, that they made <hi>the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment of God of none effect by it?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 15.6.</note> Or what did he think of the Antients, whoſe authority he do's upon all occaſions urge us with? were not they lawfull Paſtors? And yet do they not teach many errors? Do they not frequently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict one another, nay themſelves? Nay, what did he think of many of his own Writers of greateſt credit and eſteem? were not they lawfull Paſtors? And yet hath not Dr. <hi>Morton</hi> in his <hi>Appeal,</hi> produced multitudes of clear teſtimonies out of them, for almoſt every point we main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain againſt the Church of <hi>Rome?</hi> Nay, do's not <hi>Bellarmine</hi> himſelf, ever and anon, after he hath recited their opinions, reject them as erroneous and unſound? 2. It is no new thing for law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Paſtors to degenerate into Hereticks, and oppoſe thoſe Truths that formerly they have aſſerted and defended. What would he have ſaid to <hi>Arrius, Macedonius, Neſtorius, Eutiches?</hi> Were not they lawfull Paſtors, and yet did they not fall into blaſphemous and dangerous here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, and with both zeal and confidence preach the ſame? Now when they preached them, was their Doctrine good and manifeſtly good, and ſuch as the people ought to receive without any ſcruple or cenſure? If ſo, then it was their duty to blaſpheme God, overthrow Religion, and undo themſelves and others. And thus you ſee whither theſe Principles lead, and what it is to caſt your ſelves upon the fincerity of men, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:107190:29"/>reſt upon their authority. It expoſes to no leſs than the danger of blaſphemy, ruine and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion. To ſecure us from which, God hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded this remedy, that we ſhould not <hi>caecâ fide,</hi> take things upon truſt, but bring them to trial, and thereby inform our ſelves of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of them. This every man ought to do, and this every good mand does do; for as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaith, <hi>He that is ſpiritual judgeth all things.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.15.</note> Whiles <hi>natural</hi> men, that is, carnal, unregenerate ones, who are blind, and cannot diſcern; and careleſs, and will not diſcern, make no diſtinction of things, but turning their ſouls into ſo many im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure ſinks, receive all that comes, whether good or bad, he who is <hi>ſpiritual,</hi> that is, he who is acted, inlightned and ſanctified by the Spirit, and minds and lives upon ſpiritual things, takes another courſe: he neither receives all, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects all, but as the Apoſtle ſaith, he <hi>judgeth</hi> all, and then receives what is good, and rejects what is bad.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Who they be that are to prove all things; and thoſe are all Chriſtians, every one that is a member of the Church, every one that hears the Goſpel preached, nay, every one that would not fall into thoſe deluſions that attend implicit faith and blind obedience. It does not onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to Governours, whether Civil or Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical, Supreme or Subordinate; but unto all perſons whatſoever that would ſecure themſelves againſt errour and deſtruction. For the Apoſtle does not in this place direct his diſcourſe to Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours onely in the Church of <hi>Theſsalonica,</hi> either of one ſort or other; but to all the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:107190:30"/>thereof without any exception, willing every of them, as they tendered their own ſafety, to perform this neceſſary and important duty of Chriſtian trial.<note place="margin">l. <hi>3.</hi> de verb. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Bellarmine</hi> indeed, that he may the better evade the force of this place, tells us that when <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>prove all things,</hi> he meant not, <hi>ut omnes de eccleſia id faciant, that all in the Church ſhould do it, but that thoſe ſhould do it to whom it belong'd:</hi> As if one ſhould write to an Univerſity to examine ſuch a book, it were not to be thought it were intended that every one in the Univerſity ſhould do it, but onely the Doctors of that faculty whereof the Book treats. But this is a frivolous ſhift; for 1. The Apoſtle does not direct his Epiſtle to the Paſtors of the Church of <hi>Theſſalonica,</hi> but the Church there, whom, without any exceptions or limitations, he adviſes to this duty, which is a plain evidence that he intended it rather for the People than the Paſtors. For though I grant, that by the word <hi>Church</hi> in Scripture, we are ſometimes to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Paſtors thereof, duly aſſembled, for the determining of the differences that lie before them; yet we do not find that any of the Epiſtles, the Apoſtle directed to the ſeveral Churches to whom he wrote, were intended peculiarly for the Paſtors, but that belonged to the People equally with them. 2. The whole ſcope and matter of the Epiſtle (which no doubt he ſuited to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, whoſe inſtruction and uſe he intended in it) do equally concern the People with the Paſtors. Do but peruſe his Salutations, Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations, Narratives, Doctrine, Exhortations, Thankſgivings, and you ſhall find, they are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodated
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:107190:30"/>to the People as well as the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors; nay, rather to the People than them. Nay, 3. The Apoſtle, as if he had, <hi>de induſtriâ,</hi> deſign'd the anticipating of ſuch an objection, and made it his buſineſs to aſſure us, that he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended the People as well as the Paſtors in this precept, as alſo in thoſe prefixed and annexed to it, does in the 12 and 13 <hi>verſes</hi> openly addreſs himſelf to them: <hi>We beſeech you,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>brethren, to know them which labour among you, and are over you in the Lord, and admoniſh you, and to eſteem them very highly in love for their works ſake.</hi> Here certainly, if he underſtood what he ſaid, he meant not the Paſtors but the People. 4. As if all this were not ſufficient, he uſhers in the words of the Text with a precept, that does principally, if not onely, concern the people, which he prefixes immediately before them, <hi>Deſpiſe not propheſyings;</hi> whereunto, as an anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dote againſt running into the extremes before mentioned, he ſubjoyns, <hi>prove all things.</hi> Now what reaſon can be rendred, wherefore the former precept (as well as thoſe which go before and follow after) ſhould belong to the People and not this, all the while it hath nothing in its own nature, but what is proper and agreeable to their ſtate? none at all. And therefore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting this and ſuch like vain cavils, ſuiting neither with the deſign of the Spirit of God, nor the ſafety of Religion, we are to look upon this duty as belonging, not onely unto Paſtors, but likewiſe the people, who by virtue thereof ſtand bound to prove what is delivered to them as well as they.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:107190:31"/>
            <p n="4">4. What it is by which all things muſt be <hi>proved.</hi> In all rational and orderly trials there is ſtill ſomething ſuppoſed, to which we reduce what we are trying, and if we find it agreeable thereunto, we approve of it; if not, we reject it. And we muſt of neceſſity take this courſe, for it is impoſſible that we ſhould ever bring any trial to a fair iſſue, until we agree upon ſome common rule to proceed by. To ingage in a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate without premiſing certain <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon principles,</hi> acknowledged on all ſides, as the meaſure thereof, is to follow an <hi>ignis fatuus,</hi> run after our own ſhadows, and create to our ſelves fruitleſs as well as endleſs trouble. Since therefore it is the duty of every one to try what comes before him, and that there muſt of neceſſity be ſome rule to proceed by, I ſhall in the next place enquire what this rule is, by which we muſt make this trial; and we need not to go far to learn tydings of it,<note place="margin">Rom. 10.6.</note> we need neither to <hi>aſcend into heaven,</hi> nor <hi>deſcend into the deep;</hi> for <hi>it is nigh</hi> us, <hi>even in</hi> our <hi>mouthes, and in</hi> our <hi>hearts.</hi> It is, in plain terms, none other than the word of God, contained in the writings of the Prophets and Apoſtles, to which he hath directed us to have recourſe upon all occaſions, as the infallible mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of truth and falſhood,<note place="margin">Iſa. 8.20.</note> good and evil. <hi>To the law and the teſtimony,</hi> (ſaith the Prophet) <hi>if they ſpeak not according to this word, it is becauſe there is no light in them.</hi> In which he plainly ſhews whither we muſt go with our doubts and ſcruples, with whom we muſt conſult, and of whom we muſt take advice: not of <hi>them that have familiar ſpirits,</hi> not of <hi>wizards that peep and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:107190:31"/>mutter;</hi> but of <hi>the law and the teſtimony.</hi> There is all the reaſon imaginable, that he who made the world ſhould rule and govern it, and that in order thereunto he ſhould give forth Laws con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining his ſovereign will and pleaſure, touching the obedience and ſervice he expects from his creatures; and this he hath fully done in his word, whereby he hath guided his Church all along from firſt to laſt, though with ſome varia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ever ſince ſhe had a being. Before the fall, he guided her by it according as he had writ it in mans heart; from the fall to <hi>Moſes,</hi> according as he was pleaſed to grant it forth and renew it by occaſional revelations; and from <hi>Moſes</hi> till this time, according as he hath, by his own Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretaries, ſet it down in the holy Scriptures, with which he will have us in all caſes to conſult, and to which we muſt conſtantly cleave, without warping or turning aſide either one way or other. And hither it was that our Saviour, the Prophets, Apoſtles and Paſtors of the antient Church, upon all occaſions betook themſelves; hereby it was that they taught the Doctrin of ſalvation, defended the truth, refuted error, eſtabliſhed the weak, convinced gain-ſayers, and ſet up the Kingdom of God in the world. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it was that <hi>they ſubdued kingdoms,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11.33</note> 
               <hi>wrought righteouſneſs, ſtopped the mouthes of Lions, out of weakneſs were made ſtrong, waxed valiant in fight, and turned to flight the armies of aliens. Clemens</hi> of <hi>Alexandria</hi> ſpeaking of the word, ſaith, it is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Strom. l. <hi>7.</hi> ad fin.</note> 
               <hi>the touchſtone of truth and falſhood.</hi> So it is in it ſelf, and ſo in the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive and purer times it was ever eſteemed.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:107190:32"/>
               <hi>Theodoret</hi> tells of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Inſt. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> that he would have the Fathers in the Council of <hi>Nice</hi> to take the reſolution of things in queſtion, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>out of the divinely inſpired writings.</hi> He would not have them to truſt to their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, learning, judgment, or any ſuch uncertain thing, but to the Scriptures, which he look'd upon as fitteſt to decide all controverſies in Religion. And they readily complied with him, laid the Scriptures before them, ſearched them, and determined all by them. There was then no ſuch crying up of Traditions, appealing to the authority of the Church, and enquiring after the Oracles of the <hi>Porphyry</hi> Chair, as later ages have been acquainted with; but they contented themſelves with the lamp of the Word, ſteered their courſe by it, and fram'd all according to it. And the ſame method they uſed in ſucceeding Councils; when ever they aſſembled for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciding of any controverſie, they ſtill brought the Bible along with them, and reverently laid it before them, as the onely authentick rule where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they were to judge of the matters they had in hand. And thus we muſt do, hither we muſt bring whatſoever is tendred to us to be believed, obſerved or done. Anſwerable hereunto is that which we find contained in the Confeſſion of the Church of <hi>England,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Corp. conf. p. <hi>93.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The Canonical Scriptures</hi> (ſay they) <hi>is the certain rule, ad quam omnis doctrina Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtica debet revocari, to which all eccleſiaſtical doctrin ought to be reduced; againſt them neither Law, Tradition or Cuſtom is to be heard.</hi> Hither it is that we muſt bring, not onely the Doctrine of ſingle Paſtors, but the Decrees of Councils,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:107190:32"/>and the Determinations of Kings and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, how wiſe or juſt ſoever they are. Though they be high, and upon that account are to have honour and obedience, yet there is one that is <hi>higher than they,</hi> whoſe Authority and Laws we muſt prefer before all Authority and Laws what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever; otherwiſe we ſhould violate our alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance, and forfeit our ſouls into the hands of Juſtice. To be ſhort, the Word is that whereby we muſt try and judge all, and whereby we muſt rate and value every thing that is preſented to us, neither condemning any thing it allows, nor allowing any thing it condemns, but eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of every thing according to the judgment and ſentence thereof. Herein we have the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frage of ſome of our adverſaries themſelves. <hi>Menaſſes Ben Iſrael</hi> ſaw ſo much, that he ſaid, <hi>All writings are true or falſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De fragilit. hum. p. <hi>109.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>quatenus conveniunt cum divinis literis aut ab iiſdem diſcrepant, ſo far as they agree with the holy Scriptures, or differ from them.</hi> And <hi>Andreas Friccius Modrevius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">l. <hi>4</hi> de Eccl. c. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> a Popiſh Author, writes to the ſame purpoſe, <hi>All thoſe things</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>are to be examined, ad ſcripturas divinas, by the holy Scriptures, that are to be ratified and eſtabliſhed in the Church of God.</hi> Had all Jews and Papiſts kept cloſe to the profeſſion and practice of this Doctrine, they had not fallen into that lamentable apoſtaſie that they lie under the guilt of at this day, to the draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down of the juſt diſpleaſure of God upon them, and the occaſioning the Church of Chriſt to ſeparate from them.</p>
            <p n="5">5. How, or after what manner we muſt prove all things. For the better underſtanding of this,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:107190:33"/>we muſt note, that unto a regular and fair tryal, ſome things are neceſſary as <hi>antecedents,</hi> others as <hi>concomitants,</hi> and others as <hi>conſequents;</hi> to each of which I ſhall ſpeak ſomewhat, taking them in order.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Unto a due tryall, ſome things are neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry as <hi>antecedents,</hi> or Preparatives, ſerving to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and make way for a ſucceſsfull management of the work. And,</p>
            <p n="1">1. We muſt humble our ſelves before God, under the ſenſe of our great darkneſs, ignorance, and folly, unfeignedly lamenting the loſs of that light, knowledge, and wiſdom we had by our Creation, confeſſing with much ſorrow and brokenneſs of heart that we have thereby ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered our ſelves altogether unworthy to come to the knowledge of the truth. When <hi>John</hi> ſaw there was no one found worthy to <hi>open</hi> and <hi>read</hi> the little Book,<note place="margin">Rov. 5.4.</note> or <hi>look</hi> therein, <hi>he wept much.</hi> It is a ſad thing to be ignorant of the will of God: It is ſinfull, uncomfortable and dangerous, and therefore we ſhould humble our ſelves under the ſenſe of it, abhorring and deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing our ſelves, that we have ſinn'd away our light, and thereby made our ſelves ſtrangers to what we were once acquainted with. One of the firſt things a man is to do in order to the obtaining of true wiſdom, is to acknowledge his own folly.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.18.</note> Hence that of the Apoſtle, <hi>if any man among you ſeemeth to be wiſe in this world, let him become a fool, that he may be wiſe.</hi> Not that he muſt give over the uſe of his Reaſon, or utterly renounce what he knows, but he muſt look upon himſelf as imperfect, and ſhort of thoſe
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:107190:33"/>attainments he ſhould arrive to; which do's much towards the preparing of him for further growth. <hi>Epict. Arrianus</hi> writes an intire <hi>chapter</hi> of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of <hi>Philoſophy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 11. <hi>p.</hi> 154.</note> and ſhews that the firſt thing a man is to do in order to his becoming a <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher,</hi> is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or, <hi>the conſideration of his own inſufficiency and weakneſs.</hi> As long as a man conceits he knows enough, hee'll care little for knowing more. Many had found out the Truth, if they had not flattered themſelves with vain apprehenſions of being already poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of it. I ſpeak not this, as if I would have all turn <hi>Scepticks,</hi> or give up themſelves to irrational and groundleſs doubtings, the common Engines whereby Satan draws men to error and apoſtacy, but that they ſhould underſtand their own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, remember from whence they are fallen, conſider what imperfections do attend them, humble themſelves before God, and mourn un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſenſe thereof, which is the way to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der God propitious, and prevail with him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal his minde to us. Though he be willing to teach, yet before he do's it, hee'll have us to be ſenſible both that he is able to teach us, and that we ſtand in need of being taught, and when we are thus qualified, we are fit to enter into his School, and not till then. If we mean to find out the truth, we muſt not uſher in our en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiries after it, with high ſelf-admiring thoughts, but throwing our ſelves down at the feet of that Majeſty we have offended, we muſt look upon our ſelves as empty, fooliſh Creatures, wholly unfit to be acquainted, or have to do, with Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred things. And to encourage us hereunto,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:107190:34"/>God tells us,<note place="margin">Pſ. 25.9.</note> that <hi>the meek will he guide in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the meek will he teach his way.</hi> Such is the reſpect that he bears to meek and humble men, that he hath promiſed when they ſit in Judgement on ſuch things as come before them, he will guide and aſſiſt them, that ſo they may not paſs an unjuſt ſentence, but ſuch as is according to truth. While he ſuffers the proud and haughty to follow their own imaginations and deluſions, he will direct them in judging, and inſtruct and teach them the way they are to go.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We muſt addreſs our ſelves unto God in Prayer, and with all holy importunity and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſs intreat him to aſſiſt us in the buſineſs we have in hand, reveal his minde to us, and help us to cloſe therewith. Though we have all outward advantages of finding out the truth, yet unleſs he be pleaſed to open our eyes, and ſhew us the evidence and beauty of it, we are never the nearer. The doctrine of Religion is attended with ſo many abſtruſe and ſtupendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous myſteries, that its beyond the ability of any mortal man, without the direction of ſuperve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient, auxiliary light to underſtand it. This our Saviour teaches when he ſaith,<note place="margin">Joh. 3.19.</note> 
               <hi>No man hath aſcended up to Heaven, but he that came down from Heaven.</hi> By <hi>aſcending</hi> into Heaven he means, not a going up thither in a proper ſenſe, but a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect underſtanding of heavenly myſteries, which no man how great ſoever his perſpicacity or dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence was,<note place="margin">Com. in loc.</note> did ever fully attain unto. And with this agrees that of the <hi>judicious Calvin, aſcending into Heaven</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſignifies, puram myſteriorum Dei notitiam, &amp; ſpiritualis intelligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:107190:34"/>lucem, the pure knowledge of the myſteries of God, and the light of ſpiritual underſtanding.</hi> Upon our Saviours aſſerting to <hi>Nicodemus</hi> the neceſſity of Regeneration (a myſtery he underſtood not) he breaks forth into audacious and arrogant ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtulations with him, demanding of him, <hi>How can a man be born when he is old? can he outer the ſecond time into his mothers womb? and how can theſe things be?</hi> He pretended to come to him as unto <hi>a Teacher ſent from God,</hi> attended with his preſence, and able to demonſtrate the truth of his Doctrine by Miracles, and yet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of ſubmitting to his authority and wiſdom, as he ought to have done, he thus proudly and vainly reaſons with him, behaving himſelf as if he thought nothing could be truth but what he apprehended to be ſo. And thus while he ſeems to contradict our Saviours Doctrine, he unawares verifies it, declaring to us by his own example, that the greateſt Maſters of Learning are unable to receive the things of the Spirit of God, till he help them to do it.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Com. in</hi> Luk. 14.</note> 
               <hi>Theophilact</hi> ſpeaking of the Carnal man, ſaith, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>he believes nothing above Nature.</hi> He meaſures the arm of the Creator by the arm of the Creature, the abilities of Divine Power by the abilities of Nature, and what will over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>match the latter, he thinks will alſo overmatch the former. And after this manner <hi>Nicodemus</hi> (who, one would have thought, being a Maſter of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſhould have known better) carryed himſelf: Though he acknowledge our Saviour to be come from God, yet he will not take his word. He muſt either know how and by what
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:107190:35"/>means, a man ſhould be born again, or elſe he will not believe there can be any ſuch thing. Now our Saviour the better to repreſs this his vain and fooliſh arrogancy, and thereby make way for his own Doctrine, acquaints him with the utter inability of men by their own power to underſtand Heavenly Truths, and withall lets him know it was his Prerogative who came down from Heaven, and at that time in reſpect of his Divine Nature, was in Heaven to do it. It is as eaſie for a man in a proper ſenſe to climbe up to Heaven, as by his own power fully and ſavingly to underſtand the Doctrine of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. Now this conſideration, as it was a proper antidote for the ſelf-conceitedneſs of <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>codemus,</hi> ſo it may ſerve as a ſtrong argument unto us, both to humble us under the ſenſe of our inſufficiency, and alſo ſtirre us up to ſeek unto him who is able to relieve us. As we muſt not judge our ſelves ſufficient to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand heavenly truths, ſo neither muſt we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent our ſelves with our own inſufficiency, but we muſt ſeek unto him for direction and help. This courſe <hi>David</hi> took,<note place="margin">Pſ. 119.18.</note> 
               <hi>Open thou mine eyes</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that I may behold wonderous things out of thy Law.</hi> Though he were a man of eminent knowledge, wiſer than his Teachers, yet he was ſenſible of his own imperfection, and runs to God for a ſupply thereof. And this courſe like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the Apoſtles took; when ever our Saviour delivered any thing that exceeded their capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, they intreated him to expound it to them. <hi>Declare unto us</hi> (ſay they) <hi>the Parable of the tares of the field.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 13.36.</note> And when he had ſhewed them what
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:107190:35"/>defiles a man, they deſired him to tell them the meaning of it, ſaying,<note place="margin">Mat. 7.17.</note> 
               <hi>declare unto us this Parable.</hi> And when he had ſpoken to them of the deſtruction of the Temple, they came to him privately, ſaying, <hi>Tell us when ſhall theſe things be.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 24.3.</note> And the ſame courſe they took themſelves, the ſame they preſcribed unto others. <hi>If any of you</hi> (ſaith one of them) <hi>lack Wiſdom,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jam. 1.5.</note> 
               <hi>let him ask it of God, that giveth to all men liberally, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braideth not; and it ſhall be given him.</hi> Though we want Wiſdom, there is enough in God: he is the Father of Lights, the only wiſe God, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite in underſtanding; and he is ready to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate to his Creatures. As the Sun offers its light unto the World, ſo do's he offer his aſſiſtance to us; and therefore we ſhould neither allow our ſelves in darkneſs, nor ſtand complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it, but run to him for light. Whenever we find our ſelves at a loſs, we muſt run pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently to him, and deſire him to enlighten our darkneſs, reſolve our doubts, and make our way plain for us. When men urge upon us New Doctrines and Canons, we muſt take them as <hi>Hezekiah</hi> did <hi>Rabſhakeh</hi>'s Letter, and laying them before the Lord, ſay, <hi>Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 37.14.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall we believe or ſhall we not believe? ſhall we obey or ſhall we not obey? ſince thou wouldſt not have us erre, keep us that we may not do it.</hi> Such behaviour will both pleaſe him, and conduce to our own ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. <hi>Calvin</hi> writing upon the Text hath this paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage. <hi>If</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>we perceive our ſelves to be deſtitute of the faculty of proving aright, ab eodem ſpiritu qui per Prophetas ſuos loquitur petenda eſt, we muſt beg it of the ſame ſpirit which ſpeaketh by
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:107190:36"/>the Prophets.</hi> He is the author and Fountaion of Truth, and is only able to open the eyes to ſee it, and perſwade the heart to cloſe with it, and therefore it concerns us and all thoſe who be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous of it to ſeek to him for it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. We muſt lay aſide and baniſh from us all prejudice, which way ſoever it hath been occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned, reſolving freely cloſe with whatſoever God ſhall make out to be truth to us. We muſt not bring our Religion to the Scriptures, but receive it from them. We muſt not, as moſt do, firſt take up ſuch opinions, as our own intereſts ſhape out to us, and then bring them to the Scriptures, rather to confirm than examine them thingking then as ſimple people do of the Bells, that whatever they ſay, is for us, but diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging and ſtripping our ſelves naked of all prejudicate apprehenſions and opinions, we muſt go to the Scriptures, with mindes ready to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace whatever God ſhall thereby reveal to us, reſolving with <hi>Micaiah</hi> that <hi>what the Lord ſaith unto us,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kings 22.14.</note> that we will cloſe with, being equally content to follow his voice which way ſoever he ſhall call us. Prejudice is a prepoſterous judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment whereby we paſs ſentence upon things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we have duely inform'd our ſelves con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning them, and ſo come to approve what we ſhould condemn, and condemn what we ſhould approve.<note place="margin">Ad frat. in Erem.</note> 
               <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, it is <hi>inauditi addictio, the condemning of a perſon or thing unheard.</hi> Now this we muſt by all means beware of; we muſt neither approve nor condemn things before we hear them, but we muſt grant them a fair try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, and then deal with them as we ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:107190:36"/>finde cauſe. We muſt neither judge perſons nor things, <hi>indictâ causâ,</hi> before we have heard them: that was not only diſallowed,<note place="margin">Joh. 7.51.</note> as <hi>Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demus</hi> ſhews, among the <hi>Jews,</hi> but likewiſe, as <hi>Tully</hi> ſhews, among the <hi>Romans,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Orat. pro Cluent.</note> who puniſhed ſuch as they found duilty of it. Though what we have before us be a truth, yet we ſin, if we cloſe with it, ere we have made tryall of it. The Judge that paſſes ſentence before he hath heard both parties, arrs, though his ſentence be in it ſelf juſt, becauſe through his prepoſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſneſs it might have proved otherwiſe. And ſo it is in this caſe; he that takes up an opinion, before he hath made proof of it, errs, though it be in it ſelf good, becauſe through his inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derateneſs and raſhneſs it might have proved evil. It is not enough that we take up the Truth, except we take it up upon mature con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, and good grounds, ſufficient in their kinde to ſatisfie us that it is the Truth, which we have before us. But ſuch is the indiſcretion and raſhneſs of moſt, that they eſpouſe Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and wayes, and are ready to perſecute all that will not joyn with them therein, before they have made any tryall of them, or can give any rational grounds for their ſo doing. Thus did the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Epheſians;</hi> they were both full of heat and rage;<note place="margin">Luk 23.23. Acts 19.32</note> the former againſt Chriſt, the latter againſt his Servants, but neither of them knew why. And there are more than a few of ſuch as theſe amongſt us, who have <hi>a zeal, but not according to knowledge.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 10.2</note> They are very forward in their way, but can render little more reaſon for it, than they can for the ebbing
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:107190:37"/>and flowing of the Sea at its appointed times. Perhaps they can alledge ſuch things as education, cuſtom, carnal intereſt, the example of the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, the command of Superiours; but alas, what uncertain ſilly things are theſe for men to build their Religion upon?<note place="margin">Pſal. 62.9.</note> 
               <hi>To be laid inthe bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance they are altogether lighter than vanity.</hi> Now for the preventing of the may evils attending on this precipitant courſe, it behoves us to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, what opinions we like and what we diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, and upon what grounds we like the one and diſlike the other; and if opon enquiry we find, that we have through prejudice, that is to ſay, immature haſty judgment, or otherwiſe, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up al liking of what we ſhould diſlike, or a diſliking of what we ſhould like, we muſt not onely, for the repairing of the honour of the truth, which we have ſinfully violated, but alſo for our own ſafety, return again, and ſteer a new courſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Having thus ſpoken of ſuch matters as are neceſſary to this proof of things as <hi>antecedents,</hi> or preparatives, I ſhall now ſpeak of ſuch as are neceſſary, as <hi>concomitants</hi> or adjuncts. And,</p>
            <p n="1">1. We muſt prove them carefully, as things that concern our ſouls, and everlaſting happineſs, and wherein we cannot miſtake without danger of utter ruine. We muſt not run over the work heedleſy and ſlightly, (that's the way to favour errour and wrong the truth in as much as we are by nature prone to the former, and averſe to the latter) but we muſt manage it with all holy circumſpection and caution, as thoſe who are indeed zealous of the truth, and deſirous to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:107190:37"/>find it out. We read, <hi>Numb.</hi> 9.8. that when certain men came to <hi>Moſes</hi> for reſolution in a caſe, he was ſo cautious, that though it were but a buſineſs of a <hi>ceremonial</hi> nature, yet he would not preſently give judgment in it, but he firſt goes and <hi>enquires of the Lord</hi> concerning it. And ſome of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Writers tell us,<note place="margin">Jonath. Targ. in loc.</note> that there were four ſorts of cauſes that came before <hi>Moſes,</hi> two of which were of leſs moment, the other of greater; in the former he haſtned, in the later he delaid; but both concerning the one and the other he ſaid, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>I have not heard,</hi> namely, from the Lord, teaching us thereby, that deliberation and conſultation with God, ought to be uſed in all matters before ſentence be given. In our enquiries after the nature of thoſe things which come before us, we muſt not,<note place="margin">Joh. 18.38. Luk. 2.48. Heb. 12.17.</note> with <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late,</hi> careleſly demand, <hi>what is truth,</hi> and ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs the work; but we muſt ſeek it as <hi>Joſeph</hi> and <hi>Mary</hi> did Chriſt, and as <hi>Eſau</hi> did the bleſſing, with <hi>care, ſorrow</hi> and <hi>tears.</hi> As it is no ſmall bleſſing to find the truth, ſo it is no ſmall judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to miſs of it, and therefore it concerns us to uſe care in our enquiries after it. Such is our proneneſs to miſtake, that we muſt keep a jealous eye upon our ſelves, and even when our grounds ſeem fair and plauſible, proceed with caution, leſt with <hi>Ixion</hi> we embrace a cloud inſtead of <hi>Junto,</hi> and with <hi>Diomedes,</hi> take up with weapons of braſs for weapons of gold.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We muſt prove them diligently, chooſing rather to be at any pains than remain ignorant of the truth. The <hi>Judicial</hi> Law required, that when the Judges ſate upon their Tribunal, and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:107190:38"/>had a controverſie before them, they ſhould make <hi>diligent inquiſition.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 19.18.</note> They were not to run over the buſineſs ſuperficially or negligently, but to make thorow enquiry into it; and the reaſon was, that they might not give a falſe and groundleſs, but a juſt and equal ſentence. And if it be a duty to make ſuch diligent inquiſition in matters of ſecular and temporal concernment, it is ſurely much more a duty to do it in matters of ſpiritual and eternal concernment. By how much the ſoul is more to be accouted of than the body, and eternity than time, by ſo much we ſhould be more diligent in our enquiry in the latter than the former. And therefore we muſt ſee that we go thorow with the work, not leaving off till we have been at the bottom, know the ſtate of things, and found where the truth lies. This the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> imports, which,<note place="margin">part <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>691.</hi>
               </note> as Dr. <hi>Whitaker</hi> notes, (whoſe <hi>Cygnea Cantio</hi> was on this ſubject) ſignifies ſo to prove as not to deſiſt, till we have found out <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>the thing we are in purſuit of.</hi> God hath preſcribed diligent enquiry after the truth, as the means of finding it, and hath promiſed his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to it:<note place="margin">Prov. 24.5.</note> 
               <hi>If thou ſeekeſt her</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>as ſilver, and ſearcheſt for her as for hid treaſures: then ſhalt thou underſtand the fear of the Lord, and find the knowledge of God.</hi> Such is the excellency of truth, that it is worthy our greateſt diligence, and upon that account we ſhould ſpare no pains in the ſearch of it. The reaſon wherefore it is hid from many, is not becauſe God is unwilling to reveal it, but becauſe they are not diligent in their enquiries after it: would they but take
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:107190:38"/>that pains for it which men do for <hi>ſilver</hi> and <hi>gold,</hi> they might ſoon come to the knowledge of it; but they ſlight it, and are ſlothful in the ſearch of it, and ſo go without it. And indeed its juſt with God to let them ſeek and not find, till they have learn'd to value and ſeek it at another rate. If ever we mean to find the truth, and eſcape the deluſions that others periſh by, we muſt labour and take pains for it, nay, and count our ſelves happy, if in ſo doing we may attain to the knowledge of it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. We muſt prove them faithfully, weighing the evidence on both ſides, and giving ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence according thereunto. We muſt not judge of things according to what our car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal intereſts would have them to be, nor according to what at the firſt ſight they may ſeem to be; but according to what upon due examination and ſearch we ſhall find them. God does every where in Scripture prohibit and condemn partial and unequal judgment, as that which is highly drſpleaſing and hateful to him, witneſs that of <hi>Moſes</hi> to his Judges, <hi>Hear the cauſes between your brethren,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 1.16, 17.</note> 
               <hi>and judge righteouſly between every man, and his brother, and the ſtranger that is with him. Ye ſhall not reſpect perſons in judgment, but ye ſhall hear the ſmall as well as the great: ye ſhall not be afraid of the face of man, for the judgment is gods.</hi> With which agrees that of our Saviour, <hi>Judge not according to the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, but judge righteous judgment.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 7.24.</note> It muſt be our care then that truth may take place, and therefore waving all motives and inducements to the contrary, we muſt give ſentence for it.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:107190:39"/>The <hi>Thebans</hi> painted Juſtice without <hi>hands,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plut. de Iſid.</note> and without <hi>eyes;</hi> teaching by the one, that ſuch as ſate in judgment muſt receive no <hi>bribes;</hi> and by the other, that they muſt not reſpect <hi>perſons.</hi> From whence we who are <hi>Chriſtians</hi> may gather this uſeful inſtruction, That in our judicial pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, whether more publick or private, we muſt not ſuffer any ſiniſter reſpects to ſway or corrupt us, following the free and impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial dictates of our own judgment and reaſon, we muſt give a juſt and equal ſentence. Error hath commonly many advocates to plead for it, as riches, honour, and the like, that like <hi>Galeacius</hi> his children, follow the ſoul with paſſionate and vehement importunity; but ſtopping our ears at the fooliſh blandiſhments and vain ſuggeſtions thereof, we muſt give the truth its deſerved pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminence. We muſt not allow of this opinion, becauſe it wears ſcarlet, nor diſlike that, becauſe it goes in rags. We muſt not cloſe with the one, becauſe it tends to our worldly making, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject the other, becauſe it tends to our undoing; but waving all ſuch trivial conſiderations, as adding nothing to the true and real worth of them, we muſt judge of both according as the light of the word, whereby we are to try them, does repreſent them to us.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Having likewiſe ſpoken of ſuch matters as are neceſſary to the proof of things, as <hi>concomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants</hi> or adjuncts; I ſhall now in the laſt place paſs to ſuch as are neceſſary as <hi>conſequents,</hi> that muſt follow thereupon. And,</p>
            <p n="1">1. When we have made this proof, and have thereby, both according to God's promiſe, and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:107190:39"/>our own deſire and expectation, diſcovered the truth, we muſt bleſs and praiſe him for it, as knowing that without his concurrence and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, our endeavours, how great ſoever, would have been altogether ineffectual. Such is the unhappineſs of ſome, that they do not ſo much as ſeek for truth, and ſo deſervedly remain ſtrangers to it; others ſeek it, but through want of help from Heaven do not find it. What cauſe then ſhall we have to bleſs God, if it ſhall pleaſe him not onely to put us upon the ſeeking it, but by his ſpecial aſſiſtance enable us to find it? It is a mercy to put us upon ſeeking it, but more a mercy in ſeeking it to help us to find it. Oh, truth is a deſirable and ſweet thing, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of our greateſt endeavours <hi>till</hi> we have it, and our higheſt praiſes <hi>when</hi> we have it; witneſs that golden dictate of truth it ſelf;<note place="margin">Prov. 8.35.</note> 
               <hi>Whoſo findeth me findeth life, and ſhall obtain favour from the Lord.</hi> Though ignorant carnal men, that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with nothing but dunghills, ſee no form or comelineſs in it, yet in the judgment of all thoſe, who are worth taking notice of, it is moſt amiable and lovely. Such was the eſteem the <hi>Platoniſt</hi> had of it, that he ſaid, That if Almighty God would be pleas'd to aſſume a compoſition, he verily thought he would take Light for his Body, and Truth for his Soul. It is a fruitful bough, a pearl of great price, a rare bleſſing: and therefore when ever God is pleaſed to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover it to us, we ſhould be thankful for it. Herein our bleſſed <hi>Saviour</hi> hath lead us the way. How thankful was he to his Father for revealing it to his Diſciples? <hi>I thank thee,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>O Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:107190:40"/>
               <hi>Lord of heaven and earth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 11.25.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe thou haſt hid theſe things from the wiſe and prudent, and haſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed them unto babes.</hi> He gives not thanks be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God had hid the myſteries of his Kingdom from the wiſe and prudent, for he would have had all to have been acquainted with them, but that whiles, as a juſt recompence of their pride and contempt, he hid them from them, he was pleaſed out of his great mercy and compaſſion to reveal them unto babes. And if he be thus thankful to his Father for revealing hsi truth to us, how thankful ſhould we be our ſelves? If <hi>Pythagoras</hi> were ſo affected with his finding out the myſtery of the <hi>Triangle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Laert. ejus vit. p. <hi>575.</hi>
               </note> that he did <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſacrifice a whole Hecatomb,</hi> how ſhould we be affected, when God is pleaſed to reveal to us the myſteries of his Kingdom, and make us partakers of that knowledge which leads unto everlaſting lefe?<note place="margin">Theſ. ep. Lect. p. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> Such was the ingenuity of <hi>Eraſtus,</hi> that he proteſted, that whoever would ſhew him his errour, <hi>Coram Deo &amp; hominibus gratias actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, he would give him thanks before God and men.</hi> Truth is the light, glory and ſafety of the foul, that which does direct beautifie and ſecure it: and therefore when ever God is pleaſed to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow it, we ſhould not onely receive it, but ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him thanks for it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. When we have made this proof, and have thereby found out the truth, we muſt faithfully preſerve and retain it, ſuffering neither fraud nor violence to wreſt it from us. Till we have it, it muſt be our care to get it; and when we have it, it muſt be our care to keep it. This the Apoſtle ſhews, when he ſaith, <hi>Hold faſt that which is
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:107190:40"/>good.</hi> In our diſcuſſion of things, we ſhall meet both with gold and droſs, wheat and chaff; and as we muſt let go the one, ſo we muſt retain the other. We may be ſure, that as ſoon as ever we have got the truth,<note place="margin">Matth 13.19.</note> the <hi>wicked one</hi> will be <hi>catching</hi> at it; but we muſt not upon any terms ſuffer him to bereave us of it. Though he ſhould deal with us as he dealt with our Saviour,<note place="margin">Matth. 4.8.</note> offer us <hi>all the kingdoms of the world, and the glory of them</hi> in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change of it, yet we muſt not part with it. We muſt lay it, as <hi>Mary</hi> did the <hi>ſayings</hi> of our Saviour,<note place="margin">Luk. 2.51.</note> in our <hi>hearts,</hi> and not upon any account what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever let it go. This is <hi>Solomon</hi>'s advice,<note place="margin">Prov. 4.13.</note> 
               <hi>Take faſt hold</hi> (ſaith eh) <hi>on inſtruction, let her not go, keep her, for ſhe is thy life.</hi> The life! what more precious than life? what will not a man part with rather than his life? though he love out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward injoyments never ſo well, yet he'l let them all go rather than part with his life. The wary Marriner, that gets what he hath with ſo much toil and hazard, will throw all <hi>into the ſea</hi> to ſave his life. And <hi>Satan</hi> ſpoke no other than truth,<note place="margin">Acts 27.19.</note> when he ſaid, <hi>Skin for skin, and all that a man hath will he give for his life.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 2.4.</note> A man will give the skins, not onely of his cattel and ſervants, but of his own dear children and neareſt relations, to ſave his own. Why, truth is our life, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore according to rules of ſelf-preſervation, which of all other have the deepeſt rooting in nature, we ſhould rather part with any thing than let it go. When God hath once revealed it to us, and committed it to our cuſtody, he looks that we ſhould keep it, and will call us to an account for it; and therefore it concerns us to look to it, and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:107190:41"/>preſerve it. It were far better for us not to have it, than when we have it to let it go. This the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> is clear in.<note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.21.</note> 
               <hi>It had been better for them not to have known the way of righteouſneſs, than after they have known it, to turn from the holy commandment, delivered to them.</hi> The ſin of Apoſtacy is greater than that of bare Infidelity. It is a leſs ſin not to come into <hi>Chriſt,</hi> than after we are come in, to turn our backs upon him and leave him. A man can ſcarcely be born to do Religion greater injury, than for a ſeaſon to profeſs it, and afterwards, forſake it. As it do's highly aggravate his ſin, ſo it will his puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And therefore it concerns every one that hath ſearched for the Truth, and attain'd to it, to hold it faſt, otherwiſe his <hi>latter end</hi> will be <hi>worſe than the beginning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. When we have by our proof found out the Truth, we muſt communicate and reveal it to others, that they being enlightened by it may ſerve God with us, and receive the rich bleſſings that do attend it. When God is pleaſed to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver the Candle of his Word into our hands, it is not that we ſhould <hi>put it under a buſhel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 5.15.</note> 
               <hi>but on a Candleſtick, that it may give light to all that are in the houſe.</hi> When he put light into the Sun, Moon and Stars, it was not that they ſhould ſhine utno themſelves, but that they ſhould enlighten the World; ſo when he reveals his truth to any of his ſervants, it is not that they ſhould impriſon it within the private walls of their own boſoms, but that they ſhould lift it up, and hold it forth to others. One great Office of the Church in relation to the Truth, is to <hi>publiſh it,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:107190:41"/>and make it known.</hi> Though it belong not to her,<note place="margin">Whit. part. <hi>1.</hi> cont. <hi>1.</hi> q. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>316.</hi>
               </note> to decree what ſhall be Truth, and what not, yet when God who is the eſſential and eternal Truth, hath decreed it, and made it known to her, ſhe ought to make it known to others. As the <hi>Cryer</hi> publiſhes the <hi>Decrees</hi> and <hi>Edicts</hi> of the King, ſo is ſhe, and every member thereof, in his place, and calling, to ppubliſh it. And indeed ſuch is the nature of ſaving Truth, that whereſoever it comes, it provokes, nay conſtrains the ſould to make it known. When God had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed his minde to <hi>Jeremy,</hi> what a ſcorching Feaver was he in till he had publiſhed it? <hi>His word</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>was in mine heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 20.9.</note> 
               <hi>as a burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fire ſhut up in my bones, and I was weary with forbearing, and I could not ſtay.</hi> And when Chriſt had committed the Goſpel to the Apoſtles, what an holy force did they finde themſelves under? <hi>We cannot</hi> (ſay they) <hi>but ſpeak the things which we have ſeen and heard.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts. 4.20.</note> They were like <hi>old Bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles</hi> filled with <hi>New Wine,</hi> till they had delivered the Meſſage wherewith they were intruſted. As ſoon as ever a man is ſavingly acquainted with Chriſt, he preſently endeavours to bring in others to him. <hi>Andrew</hi> no ſooner findes him.<note place="margin">Joh. 1.42, 46<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> l. 29.</note> but he brings in <hi>Peter</hi> to him; <hi>Philip</hi> no ſooner findes him, but he brings <hi>Nathaneel</hi> to him; and the Woman of <hi>Samaria</hi> no ſooner findes him, but ſhe will have the <hi>whole City</hi> to come out to him. So that you ſee, Truth is no dull or ſluggiſh, but a lively and active Principle, and ſuch as do's incite the Soul wherein it ſeats it ſelf, to publiſh it and make it known. If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we will make it to appear we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:107190:42"/>the Truth, and will perform that ſervice, we owe to it, we muſt ſo far as our places, abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities and opportunities will extend, acquaint others with it.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Having thus told you, the <hi>manner</hi> how this proof muſt be manag'd, not only in reſpect of the <hi>antecedents,</hi> but likewiſe in reſpect of the <hi>concomitants</hi> and <hi>conſequents.</hi> I ſhall now come to the main buſineſs, which I have all this while been but making way for, and that is, to evince to you, That there do's by a <hi>divine right,</hi> belong to all Chriſtians, a <hi>private, diſcretive, ſelf-directive</hi> Judgement, by virtue whereof they not only may, but ought to prove thoſe things that are recommended to them by their Teachers; which I ſhall endeavour. to do by theſe arguments. And, 1, God himſelf, whoſe Word is a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent warrant for all their undertakigs, out of the reſpect he bears to their ſafety and welfare, do's in expreſs terms impower, nay charge them to do it. It was never his minde that they they ſhould pin their Faith upon their Teachers ſleeves, captivate their Judgments to theirs, or believe and do whatever they think is meet, but that they ſhould take their inſtructions, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fintions, and concluſions, to the rule of the Word, and try them thereby, and then cloſe with them according as the reeaſon they find attending them ſhall perſwade and induce them. This plainly apperas by theſe words of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>Prove all things;</hi> which are ſo clear and full to the point, that nothing but wilfull blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or obſtinate prejudice, can gainſay them. And yet as if what he ſaith here, were not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:107190:42"/>he ſpeaks elſewhere to the ſame purpoſe; witneſs that paſſage to the <hi>Corinthians;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.15.</note> 
               <hi>I ſpeak</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>as to wiſe men, judge ye what I ſay.</hi> Here, as <hi>Eſtius</hi> confeſſes,<note place="margin">Com. in loc.</note> he ſpeaks <hi>de judicio diſcretionis,</hi> of that Judgement of <hi>private diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> we are diſcourſing of, but then to avoid the force of the place, he tells us that the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians</hi> were perſons of extraordinary gifts and abilities, and therefore thoug the Apoſtle do in theſe words impower them and ſuch like, to judge of the Doctrine of their Paſtors, yet it do's not follow that he do's impower all to do it. <hi>Anſw.</hi> The <hi>Corinthians</hi> indeed were excellently gifted, they had arrived to very high attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, by reaſon whereof they were fitter to judge of what the Apoſtle was about to deliver to them, and tgherefore he urges it as an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to them to do it. But yet we muſt not think that he only aim'd at them, or ſuch as have made the ſame proficiency with them, in it, for though every Chriſtian have not the ſame degree of Wiſdom that they had, and in that reſpect be not ſo fit for the work as they were, yet he hath (as I ſhall ſhew anon) that meaſure, that by prayer, diligence, and the aſſiſtace o the Spirit in the uſe of means, do's render him ſo far fit for it, as is neceſſary to his own Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And therefore we muſt not think that the Apoſtle doe's urge it as a Priviledge or Duty, pertaining only to men of eminent Wiſdom, ſuch as many in the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> were (as the <hi>Schoolman</hi> would have us underſtand him) but as belonging to all Chriſtians what ſoever. One would think thoſe quick eyes that can, <hi>In thou
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:107190:43"/>art Peter,</hi> read the <hi>Popes</hi> power of depoſing Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, diſcharging Subjects of their Allegiance, the tranſlating of thier Kingdoms from them, with many ſuchrare myſteries, ſhould in theſe and ſuch like places, read the Peoples power of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Doctrines. But what can be ſo plain, that intereſt and prejudice will not contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict?</p>
            <p n="2">2. He layes upon them ſeveral important Duties that do neceſſarily ſuppoſe it, inſomuch that unleſs they be allowed the liberty of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian proof, they cannot perform them. As,</p>
            <p n="1">1. He wil have them to uſe caution about their Teachers. They muſt carefully diſtinguiſh betwixt the true and the falſe, betwixt the Meſſengers of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and the Meſſengers of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt. Beware</hi> (ſaith our Saviour) <hi>of falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets which come to you in. Sheeps cloathing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 7.15, 16.</note> 
               <hi>but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly they are ravening Wolves.</hi> And what courſe will he hav e them to take that they may diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh betwixt the true Prophets and the falſe? why, he tells them; <hi>ye ſhall know them by their fruits:</hi> And what are theſe <hi>fruits?</hi> are they their Lives? No; thoſe are no ſure Rule to go by: for Hypocrites and Deceivers can make as great ſhews of piety and holineſs as the beſt men whatſoever. And therefore theſe Fruits where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the People muſt diſtinguiſh the falſe Prophets from the true,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Part.</hi> 1. <hi>cont.</hi> 1. <hi>q.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 8. <hi>p.</hi> 359.</note> are rather (as Dr. <hi>Whitaker</hi> ſhews) their <hi>interpretations, expoſitions,</hi> and <hi>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines,</hi> than their <hi>lives.</hi> Thereby it is that all thoſe who would inform themſelves concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, muſt try what they are. And agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to this Precept of our Saviour, is that other
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:107190:43"/>of the Apoſtle; <hi>Beloved, believe not every Spirit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Joh. 4.1.</note> 
               <hi>but try the ſpirits, whether they are of God.</hi> It is to be obſerved, he ſpeaks this to thoſe whom he terms <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>little children,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De Jud. c. <hi>27.</hi> p. <hi>162.</hi>
               </note> which (as <hi>Davenant</hi> well notes) do's far better agree <hi>privatis fideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, to private Believers,</hi> than to <hi>Doctors</hi> and <hi>Rulers.</hi> It belongs then to <hi>private Believers,</hi> even to ſuch as the Holy Ghoſt thinks meet to ſpeak of under the appellation of <hi>little children</hi> to make tryall of their Teachers. And whereby muſt they come to know what they are, but by their <hi>fruits,</hi> which as you have herard, are their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines? When the Holy Ghoſt therefore do's in theſe places admoniſh the faithfull to uſe this prudent Caution a out their Teachers, and do's propound their Doctrine as that wheregby they muſt diſtinguiſh them, he do's in effect bid them prove their Doctrine.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He will have them to ſee that they ſuffer not themſelves to be poyſoned or corrupted bby ſuch Doctrines as are erroneous and unſound. They muſt not only diſtinguiſh betwixt Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Teachers, but betwixt Doctrines and Doctrines, taking care they receive what is good, and avoid what is bad.<note place="margin">Mat. 24.4. Eph. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 6. 2 Theſſ. 1.3.</note> This the Holy Ghoſt inſiſts much upon. And <hi>Gratian</hi> tells out of <hi>Iſidorus,</hi> that if be who is over the People, teach or command any thing beſides the will of God,<note place="margin">Cauſ. <hi>11.</hi> q. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> or beſides what is evidently required in the Holy Scriptures, they are to look upon him <hi>tanquam falſus Dei teſtis, aut ſacrilegus, as a falſe Witneſs of God, or ſacrilegious.</hi> It is then paſt doubt, that the people muſt uſe circumſpection, and not ſuffer themſlves to be deceived; but
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:107190:44"/>ſince there are ſo many falſe Teachers in the Would, and ſo much unſound Doctrine broach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by them, how is it poſſible they ſhould eſcape being deceived, unleſs they be allowed to prove what is delivered to them before they cloſe with it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He wil have them, when their Teachers fall into Errors, grow negligent, or fail in their Duty to admoniſh them and exhort them. <hi>Paul</hi> will have the <hi>Coloſſians</hi> to <hi>ſay to Archippus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 4.17.</note> 
               <hi>take heed to the Miniſtry which thou haſt received in the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">22. <hi>q.</hi> 33. <hi>a.</hi> 4.2.</note> 
               <hi>that thou fulfill it. Aquinas</hi> ſaith, this <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chippus</hi> was the Biſhop of <hi>Coloſs;</hi> and propound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Queſtion, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trum quis teneatur corrigere Prelatum ſitum, Whether any man be bound to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove his Prelate;</hi> he determines it affirmatively, urging this very place for what he aſſerts, infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring from it, that the People, when there is oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion may reprove their Prelates, ſo they do it <hi>cum reverentia, &amp; honore, ac manſuetudine,</hi> with <hi>reverence,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cauſ.</hi> 2 9.7.</note> 
               <hi>honour and meekneſs.</hi> And <hi>Gratian</hi> ſhews from Pope <hi>Euſebius,</hi> that people may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove their Paſtors in caſe they do <hi>à fide exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare, depart from the Faith.</hi> In the Judgement then of the very <hi>Papiſts</hi> themſelves, and thoſe too, who are of greateſt account, if Miniſters, nay the Prelates, miſs in their proceedings, the People not only may but ought to tell them of it, and admoniſh them about it. And how ſhall they do this, unleſs they may have liberty to cenſure and make a Judgement upon what they ſay and do.</p>
            <p n="4">4. When the Church wherein they live, do's apoſtatize and decline, he will have them to ſit
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:107190:44"/>in judgment upon her, and proteſt againſt the corruptions they find her guilty of. This appears by the charge the Prophet gives,<note place="margin">Hoſ. 2.2.</note> 
               <hi>Plead</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>with your mother, plead,</hi> where obſerve,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Who they be he gives this charge to; and thoſe are the godly ones in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who remain'd faithful and ſtedfaſt in that time of general Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſie that the Prophet in this book refers to. Though the body of the Nation followed <hi>Jero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam,</hi> nd gave up themſelves to ſuperſtition and idolatry; yet there were ſome that ſtood their guound, and ocntinued upright; and thoſe the Prophet in this place directs his ſpeech to.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Who it is that he means by <hi>Mother,</hi> and that (as <hi>Zanchy, Rivet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Com. in loc.</note> and others ſhew) is <hi>Iſraelitica Eccleſia,</hi> the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> conſiſting of Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, Miniſters and People, as ſhe lay in her cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt ſtate, polluted with idolatry, which ſhe fell into by walking after the commandment of the wicked Princed before mentioned, whom God hath for ever ſtigmatized with this mark of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famy, that he <hi>made Iſrael to ſin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. What it is he will have them to do, and that is, <hi>Plead with her;</hi> the word in the original is, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which interpreters do variouſly render; the <hi>vulgar Latin</hi> turns it, <hi>judicate,</hi> judge her; <hi>Pagnine contendite,</hi> contend with her; <hi>Vatablus, expoſtulate,</hi> expoſtulate with her; <hi>Calvin,</hi> and others, <hi>litigate,</hi> plead with her. The Prophet would have them to enter into judgment with her, cenſure her, and deal with her by ſuch ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, reproofs and admonitions, as might beſt ſerve to convince her of the ſin ſhe ſtood guilty of, and bring her to repentance.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:107190:45"/>
            <p n="4">4. The repetition, <hi>plead, plead,</hi> whereby he does nto onely hold forth the necedſſity and impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the work, but likewiſe intimates, that they muſt do it ſpeedily, boldly and vigorouſly, as thoſe that were troubled to behold the honour of God ſuffer by her apoſtaſie, and deſirous to ſee it repaired by her return. So that the words imply as much as if he had ſaid, Ye pious nad faithful ones in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who adhere unto God, and ſtand up for his pure worſhip and ſervice, you ſee how lamentably your Mother the Church, that ſhould have been an example to you of piety and conſtancy, is revolted and fallen to idolatry: as ever you will make it to appear you have any zeal or love to the truth, take her caſe into conſideration, tell her of her fault, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove her for it, reaſon with her about it, and do all you can to reduce her int thoſe holy ways ſhe heretofore walked in, and in compliance with the commandment of her wicked King hath ſo unworthily forſaken. We ſee then the Church, notwithſtanding the uncontrolable height that ſome advance her to, is no ſuch tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendous thing, but that even private men may, by divine allowance, freely cenſure her, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtulate with her about her proceedings: and how ſhall they do this, unleſs they exerciſe a <hi>judgment</hi> of <hi>diſcretion</hi> to direct and guide them in it?</p>
            <p n="5">5. He will not have them to do any thing raſhly, or with doubting, but throughly to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form and ſatisſie themſelves of the lawfulneſs of it,<note place="margin">Rom. 14.5.</note> ere they undertake it: <hi>Let every man</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>be fully perſuaded in his own mind.</hi> Before
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:107190:45"/>they cloſe with any doctrin, or ſet upon any ſervice, they muſt enquire into it, and be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded, nay, fully perſuaded of the warranta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs of it. They muſt not go upon ſlight pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>babilities or conjectures, but muſt be at a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty, ſo that they may ſay with <hi>Peter,</hi> in the name of himſelf and the reſt,<note place="margin">Joh. 6.69.</note> 
               <hi>We believe and are ſure.</hi> But how is it poſſible they ſhould attain to this full perſuaſion and certainty of the nature and ſtate of things, unleſs they make proof of them? what, is the teſtimony of others ſufficient ſecurity to them? Then what error is ſo great or dangerous, that they may not be fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded and aſſured of?</p>
            <p n="6">6. He would have them to decline <hi>evil</hi> and chuſe <hi>good,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.11. Iſa. 1.16, 17.</note> forſake the <hi>one</hi> and hold faſt the <hi>other.</hi> This is ſet down as plainly in Scripture as if it were written with a beam of the Sun. But unleſs they may bring things to trial, how ſhall they be able to do it? How ſhall they di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh betwixt good and evil? how ſhall they know what to chuſe and what to refuſe, when to ſtand and when to go?</p>
            <p n="7">7. He will have them to clear up their evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences for heaven, and aſcertain themſelves of their ſalvation. This the Apoſtle aims at when he ſaith,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.10.</note> 
               <hi>Give all diligentce to make your calling and election ſure.</hi> There is a two-fold certainty of a mans calling and election; there is <hi>certitudo objecrti,</hi> and <hi>certitudo ſubjecti;</hi> a <hi>certainty</hi> of the thing it ſelf, and a <hi>certainty</hi> there of to a man's own ſoul; the one reſults from the ſincerity and truth of grace, the other from the reflexion or manifeſtation of it. It is the latter of theſe the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:107190:46"/>Apoſtle aims at in this place; which how is it poſlible any one ſhould attain to, unleſs by his own perſonal enquiry he make proof of what he believes and does. And thus you ſee God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires of the people ſeveral unqueſtionable duties which do neceſſarily ſuppoſe this power of trial, ſo that it muſt eithr be granted, that he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended it for them, or elſe that he hath put them upon inſuperable difficulties, which to affirm were no leſs than blaſphemy.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He impowers them to do divers things in Religion that are of a more eminent nature, and call for greater abilities than the judging of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines for their own private uſe does. He al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows them in a <hi>charitative, private</hi> way to teach, exhort and warn one another, for their mutual edification and furtherance in the faith. <hi>Paul</hi> charges the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> to <hi>warn the unruly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 5.14.</note> 
               <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort the feeble minded, ſupport the weak,</hi> &amp;c. And in anſwer hereunto we find,<note place="margin">Acts 18.24, 26.</note> that <hi>Aquila</hi> and <hi>Priſcilla,</hi> ſeeing <hi>Apollos</hi> (though an <hi>eloquent</hi> man, and mighty in the Scriptures) ſhort in ſome points in Chriſtianity, <hi>they took him and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded the way of God to him more perfectly.</hi> And he does not onely allow them to do it thus in a private way, but likewiſe upon <hi>ſpecial</hi> occaſions, when the <hi>neceſſities</hi> of the Church do require it, in a more publick. The Scripture makes men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſeveral, who though they were but pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Chriſtians, yet embracing the call given them by God, they publickly appeared in the behalf of the truth, openly aſſerted it, and pleaded for it.<note place="margin">Acts 6.10.7.2.</note> 
               <hi>Stephen,</hi> though but a <hi>Deacon,</hi> or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained to <hi>ſerve tables,</hi> yet being call'd in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:107190:46"/>by the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> council for his faith in Chriſt, he owns him before them all, <hi>teaches</hi> him, and <hi>diſputes</hi> for him. And <hi>Apollos,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 18.25.</note> though he were but a private man, and knew only the <hi>Baptiſm</hi> of <hi>John,</hi> yet he diſputed with the <hi>Jews,</hi> and <hi>ſpoke</hi> and <hi>taught</hi> diligently <hi>the things of the Lord.</hi> Nay, and all the <hi>Diſciples,</hi> ſcattered abroad upon the death of <hi>Stephen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 8.4.</note> went every where <hi>preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> the word. And if we conſult ſucceeding times, we ſhall find, that the Chriſtians of thoſe days did both challenge and practiſe the like liberty. <hi>Origen,</hi> before he entred into holy Orders, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſed,<note place="margin">Euſeb. eccl. hiſt. l. <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>20.</hi> gr.</note> expounded, diſputed, and that pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly, both before the Clergy and People. Its true, <hi>Demetrius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Alexandria</hi> excepted againſt it, alledging it was without preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that <hi>lay-men</hi> ſhould teach in the Church in the preſence of Biſhops; but <hi>Alexander</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and <hi>Theoctiſtus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Ceſarea,</hi> took him roundly up for it, charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him with a manifeſt untruth, and telling him, that ſeveral others as well as <hi>Origen,</hi> though but private men, had taken upon them to teach in publick Aſſemblies, even at ſuch times as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers learned men were preſent; and that the Biſhops of thoſe places did not onely allow it, but deſire them to do it. And they inſtance in <hi>Evelpis</hi> at <hi>Laranda,</hi> requeſted to it by <hi>Neon;</hi> in <hi>Paulinus</hi> at <hi>Iconium,</hi> requeſted to it by <hi>Celſus;</hi> in <hi>Theodorus</hi> at <hi>Synada,</hi> requeſted to it by <hi>Atticus.</hi> And they alſo add, that it was like that this courſe was practiſed <hi>in other places,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. hiſt. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>30.</hi> gr.</note> though unknown to them. And <hi>Socrates</hi> tells of <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> that whiles he was Lieutenant of <hi>Millain,</hi> and Conſul,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:107190:47"/>even before he was baptized, the people unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectedly making choice of him to ſucceed <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xentius</hi> their deceaſed Biſhop, and the Biſhops preſent allowing of it, he without any more ado took upon him the place. And <hi>Chamier,</hi> out of <hi>Jerom,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Panſt. t. <hi>1.</hi> l. <hi>28.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi> ſect. <hi>21.</hi> p. <hi>585.</hi>
               </note> makes mention of <hi>Ariſtides, Agrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa, Hegeſippus, Juſtinus, Muſanus, Modeſtus,</hi> the two <hi>Apollonii, Heraclius, Maximus,</hi> and divers others, who though they were never ordain'd to any office in the Church, yet wrote Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies and Diſputations in behalf of the Chriſtian Religion, againſt Heathens, Hereticks, and the enemies thereof. And he alſo inſtances in <hi>Arno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius</hi> and <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> who fell to write before they were baptized; and in <hi>Leo</hi> the <hi>Emperour,</hi> whoſe <hi>Homilies, Gretzer,</hi> though an angry and fierce <hi>Jeſuite,</hi> publiſhed a while ago, giving them this commendation, that they were by ſo much the more to be eſteemed, <hi>quo pauciora in hoc genere monumenta, ab imperatoribus profecta exiſtent; by how much the monuments of Emperors of this kind are the more rare.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hiſt. eccl. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>23, 24.</hi>
               </note> And what will our adverſaries ſay to <hi>Edeſius</hi> and <hi>Frumentius,</hi> two <hi>Merchants,</hi> and <hi>young</hi> men, that preached the Goſpel to the <hi>Indians;</hi> nay, to a <hi>Woman,</hi> that did the like among the <hi>Iberians,</hi> which <hi>Theodoret</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Cyrus</hi> hath inſerted in his Hiſtory, not letting fall ſo much as one word by way of reflection or diſallowance? By theſe inſtances it does in part appear what power private Chriſtians have here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore challenged as to matter of teaching, and what liberty the Churches wherein they lived granted to them. They did not limit them onely to a liberty of aſſent and obedience to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:107190:47"/>of their leaders, but they allowed them both to judge and teach the things of God: nay, they gave way that ſuch of them as were able, ſhould upon ſpecial occaſions publickly ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſe, expound, diſpute, write Treatiſes. And the Biſhops were ſo far from being diſpleas'd with it, that they moved them to it, and defended them againſt the cavils of ſuch, as out of errour or prejudice excepted againſt it. In anſwer here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, <hi>Stapleton</hi> ſaith, theſe were <hi>rare</hi> and <hi>extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary inſtances,</hi> and ſo not to be drawn into <hi>example.</hi> But how can they be ſaid to be <hi>rare,</hi> when there were ſo many of them almoſt in every age? and as for their <hi>extraordinarineſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">t. <hi>1.</hi> l. <hi>28.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi> ſect. <hi>23.</hi> p. <hi>585.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Chamier</hi> ſaith, <hi>Catholici negant quicquam in iis exemplis fuiſſe extra ordinem,</hi> That the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> deny there was any thing <hi>extraordinary</hi> in them. But admit they were both <hi>rare</hi> and <hi>extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary,</hi> yet this we may certainly infer, that pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate men in like caſes may take upon them ſuch ſervices; which yet I doubt his Holineſs will hardly give way to.</p>
            <p>And thus much for the liberty God allows them as to teaching. Were it needful, I might,<note place="margin">Acts 6.3.13.2. 2 Cor. 8.19. Col. 4.17. Acts 11.2.15.2.18.27. 1 Cor. 5.4.12. 2 Cor. 2.6, 7. Acts 15.23.</note> for the further proof of the point in hand, add, that he allows them to chuſe their ſeveral Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, and, when there is occaſion, to admoniſh them, (as you heard before) reaſon with them, ſend them upon meſſages, recommend them by their Letters; and that likewiſe he allows them to interpoſe with their Paſtors in Eccleſiaſtical Cenſures, judge of offenders, caſt out the obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, reſtore the penitent; nay, to ſit in council, hear, debate, &amp; give ſuffrage with them. All which
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:107190:48"/>I might have ſpoken of fully, but it is done al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready by divers learned men, who have em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed themſelves in aſſerting their intereſt in the government of the Church;<note place="margin">G. Bucer. Diſſert. p. <hi>165</hi> D. Blondel. apoloſect. <hi>3.</hi> p. <hi>379.</hi> De jure, p. <hi>14.</hi> G. Voetius Deſp. cauſ. l. <hi>2.</hi> ſect. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>21.</hi> p. <hi>268.</hi>
               </note> and I conceive I have ſaid enough for the clearing of the preſent particular, and therefore ſhall forbear to ſpeak any further of them. Now to argue <hi>à majori, ad minus;</hi> if it be the pleaſure of God that they ſhould be allowed a power to teach, write, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſe in judicial proceedings, and exert acts of government, which require higher abilities, then it is ſurely his pleaſure that they ſhould be allowed a power of private judgment, which may be managed with lower abilities; what can be more unlikely than that he ſhould think them fit for <hi>greater</hi> matters and not for <hi>leſs,</hi> allow them to judge for <hi>others,</hi> and not for <hi>themſelves?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The truth hereof does alſo appear from the multitude of intruders, uſurpers, and falſe lights that are in the world, who abuſing the vain cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulity of people, lead them into miſerable delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. Had all thoſe who intermeddle in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion a due call, ſound principles and good de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, then people might go on with greater confidence, and take things upon truſt on better grounds; but its far otherwiſe. Ever ſince the Truth firſt ſhew'd it ſelf, the world hath even ſwarm'd with Impoſtors and Deceivers, who pretend to it, with no leſs boldneſs than the faithfulleſt maintainers of it.<note place="margin">Mat. 24.5.</note> 
               <hi>Many</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>ſhall come in my name, ſaying,</hi> I <hi>am Chriſt.</hi> And, (ſaith <hi>Peter</hi>) <hi>there were falſe prophets alſo among the people,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.1.</note> 
               <hi>even as there ſhall be falſe teachers among you.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Joh. 2.18.</note> And, (ſaith <hi>John</hi>) <hi>Even now are there many
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:107190:48"/>antichriſts.</hi> The devil is God's Ape; for as he hath his Angels, ſo the devil hath his; and as he hath his Miniſters, ſo the devil hath his, who <hi>compaſs ſea and land</hi> that they may deceive. Now this even in the judgment of the holy Ghoſt himſelf, is a proper argument to move all thoſe who would not be deceived, to prove thoſe things that are delivered to them before they cloſe with them; witneſs that of the Apoſtle laſt men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, <hi>Beloved, believe not every ſpirit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Joh. 4.1.</note> 
               <hi>but try the ſpirits whether they are of God, becauſe many falſe prophets are gone out into the world.</hi> Were there never a falſe prophet in the world, then men might with more ſafety lay by their jealouſie, draw the Curtains about them, ſhut their eyes, and betake themſelves to reſt: but while there are ſuch legions of them attending on them, they may not do it, without expoſing themſelves to apparent hazard.</p>
            <p n="5">5. It does likewiſe appear from the condition even of thoſe who are faithful Paſtors and Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; they are ſubject to miſtakes. Though their call, principles and deſigns be better than thoſe of the former, yet they are not exempted from error: though in regard of their authority, abilities, experience, holineſs, they are far fitter to teach and rule than others, yet it muſt ſtill be remembred that they are but ſinful men, ſubject to the ſame paſſions and infirmities that others are, and therefore muſt be attended to with cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpection and care. He that in good earneſt thinks there is on earth either any ſingle perſon, or any ſociety or order of perſons, guided in all things by an infallible ſpirit, ſo as that they may,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:107190:49"/>in whatever they deliver challenge our aſſent and obedience, without any contradiction or cenſure, ſhews he is little acquainted either with Scripture, or what hath happened in the World. <hi>Paul</hi> cryes out, <hi>let God be true, and every man a lyar;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 3.4.</note> not that he deſired that every man might be a Lyar, but that they indeed are ſo, and that the World may take them to be ſo. What meer mortal man was ever bleſſed with greater light than this Apoſtle? who more abounded with Revelations than he? and yet (as he himſelf confeſſes) he knew <hi>but in part.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.12.</note> Thoſe who at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to the higheſt perfection, a ſtate of mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality is capable of, do fall far ſhort of what they ſhould be. As the brighteſt Stars have in them ſome darkneſs, and the cleareſt dayes ſome Clouds, ſo the wiſeſt men have in them ſome Folly and Error. Herein <hi>Davenant</hi> is free and peremptory. <hi>If</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>thou leave God, and the divinely inſpired Prophets and Apoſtles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De Jud. c. <hi>27.</hi> p. <hi>166.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>there is not any man or Society of men, qui non &amp; fallere &amp; falli poteſt in doctrinâ fidei tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendâ, who may not both deceive, and be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in delivering the doctrine of Faith.</hi> And ſhall people go and give up themſelves to the conduct of thoſe who are ſubject to Error as well as they? Were they priviledg'd from mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake, then they might caſt themſelves upon their Veracity, and receive their Dictates as ſo many ſacred Oracles; but being it is far other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, they may not do it without the guilt of vain confidence and raſhneſs.</p>
            <p n="6">6. It do's yet further appear from the lyable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, nay proneneſs that is in people to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived.
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:107190:49"/>Were it ſo that there were no falſe Lights in the World, or that thoſe who are law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Teachers could not deceive, or that the People themſelves could not be deceived, then they might be more ſecure, but ſince it is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe as to each particular, it concerns them to be more circumſpect. What is to be thought of the two former hath been ſhew'd already, and as for the latter, the Caſe is no leſs plain. Ever ſince the Eclipſe in <hi>Eden,</hi> the ſons of men have all along from firſt to laſt, lien in darkneſs; and not only ſo, but they have had in them an unhappy averſneſs to Truth, and proneneſs to error. There was a time when there was a ſweet union betwixt the Soul and Truth, ſo that they ſeem'd to lye faſt in the ſincere embraces of each other; but now the ſtream is turn'd. The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect that the Soul heretofore bare to Truth, it now bears to Error, and the hatred that here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore it bore to Error, it now bears to Truth. This was it which made our Saviour when he was on Earth complain,<note place="margin">Joh. 3.19.</note> that <hi>light was come into the World, and men loved darkneſs rather than light.</hi> And as it was then, ſo it is now. How much are men in love with Error, and how little with Truth! Truth, <hi>ſhe cryes without,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov 1.20.</note> 
               <hi>ſhe utters her voice in the ſtreets, ſhe cryes in the chief places of concourſe, in the opening of the Gates, in the City ſhe utters her words, ſaying, How long ye ſimple ones will ye love ſimplicity — turn you at my reproof:</hi> And it falls out to her as it did to <hi>Baals</hi> Prophets, there is <hi>neither voice,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 King. 18.29.</note> 
               <hi>nor any that anſwers, nor any that regards;</hi> but Error no ſooner ſpeaks, but people run to it and receive it.
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:107190:50"/>Truth comes and knocks at the door of their hearts,<note place="margin">Cant. 5.2.</note> ſaying, <hi>Open to me my ſiſter, my love, my dove, my undefiled, for my head is filled with dew, and my locks with the drops of the night:</hi> and they ſit ſtill making Excuſes, and ſaying, <hi>I have put off my coat, how ſhall</hi> I <hi>put it on,</hi> I <hi>have waſhed my feet, how ſhall</hi> I <hi>defile them?</hi> But Error no ſooner knocks but they open to it and let it in. How ordinarily do's Truth that was once ſo dear unto the Soul ſtand by deſpiſed and rejected, while Error is entertained and embraced! How familiarly do People take up Error into the bed of Truth, and there moſt unworthily ſuffer it to raviſh them and defile them, to the high provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of <hi>Jeſus</hi> Chriſt, who hath ſtrictly charged them to keep themſelves <hi>unſpotted from the World!</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jam. 1.27.</note> Now ſince men are thus prone to be deceived, what madneſs is it to take things upon truſt, without making tryall of them? What is it leſs than a tempting of God to forſake them, and a proſtituting themſelves to the pleaſure of every Seducer?</p>
            <p n="7">7. For the people to take things from their Teachers upon truſt, without any proof is to give them more reſpect than is due to them; It is no leſs than to ſet them in the room of God, make them Lords of their Faith, found their Religion upon their Authority, and ſo ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der themſelves the meer <hi>ſervants of men,</hi> which the Holy Ghoſt do's every where declare againſt, and condemn, as prejudicial to his Intereſt, and their own neceſſary liberty. There was none of the Apoſtles who preach'd up the authority and honour of Miniſters more than <hi>Paul,</hi> yet
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:107190:50"/>would not he have people to yield up their Faith to them, or aſſent to whatſoever they ſhall deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; he was ſo far from laying on them any ſuch duty, that he do's in expreſs terms forbid it, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Be ye not the ſervants of men.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 7.23.</note> As he forbids Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters to challenge an arbitrary, lordly power over people, ſo he forbids people if they through pride and arrogance do challenge it, to yield it to them. Though he will have them to reverence and encourage them, as they are the <hi>Meſſengers</hi> of God, &amp; ſuch as do <hi>watch for their ſouls,</hi> yet he will not have them to look upon them as infallible, or take all upon their word. To be believed meerly upon the credit of his own Word, is pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar to God himſelf, and may not be given to any of his Creatures how excellent ſoever, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out manifeſt alienation of his right, which by all means muſt be maintain'd and kept inviolable. When we have to deal with God, our Enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry muſt not be whether that be true which he ſaith, but whether it be he that ſaith it, being aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured if he ſay it, it cannot but be true. But when we have to do with men, we are to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed far otherwiſe; our enquiry then muſt not only be, whether it be Man that ſaith it, but whether that be true which he ſaith, as know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the conſideration of his Nature it may be otherwiſe. God being Truth it ſelf, his bare word is ſufficient evidence and ſecurity in the moſt arduous and difficult Caſes whatſoever; but it is not ſo with man: he is not only a Creature, but a lapſed and degenerate Creature, ſubject to Error, and therefore we muſt receive his Dictates and Precepts with ſuſpicion, cloſing
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:107190:51"/>with them no further than he makes it to appear they are conformable to the Divine Law.</p>
            <p n="8">8. God hath furniſhed them with various priviledges and helps, whereby he hath qualified and fitted them for the work.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He hath given them his Word as a certain Rule and Meaſure to direct and guide them, that ſo they may not make a falſe Judgement, but ſuch as is according to Truth. That the Scripture, and the reading thereof, do's belong to the people, <hi>Chamier, Whitaker,</hi> and other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Writers have copiouſly and unanſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably proved. And to what end ſhould they either have it, or read it, unleſs they be allowed tojudge of the ſenſe of it, and the Doctrines of their Teachers by it? God do's not diliver it into the hands of any, to lay it by them as a thing of no uſe, or wherein they are not concern'd, but that they ſhould acquamt themſelves with it, and frame their wayes and doings according to it. The reaſon wherefore he puts it into the hands of Magiſtrates, Miniſters, People, is that they may each of them thereby come to know their duty, and perform it. The reaſon wherefore he would have <hi>Joſhuah</hi> to <hi>meditate</hi> in it,<note place="margin">Joſh. 1, 8.</note> was that he might <hi>obſerve todo accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to all that was written therein.</hi> And the reaſon wherefore he would have <hi>Timothy</hi> to be converſant in it,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 3.14, 15.</note> was that he might <hi>know how to behave himſelf in the houſe of God.</hi> In like manner,<note place="margin">Acts 17.11.</note> the reaſon wherefore he would have the <hi>Beraeans</hi> to <hi>ſearch</hi> it, was that they might ſee whether the things delivered by their Paſtors
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:107190:51"/>
               <hi>were ſo.</hi> And it is not reaſonable to thing, that God, who is the wiſe, righteous and merciful Governour of the world, ſhould give Laws to men to live by, and yet ſhould not allow them power and liberty, as to their own private uſe and practice, to judge of the ſenſe of them, and what is agreeable to them, and what is not.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He hath indued them with reaſon, judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, wiſdom, and ſuch like accompliſhments, whereby he hath competently enabled them to do it. There are two things neceſſary to the begetting of faith; an outward <hi>notification,</hi> or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of the Doctrin to be believed; and an inward <hi>illumination</hi> and perſuaſion of the mind, to ſee the evidence and truth thereof, and to cloſe with it and embrace it. The former he vouchſafes in his Word, the latter he works by his Spirit; and the faithful having theſe two, they have all things neceſſary to this judgment. That they have the former, appears by what I have alledg'd already, and that they have the latter is no leſs manifeſt. God hath promiſed his Church, that he will <hi>teach</hi> her <hi>children;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 54.13. Jer. 31.33, 34.</note> and that he <hi>will put</hi> his <hi>law in their inward parts, and write it in their hearts,</hi> infomuch that <hi>they ſhall teach no more every man his neighbour, and every man his brother, ſaying, Know the Lord, for they ſhall all know him, from the leaſt of them unto the greateſt of them.</hi> And what he thus graciouſly promiſed in the Old Teſtament, he hath emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently performed in the New, pouring forth his Spirit in ſuch a plentiful manner upon his people, that according to his own language they <hi>have ſenſes exerciſed to diſcern both good and evil;</hi> nay,<note place="margin">Heb. 5.14.</note>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:107190:52" rendition="simple:additions"/>they have ſuch <hi>an unction,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Joh. 2.20, 27.</note> 
               <hi>that they know all things, and need not that any man teach them, but as the ſame annointing teacheth them.</hi> Which yet the Apoſtle ſpeaks not, as if thoſe he wrote to knew <hi>all things,</hi> in a ſtrict and proper ſenſe, for that is God's prerogative; or that they really knew ſo much, that they needed no teaching at all, for then to what purpoſe did he ſend to them this Epiſtle? but that they knew all the principles and grounds of Religion, and all things that were abſolutely neceſſary for them to know, (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially as to that buſineſs he wrote to them about) ſo that the work of their Teachers was rather to exhort them to perſeverance, and build them up higher in the Truths they knew, than ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint them with new onew. And it is well known,<note place="margin">Syntag l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>7.</hi> p. <hi>216.</hi>
               </note> which <hi>Lud. Crocius</hi> tells us, that even among private Chriſtians, there have been ſome, who by prayer, and the diligent reading and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditating of the Scripture, have obtain'd the gift of interpretation and trial of ſpirits, <hi>ampliori menſurâ quàm nonulli paſtores, in a larger meaſure than ſome paſtors.</hi> Not to turn back ſo far as the times of the Antients, which yet yielded great plenty of eminent men of private capacity, what will our adverſaries ſay to <hi>Laurentius Valla,</hi> the two <hi>Earls</hi> of <hi>Mirandula, Capnio, Fagius, Eraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, Faber, Mercer,</hi> both the <hi>Scaligers, Druſius, Caſaubon, Tilenus, Grotius, Heinſius, Selden, Salmaſius, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and divers others of la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter times, who though they never entred into holy Orders yet were men of ſuch high abilities, that their names are famous throughout a great part of the Chriſtian world? And to what end
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:107190:52"/>does God beſtow all this light and wiſdom on private perſons, that it ſhould lie by them as a thing of no uſe? no, but that they may thereby, as he himſelf ſhews,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.12. Phil. 1.10.</note> 
               <hi>know the things that are freely given them of God,</hi> and <hi>approve things that are excellent.</hi> As <hi>Nature</hi> does nothing <hi>in vain,</hi> ſo neither do's <hi>God.</hi> When he delivers <hi>Talents</hi> unto his ſervants, it is not that they ſhould <hi>napkin</hi> them up, but that they ſhould, as his Factors by negotiation, improve them for him. <hi>Zanchius</hi> ſpeaks an undoubted truth when he ſaith, <hi>Dona Dei in ſanctis non ſunt otioſa,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Com. in</hi> Phil. 1.10.</note> 
               <hi>The gifts of God in his ſaints are not to no purpoſe.</hi> When he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtows them upon them, it is not that they ſhould let them lie idle by them, or convert them to a private uſe, but that they ſhould lay them out for him in the ſervices proper to them. This he takes to be ſo reaſonable, that upon his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring abilities upon them, he expects that they ſhould, without looking for any particular com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, immediately fall to work, and improve them for him. We need not then go far for ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments to evince the peoples power of judging of doctrins; their qualifications ſlew it was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended they ſhould do it. As the ſhape of <hi>Anax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agoras</hi> his body ſhew'd he was made <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>to contemplate the Sun,</hi> ſo the abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities wherewith God hath fitted them for this judgment, ſhews he intended them the liberty of it. The very conſtitution and frame of things, does commonly declare and expreſs their work and office. The figure of a Bowl ſhews it was made for circular motion; that of an Arrow ſhews it was made for flight. In like manner the faculties
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:107190:53"/>and abilities wherewith God hath indued the People, ſhew he never intended they ſhould be govern'd like beaſts, or ſtones, but as creatures that have power of judging betwixt good and evil.</p>
            <p n="9">9. If it be the duty of the people to cloſe with the doctrines and commands of their Teachers, upon a meer implicit faith, without making proof of them, then it is ſometimes their duty to cloſe with that which is unlawful and ſinful, to omit what God hath required, and commit what he hath forbidden; nay, to deny him, worſhip idols, and give up themſelves to all manner of wickedneſs; which to maintain is impiety ſo groſs, that one would think, none who beſieve the Seriptures ſhould be guilty of it. And yet I ſee not how thoſe, who are for the fore-mentioned implicit faith, can avoid it. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps they I ſay, when they plead for peoples obeying the dictates of their teachers, without any examining them, they mean onely in lawful things. As long as they command lawful things, they muſt obey them, but when they do other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, they muſt not. But this is a miſerable <hi>ſubterfuge;</hi> for how without examination ſhall they do to know, whether the things they enjoyn them be lawful or not lawful? Their Teachers will have them ſubſcribe to ſuch and ſuch points, and practie ſuch and ſuch obſervations; if they are lawful, they muſt do them; if otherwiſe, they muſt not. Now how (as I ſaid) without examination ſhall they know whether they be lawful or not lawful, whether they may be done or not done? There is no way but two;
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:107190:53"/>either they muſt take them upon the word of their Teachers, or not; if not, then they muſt neceſſarily examine, which is the thing contended for; if they muſt, then, I ſay, they muſt (ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times at leaſt) neceſſarily ſin, which yet is alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether indiſpenſable and unwarrantable.</p>
            <p n="10">10. If it were the pleaſure of God, that peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhould embrace and ſubmit to the doctrins and precepts of their Leaders, without any exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination or doubting, then he would certainly excuſe them, if they ſhould thereby fall into error and profaneneſs. For it may not conſiſt with his juſtice to require them, without any examination or doubting, to follow the guid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of their Leaders, and then be diſpleaſed with them for ſo doing; this were no leſs than to render them <hi>evil</hi> for <hi>good,</hi> and puniſh them for doing their duties. But he will be ſo far from excuſing them, if upon their embracing and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting to the doctrins and precepts of their Leaders, without examination or douting, they fall into error and profaneneſs, that he will call them to an account, and puniſh them ſeverely for it. Their obedience unto men ſhall not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe their diſobedience unto him. <hi>Tannerus</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed,<note place="margin">Colloqu. Ratif. Seſſ. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> according to his wonted orthodoxneſs and modeſty, that he may the better perſuade and encourage the people to follow their Teachers whither they pleaſe to lead them, affirms the clean contrary; but they had beſt take heed how they truſt to ſuch doctrin. As he will puniſh their Teachers for leading them into ſin, ſo he will puniſh them for following them into it.<note place="margin">Mat. 15.14.</note> According to that of our Saviour, <hi>If the blind
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:107190:54"/>lead the blind, both ſhall fall into the ditch.</hi> He will puniſh both the one and the other; the one for leading, the other for following; the one for deceiving, the other for being deceived. He will not onely puniſh the deceiving Prophet, but him likewiſe that is deceived by him. <hi>They ſhall bear</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the puniſhment of their iniquity,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 14.10.</note> 
               <hi>the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of the prophet ſhall be even as the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of him that ſeeketh nuto him:</hi> that is, both the one and the other ſhall be guilty, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go the penalty juſtice ſhall aſſign them for the ſame.<note place="margin">Num. 25.8.</note> 
               <hi>Zimri</hi> ſhall not excuſe <hi>Cosbi,</hi> nor <hi>Cosbi Zimri,</hi> but they ſhall both die together. And it is a righteous thing with God, when people out of a ſlaviſh wilful credulity follow their Leaders into by-paths, to make them ſmart for it, and that for this reaſon, becauſe he hath made ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient proviſion to ſecure them againſt it. He hath told them, that notwithſtanding their high office in the Church, yet they have in them ſome dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, are liable to error, and upon that account hath warned them to hear them with caution, and to beware of being deceived by them. <hi>Take heed</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>and beware of the leven of the Phariſees and of the Sadduces.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 16.6.</note> And he is ſo far from tying them up to their lips, that he do's in expreſs terms charge them, when they require unlawful things to diſobey them.<note place="margin">Jer. 23.16.</note> 
               <hi>Hearken not</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>unto the words of the prophets that propheſie unto you.</hi> And that they may know what things are law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and what are not lawful, he hath, as I have ſhewed, delivered his Word to them, command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to read and ſtudy it: and for their bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter underſtanding of it, he hath given them a
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:107190:54"/>competent meaſure of his Spirit, ſtrictly charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to keep to it, and not ſuffer themſelves to be drawn away from it by any inducements or temptations whatſoever. Now if after all this they will yet ſhut their eyes, inſlave themſelves to their Leaders, and follow them into ſinful courſes, who will not look upon them as wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to ſuffer? I may ſay to them in this caſe, as <hi>David</hi> did to <hi>Saul</hi>'s ſouldiers, <hi>As the Lord liveth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 26.16.</note> 
               <hi>ye are worthy to die.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="111">11. If they muſt ſubmit to the dictates and precepts of their Leaders, meerly upon their au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, without any examination or tryal, then they muſt, as to the matter of obedience, give as much honour to them as to God himſelf. For when he is pleaſed to give forth his Laws, what greater honour can they give him, as to the yielding of obedience, than do what he enjoyns, meerly upon his authority, without enquiring after any other reaſon to authorize or oblige to it? And therefore I ſay, if they muſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to what is delivered by their Teachers, meerly upon their authority, without any exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination or trial, they muſt in reſpect of the abſoluteneſs of their obedience, give as much honour to them as to him. Now this he will not allow; for in all thoſe duties we are to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, which are common to men (as the objects thereof) with him, he ſtill reſerves to himſelf a peculiar preheminence, which we may neither with-hold nor diminiſh without denying him his undoubted right. As to inſtance in faith; we muſt believe both God and men, but with this difference, that we muſt aſſent to what he
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:107190:55"/>ſaith <hi>ſimpliciter,</hi> meerly upon the credit of his own Word: but we muſt aſſent to what they ſay, only <hi>ſecundum quid,</hi> or ſo far as it is agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to what is delivered by him. In like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner we muſt obey both him and men, but with this difference, that we muſt obey him <hi>abſolutely</hi> ſo far as he commands, but them with a <hi>reſerve,</hi> that is, only ſo far as what they command, is agreeable to what is commanded by him. Theſe are the bounds of the honour he allows us to give to men, and if we go any farther, we render them more than belongs to them, which we cannot do, but we ſhall intrench upon his right, and go againſt the Scripture, which forbids us to <hi>give</hi> His <hi>glory to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſo. 42.8.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12. The faithfull ſervants of God, out of the zeal they have born to the Truth and their own ſafety, have all along from firſt to laſt, exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a power of private diſcretion in matters of Religion, and that without any diſallowance or contradiction, ſave what they have met with from the open Enemies of the Truth. Though the perſons they have had to deal with, have been never ſo eminent either in Church or State, either for their authority or abilities, yet have they not captivated their Judgements to them, but have freely and boldly taken their Doctrines and Precepts under examination, and tryed them by the Rule; and ſo far as they have found them anſwerable to it, they have embraced them, and ſo far as they have found them repugnant, they have rejected them. And whiles they did thus, they judg'd they did no more, than what
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:107190:55"/>did as well conſiſt, with the reſpect and duty they owed to them who were over them, as tend to their own neceſſary ſafety.<note place="margin">Exo. 1.16.</note> When the King of <hi>Egypt</hi> required the <hi>Midwives</hi> to kill the <hi>male children;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 22.17.</note> and when <hi>Saul</hi> commanded his Souldiers to ſlay the <hi>Prieſts;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kings 21.3.</note> and when <hi>Ahab</hi> will'd <hi>Naboth</hi> to let him have his <hi>Vineyard;</hi> and when <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> enjoyned the three Children to worſhip his <hi>Image;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 3.18.6.10.</note> and when <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> forbad <hi>Daniel</hi> to pray to <hi>his God;</hi> and when the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> urged the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples to <hi>waſh hands</hi> before Meat,<note place="margin">Mat. 15.2.</note> and when the <hi>Jews</hi> forbad the Apoſtles to <hi>preach Chriſt;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 4.19.</note> they all exerciſed this judgement, doing, not what was required, but what they in their own pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate apprehenſions and preſwaſions took to be their duty.<note place="margin">Act 17.11.</note> And when <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> preached the Goſpel to the <hi>Beraeans,</hi> they took their Doctrine to the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and tryed it thereby. They did not like a company of blinde, credulous Zealots, immediately receive it upon their recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, without any more ado, but like wiſe and ſober men, that deſired Truth rather than Novelty, they brought it to the Touch-ſtone, and made proof of it thereby. And this the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt</hi> was ſo far from diſliking that he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends them for it, nay beſtows upon them a title of ſpecial honour, which he hath inſerted in their ſtory, to be read in all the Churches to their perpetual praiſe. And after this manner the Saints and Martyrs behaved themſelves in after ages. They cloſed not with things upon the credit of thoſe who delivered them to them, how eminent ſoever they were, but according
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:107190:56"/>to the liberty allowed them by the great <hi>Prophet</hi> and <hi>Law-giver,</hi> they took them under <hi>Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and then judg'd of them and received them according to what they thereby found them.</p>
            <p n="13">13. That Chriſtians may and ought to uſe a judgement of private <hi>diſcretion,</hi> in enquiring into thoſe things which are offered to them, for their own information and ſatisfaction, do's ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear from the teſtimony of the <hi>Antients,</hi> who have in their Writings plainly, and fully given their judgements concerning it. I know Truth, and eſpecially ſuch as that is we have now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us, ſhines with its own beams, and needs no teſtimony from men, yet becauſe our adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries in this, as well as in other caſes, uſe to charge us with ſingularity and novelty, I ſhall a little enquire into what they have ſaid in this particular. And I ſhall begin with <hi>Clemens</hi> of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> a man of polite and exquiſite learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, who ſpeaking on the preſent Theme, ſaith, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Strom.</hi> l. 7.</note> 
               <hi>We muſt diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh by ſerious meditation, and diligent reaſoning, the Truth from that which appears to be ſo.</hi> And a little after, ſpeaking of the manner of the Chriſtians of his times, he adds, <hi>We believe not men abſolutely affirming, to whom it is lawfull to affirm the contrary. It is not ſufficient for them ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely to ſay that which ſeems good to them, but it behoves them to prove that which they ſay. Neither do we expect the teſtimony which is given of men, but we prove that which is enquired after, by the voyce of the Lord.</hi> According to him then, there
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:107190:56"/>is not any mortal man of ſuch credit, as that we ſhould preſently by a blinde, <hi>Pythagorean</hi> Faith aſſent to what he delivers, but we muſt call upon him for proof, and that out of the Holy Scriptures; and even then when he hath produced it, we muſt not preſently ſubmit, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till that by ſerious conſideration and diligent reaſoning, we have diſtinguiſhed Truth from Error.<note place="margin">Hom. <hi>2.</hi> in <hi>Ezek.</hi>
               </note> And hence it was that <hi>Origen</hi> who was his <hi>Scholar,</hi> adviſed his Hearers, <hi>Diligently to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, and receive the grace of the Spirit, from whom proceedeth the diſcerning of ſpirits, that ſo as good bankers they might obſerve when he taught Error, and when that which is pious and true.</hi> He would not have them to take all he delivered upon his Word, but as thoſe that were both impowred, and qualified for the trying of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, to uſe their own reaſon, and thereby ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve when he was in the right, and when in the wrong.<note place="margin">Inſtit. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> And herewith agrees that of <hi>Lactan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius; It behoves</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that in that wherein the reaſon of life conſiſts, every man ſhould rather truſt himſelf, and reſt on his own judgement, and his own ſenſes, in finding out and weighing of the Truth, than going upon truſt, (as one deſtitute of reaſon) be deceived by the errors of others. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſince it is innate to all to be wiſe, that is, to ſeek the Truth, thoſe bereave themſelves of wiſdom, that without judgement approve of the inventions of their Anceſtors, Et more peeudum, and after the manner of Beaſts are lead by others.</hi> In the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs of Salvation he would have people to be ſerious, and to employ themſelves in the ſtudy of Truth; and becauſe men are ſubject to Error,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:107190:57"/>he thinks it not ſafe for them to rely upon them; and ſhews, that in his apprehenſion it is no better than to act like thoſe that are deſtitute of reaſon, nay, to turn themſelves into beaſts, and therefore he will have them to uſe their own judgment and ſenſes, and to reſt on them. And anſwerable hereunto is that of <hi>Cyril</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Catech. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Believe me not</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>in whatſoever I ſhall ſimply deliver, unleſs thou ſhalt find the things which I ſhall ſpeak demonſtrated,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>out of the divine Scriptures; for the ſafety of faith depends not on the eloquence of language, but on the proofs that are brought out of the divine Scriptures.</hi> In which words he expreſly diſſuades us from taking things upon truſt, and he renders a ſubſtantial rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for it, which is, that the eſtabliſhment of faith hangs not upon the pretences or flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes of men, but upon the Word of God, by which we muſt ſee every thing confirmed ere we give entertainment to it. And <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Millain,</hi> was ſo far from being againſt this liberty, that he declares himſelf pleaſed with ſuch as made uſe of it. <hi>Ego bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficio annumero,</hi>
               <note place="margin">l. <hi>7.</hi> ep. <hi>47.</hi>
               </note> &amp;c. <hi>I take it for a favour</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>when any one that readeth my Writings, giveth me account of what doubts he there meeteth with, firſt, becauſe</hi> I <hi>may be deceived in thoſe very things which</hi> I <hi>know. And beſides, many things eſcape us; and ſome things ſound otherwiſe to ſome, than perhaps they do to me.</hi> He knew himſelf ſubject to Errors and Miſtakes, and therefore he would have ſuch as ſhould read his Writings, to uſe their own Judgement, and when they
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:107190:57"/>met with any thing they doubted of, to make their Exceptions, which he profeſſes he ſhould be ſo far from looking upon as any kind of arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancy, that he ſhould take it as a kindneſs. And <hi>Jerom,</hi> writing of the Religious <hi>Marcella,</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Proaem. in Epiſt. ad <hi>Galat.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>When I was at</hi> Rome <hi>ſhe never met me ſo haſtily, but ſhe ſtill asked me ſomething concerning the Scriptures; neither did ſhe, after the manner of the</hi> Pythagore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, <hi>think, whatſoever I anſwer'd was right: neither did authority without reaſon ſatisfie her, ſed exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabat omnia, &amp; ſagaci mente univerſa penſabat: but ſhe examined all, and with a skilful mind weighed every thing; ſo that I took my ſelf rather to have a judge of her than a learner.</hi> Though he were a man ſo eminent for his learning and piety, yet ſuch was her diſcreet and holy caution, that ſhe would not take things on the credit of his word, but ſate her ſelf, as it were, in judgment upon them, examined and weighed them; and he knowing it to be no more than her juſt and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary liberty, allowed her in it, nay, commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her for it. Hereunto likewiſe belongs that of <hi>Auguſtin</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Hippo;</hi>
               <note place="margin">De <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nit. eccl. c. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>I ſhall</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute it to my ſelf, if upon the words of men, I yield to Error, and be ſeduced from the flock of Chriſt, eſpecially ſince he hath admoniſhed me, ſaying, My ſheep hear my voice, and follow me. Let no man ſay to me, O what doth</hi> Donatus <hi>ſay, or what doth</hi> Parmenianus, <hi>or</hi> Pontius, <hi>or any other of them, quia nec Catholicis Epiſcopis conſentiendum eſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we muſt not conſent to the catholick Biſhops themſelves, if at any time it happen they be deceived ſo as to hold any thing againſt the divine Scriptures.</hi> Wherein he teaches, that ſince Chriſt hath called
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:107190:58"/>us to attend his voice, we muſt not leave him; that if upon the ſpecious pretences and fair words of any, we ſhould do it, we ſhould be without excuſe; that the moſt Catholick and Orthodox Biſhops are lyable to miſtakes; and that therefore we muſt not take what they or others ſay for Truth, till we have firſt try'd it by the Word, wherein the Voice of Chriſt ſounds, and found it conſonant there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. To theſe teſtimonies I ſhall only add that of <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hom. in. <hi>Mat. 24.</hi>
               </note> who deſcanting on thoſe words of our Saviour, <hi>When ye ſhall ſee the Abomination of Deſolation,</hi> &amp;c. thus delivers himſelf: <hi>When ye ſhall ſee impious hereſie, which is the hoſt of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, ſtanding in the holy places of the Church, then, let thoſe which are in</hi> Judea <hi>flee to the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains: that is, let thoſe which are Chriſtians be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take themſelves to the Scriptures. But wherefore do's he command all Chriſtians to betake themſelves to the Scriptures? becauſe in this time wherein hereſie hath prevailed upon the Churches, there can neither be any proof of true Chriſtianity, nor any other refuge of Chriſtians, willing to know the truth of Faith, but the divine Scriptures. Before time it was manifeſted divers wayes which was the Church of Chriſt, and which was Gentiliſm, but now it is known no way but by the Scriptures.</hi> The people then in time of prevailing hereſie, muſt not ſtand waiting upon the lips of their Teachers, but muſt betake themſelves to the Scriptures, which they are to look upon as their refuge, and make uſe of as the only ſure Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs, they have at ſuch a time to ſteer their courſe by. Were I minded to add more teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:107190:58"/>of this nature, <hi>Colloquium Ratisbonenſe,</hi> or <hi>Davenant,</hi> nay <hi>Gratian,</hi> to trouble no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter friends, would plentifully ſupply me; but I ſuppoſe it is needleſs. Thoſe I have already mentioned may ſuffice to ſhew you the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt the language of the godly Paſtors of the <hi>ancient</hi> Church, and the preſent Maſters of the <hi>Roman Synagogue.</hi> The <hi>former</hi> teach, that the people in matters of Religion muſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly examine and diligently conſider things; the <hi>latter</hi> ſay, they muſt not ſtand to examine or conſider, but muſt without any more ado aſſent and obey. The <hi>former</hi> ſay, they muſt not believe their Teachers any further than the reaſons they bring along with them ſerve to convince and perſwade them; the <hi>latter</hi> ſay, they muſt believe them upon their bare word, without any reaſon at all. The <hi>former</hi> ſay, they muſt uſe their own reaſon; and that acting otherwiſe they play the beaſts; the <hi>latter</hi> ſay, they muſt not uſe it, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve. The <hi>former</hi> ſay, the word of men, how wiſe or holy ſoever they are, is no good bottom for their Faith; the <hi>latter</hi> ſay, it is ſufficient. The <hi>former</hi> commend ſuch for their diſcretion as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to take up with the words of their Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers when they carry not reaſon along with them; the <hi>latter</hi> cenſure and condemn them for ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as guilty of no leſs than incredulity and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſneſs. The <hi>former</hi> teach, that they muſt not regard what men ſay, but what the Scriptures ſay; the <hi>latter,</hi> that they muſt not enquire what the Scriptures ſay, but what they ſay. The <hi>former</hi> teach, that the Scriptures are their only Refuge and Security; the <hi>latter,</hi> that the reading
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:107190:59"/>of them is dangerous, and tends to no other than Hereſie and confuſion. And now I appeal to all perſons that have the leaſt grain of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and ſincerity, whether the Ancients are for us or our adverſaries; whether they are for the peoples trying the Doctrines of their Teachers or againſt it. He that hath the face to gainſay ſuch clear teſtimonies as theſe, ſhall by my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, as an obſtinate enemy to truth and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, be left to diſpute with himſelf, whether he be in his wits or no.</p>
            <p n="13">13. The caſe is ſo plain, that divers of the more grave and ſober ſort of the Papiſts them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, concurre with us, and plead for a power in the people to judge of Doctrines as well as we. Thoſe of latter times judging it inconſiſtent with the honour of their Clergy and the ſafety of their Religion, which they maintain by keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their people in ignorance, are utterly againſt it; but divers that lived in the ages paſt, before the myſtery of Iniquity attain'd to its full ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, are peremptory for it, as a certain right be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to them, without which they can neither act like reaſonable creatures, nor make due pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion for their own happineſs. I ſhall inſtance in ſome few; and begin with <hi>Aquinas,</hi> the <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelick Doctor,</hi> whoſe Judgment, amongſt thoſe againſt whom I now diſpute is (to uſe the words of the Holy Ghoſt touching the Counſel of <hi>Ahithophel</hi>) <hi>as if a man ſhould enquire at the Oracle of God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid.</hi> Dave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. <hi>in</hi> Col. 3.23. <hi>p.</hi> 255.</note> 
               <hi>Every one</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is bound to examine his own actions, by the knowledge he hath of God, whether it be natural, acquired, or infuſed: Omnis enim homo debet ſecundum rationem agere, for every
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:107190:59"/>man ought to do according to reaſon.</hi> Whereby it appears that notwithſtanding his zeal and devotion to the <hi>See</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> yet he thought that every man ſhould make proof of his own performances of what nature ſoever they are, whether enjoyn'd by Superiours or taken up of his own free choice, ere he ſet upon them, and that to proceed otherwiſe, is contrary to reaſon. To him I ſhall add the famous <hi>Picus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De fide &amp; ord. cred. Theor. <hi>22.</hi> p. <hi>307.</hi>
               </note> Earl of <hi>Mirandula,</hi> the Mirror of his time and Nation. <hi>If</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>doubtings do ariſe which of the differing parties do's more reſt upon Evangelical Verity, the ſentence muſt by no means be given precipitantly; but the Truth that commits it ſelf to the mindes of the faithfull, is to be expected, librato judicio, from a poiſed judgement, and in the mean time God is to be intreated for the diſcerning of ſpirits, and the holy Scriptures to be conſulted.</hi> A paſſage ſo full againſt the Popiſh <hi>implicit</hi> faith, that I could wiſh it were engraven on all the doors and Pillars in <hi>Rome,</hi> that ſo they might ſee that that man who was born, brought up, and ſo much admired amongſt them, hath given his teſtimony againſt them. He would not have people be ſuch fools, as to take things upon truſt, but to weigh them in the ballance of their own private Judgements, pray to God for direction, ſearch the Scriptures, and then give ſentence according thereunto. <hi>Lud. Vives</hi> is of the ſame minde:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Verit. ſid.</hi> l. 3. p. 457.</note> 
               <hi>Diligence and enquiry</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>avail to the finding out of Truth, but ſlothfulneſs and negligence bring forth Error. If you neither enquire nor ſearch concerning any mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, you will eaſily be deceived, but if you look and enquire into the cauſes and reaſons, Veritas ſeſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feret,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:107190:60"/>the truth will ſhew it ſelf.</hi> His opinion is, that careful and diligent enquiry into the grounds and reaſons of things, is the ready way to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover and find out the truth; whereas a credulous ſlothfulneſs, that will rather take up with any thing than be at the pains of trial, leads to nothing but errors and miſtakes. And indeed it is a thing ſo obvious, that had not men almoſt renounc'd their reaſon, it would be needleſs to produce teſtimonies to evince it.<note place="margin">De vanit. ſcient. c. <hi>100.</hi> de verb. dei. p. <hi>475.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Cornelius Agrippa</hi> is very plain and full, <hi>We ought</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>to examine all the diſciplines of ſciences, and all opinions, by the word of God, as the Lydius Lapis or touchſtone thereof, and in all things flee unto it, ceu ad ſolidiſſimam petram, as unto a moſt ſure rock, and by it onely judge of all opinions and ways.</hi> He thinks it not ſafe for us to cloſe with ſciences and opinions as ſoon as they are offered to us, or upon the firſt view we take of them, as moſt do; but he would have us to prove and try them. And the touch-ſtone whereby we muſt do it, is the Word of God; we muſt not try them by carnal reaſon, humane authority, or any ſuch deceitful thing, but we muſt take them to the Word, and try them by it, and by it ſolely, as being the onely ſure rock our faith hath to reſt upon.<note place="margin">Prefat. in qunt. lib. ſentent.</note> 
               <hi>Durand</hi> ſpeaks not without ſome indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, <hi>He that captivates</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>his reaſon to humane authority, incidit in inſipientiam beſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, falls into beaſtly folly.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Of Wiſd. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>218.</hi>
               </note> And <hi>Charron</hi> ſpeaks to the ſame purpoſe, <hi>To go about</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive a man of this right, is to make him no more a man but a beaſt.</hi> And if we ask <hi>Silveſter</hi> the <hi>Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitor,</hi> he will tell us,<note place="margin">In verb. ſcrupulus.</note> that <hi>to interpret the precepts
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:107190:60"/>of men by a judgment of diſcretion in the court of conſcience, pertinet ad quemlibet pro facto ſuo, belongs to every one for his own practice.</hi> And to trouble you with no more, this was one thing that <hi>Paulus <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enetus Fulgentius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tract. de Interdict. Paul. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> and the other <hi>Venetian</hi> Divines, ſtood upon, <hi>That every man might and ought to diſcern of every ſuperiours pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, even the Popes himſelf, whether it were lawful and convenient, or no.</hi> Now do but obſerve what difference there is betwixt the doctrine of theſe men, and that of <hi>Bellarmine</hi> and ſuch like; the former following the Scriptures, and treading the ſteps of the <hi>ancients,</hi> ſay, that the people may judge and try ſuch things as in the buſineſs of Religion are tendred to them, before they cloſe with them; nay, that in purſuance of their own ſafety, they ought to do it, and that if they do otherwiſe, they let go their neceſſary liberty, and do no leſs than turn beaſts. The <hi>latter</hi> ſay, that they neither may nor ought to do it; that their buſineſs is to hear their Teachers, in doing whereof they provide ſufficiently for their ſafety; and that to queſtion what they deliver, is no other than needleſs ſcrupuloſity and vain arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance. Whether of the two is in the right, I leave you to judge by what hath been ſpoken.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Having in theſe fore-going particulars evinced to you, that the people have the power of judging contended for, I ſhall in the next place ſhew you the lightneſs and vanity of thoſe objections and pretences, that are made by <hi>Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerus, Valentia, Bellarmine,</hi> and others, againſt it, which though I ſhall not mention either in their own words or order, yet I ſhall give you the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:107190:61"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:107190:61"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:107190:62"/>ſcope and ſenſe of them. And they alledge,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> 1. It is the pleaſure of God, to whom it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to determine the rights and duties of men, that the people ſhould conſult their Teachers, and not like or diſlike, chuſe or refuſe, as they themſelves ſhall think meet, but as their Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ſhall inſtruct and direct them. <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.8-12. <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.7. <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.2, 3.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That people ought in doubtful caſes to conſult their Miniſters, and take inſtructions from them, theſe places evince, and we never denied it; but that either their Miniſters ſhould be infallible, or that they ſhould aſſent to all they ſay as truth, or obey all they command as law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, without exerciſing any private judgment for their own ſatisfaction, they afford no proof at all.<note place="margin">Deut. 17.9. <hi>De Jud. c.</hi> 21. <hi>p.</hi> 123.</note> As for thoſe words, <hi>They ſhall ſhew thee the ſentence of judgment,</hi> they are not (as <hi>Davenant</hi> notes) <hi>verba promittentis ſed mandantis, words of promiſe, but of command;</hi> ſhewing not what the Prieſts <hi>would</hi> do, but what in purſuance of their office they <hi>ought</hi> to do. And ſhall we reaſon, <hi>à jure ad factum,</hi> from what they <hi>ought</hi> to do, to what they <hi>would</hi> do? what more ordinary than for men to neglect what they <hi>ought</hi> to do, and inſtead thereof do what they have a <hi>mind</hi> to do? But admit they were not words of <hi>command,</hi> but <hi>promiſe,</hi> yet were they not to be taken in an <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute</hi> ſenſe, but <hi>cum conditione annexâ,</hi> with a condition adjoyned, <hi>viz.</hi> if they ſhould conſult the Law, follow the direction of it, and teach according to it;<note place="margin">Reynolds Conf. ch. <hi>7.</hi> div. <hi>4.</hi> p. <hi>262.</hi>
               </note> then they ſhould indeed <hi>give the ſentence of judgment,</hi> otherwiſe not. This <hi>Hart</hi> acknowledges, and rejects the <hi>Rabbi</hi>'s gloſs
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:107190:62"/>upon the place for <hi>abſolute</hi> obedience, as abſurd and fooliſh. As for thoſe words,<note place="margin">Mal. 2.7.</note> 
               <hi>The prieſts lips ſhould keep knowledge,</hi> the ſame anſwer may ſerve; they hold not forth what they <hi>would</hi> do, but what they <hi>ſhould</hi> do. The holy Ghoſt was ſo far from intending to ſignifie any unerring power in the prieſts by them, that he does in the very next words ſhew their liableneſs to miſtake, and how lamentably they had even already done it, in departing from that rule they were appointed to walk by. <hi>Ye are departed</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>out of the way, ye have cauſed many to ſtumble at the law, ye have corrupted the covenant of Levi — Ye have not kept my ways, but have been partial in my Law.</hi> And is it then to be imagined that he took theſe to be infallible, or that he would have the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to believe all that they ſaid, or do all that they required? In like manner, when our Saviour ſaith, <hi>The ſcribes and phariſees ſit in Moſes ſeat;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 23.2.</note> his meaning is not that they did orthodoxly, ſincerely and truly expound the Law, but that it was their office and duty to do it. And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the holy Ghoſt does in theſe ſeveral places re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire the people to betake themſelves to the prieſts, hear them and obſerve them, his mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is not that they ſhould do it in all things, without exception, but onely when they taught according to the Law, which they were appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to expound and interpret. As for inſtance, the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> taught, that our Saviour was a <hi>deceiver,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 27.63. Joh. 9.22.</note> and forbad the people to <hi>confeſs</hi> him; now I demand whether they were bound to believe and obey them herein, yea or no? If they were, then they were bound to believe a
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:107190:63"/>lie, gainſay the truth, and undo their ſouls. If not, then theſe words are to be taken in a limited ſenſe, which is the thing contended for. The ſum of all then is this, That it is the duty of Miniſters to teach the truth, and require nothing but what is according to Scripture; which ſo long as they do, the people are to believe and obey them; but when they do otherwiſe, they muſt neither believe nor obey them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> 2. There is a belief due to all men in their own profeſſion; we believe <hi>Lawyers, Phyſicians,</hi> &amp; others, even when we do not underſtand them: Religion therefore being in a peculiar manner the profeſſion of Miniſters, in the ſtudy whereof they have employed themſelves all along, it ſeems to be no more than reaſonable that private perſons ſhould rather confide in them, than rely upon their own judgments.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. There are ſome private perſons, who though they profeſs not <hi>Law, Phyſick,</hi> or any ſuch faculty, yet by their ſtudy and induſtry have attained to ſuch skill in them, that they are able to inſtruct many that do; and that theſe either believe or ought to believe ſuch as do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs them in all they ſay, without ſo much as en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring after the grounds they proceed on, none will affirm. 2. The reaſon wherefore the people do commonly believe ſuch as profeſs theſe facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, upon their bare word, is not becauſe they may not exerciſe a judgment of diſcretion to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards what they deliver, but becauſe they are utterly unſtudied in ſuch matters, and ſo are unable to do it. But it is not ſo with them in the buſineſs of Religion; for as the knowledge
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:107190:63"/>of it is more attainable than the knowledge of other faculties, (I mean ſo much as is neceſſary to ſalvation) ſo they look upon themſelves as more concern'd in it, and upon that account take more pains in the ſtudy of it. 3. There is a great deal of difference to be put betwixt the things of the world, and the things of religion and ſalvation; in the former, people may go upon truſt,<note place="margin">Joh. 6.69. 2 Pet. 1.10.</note> and content themſelves with uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain probabilities; but in the latter, they muſt, as the Scripture ſhews, make <hi>ſure</hi> work. Were ſalvation as frivolous a thing as thoſe of the world are, they might better venture upon hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane authority; but being it is a matter of ſuch high importance, they muſt, as I ſay, make ſure work, not reſting until they have attain'd to a well-grounded certainty, and ſuch as may ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port them in an hour of temptation. Now how can they do this, while they take things upon truſt, and that from thoſe who are ſubject to error as well as themſelves?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> 3. But the common people, for the moſt part, are ſo ignorant, that they know little or nothing what belongs to Religion, and therefore it is not fit, that when Teachers in purſuance of their office have delivered to them doctrines and precepts, they ſhould have liberty to judge them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. There be few worthy the name of Chriſtians ſo ignorant, but they are <hi>pro modulo ſuo,</hi> in ſome competent meaſure able to do it, at leaſt in all things of neceſſity to ſalvation. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more certain than that many private perſons do in knowledge, underſtanding, judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and other abilities, far exceed their
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:107190:64"/>Teachers; and many amongſt the common people have poſſeſs'd the truth, and ſtoutly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended it, when their Teachers have either been ignorant of it, or forſaken it. Divers of our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries themſelves (as <hi>Toſtatus</hi> ſhews) hold,<note place="margin">Prolegom. in Evangel.</note> that from the time of <hi>Chriſts ſuffering,</hi> until his <hi>reſurrection, fides in ſolâ remanſit beatâ Virgine, the faith remain'd in the bleſſed Virgin alone.</hi> So that according to them, though ſhe were a weak and frail woman, one of that ſex, which is the more ignorant as well as timerous; yet ſhe ſtuck to the truth, when her Teachers had relinquiſhed and forſaken it. But, 2. admit that ſome be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together unable to exerciſe ſuch a judgment, muſt their inability deſtroy the liberty and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge of others? Some want eyes, muſt not thoſe therefore who have them uſe them? Some have no underſtanding, muſt thoſe therefore who are endued with it be dealt with as if they were in the ſame condition? that is unreaſonable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> 4. But to allow all that will to judge the doctrines and decrees of their Teachers, is the way to confuſion; this is it that fills the Church with endleſs diſputes; whereas if they would acquieſce in what they deliver, all would be in peace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. There is not any liberty or privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge belonging to any order or degree of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in the Church, nay, in the world, but through the depravation of mans nature it is ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of being abuſed, and made ſerviceable to bad ends and purpoſes; which yet is no ſufficient reaſon wherefore it ſhould be thought unlawful, or being thought lawful ſhould be aboliſhed and
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:107190:64"/>laid aſide. Kings and Princes have an undoubted liberty of exerciſing civil policy and government over their people, and is there any Nation in the world that cannot witneſs it hath been abuſed to arbitrarineſs and tyranny? and yet our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries will not ſay that this is a ſufficient rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon wherefore it ſhould either be thought un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful, or laid aſide. And if the liableneſs of Kings and Princes to abuſe the liberty they have to govern their people, be no ſufficient reaſon wherefore it ſhould be thought unlawful, or being thought lawful, be laid aſide; then wherefore ſhould the liableneſs of the people to abuſe the liberty they have to judge doctrines, be look'd upon as a ſufficient reaſon, wherefore it ſhould either be thought unlawful, or being thought lawful ſhould be laid aſide? 2. God knows how to frame a Charter for his Church without any direction from men; and therefore ſince he hath (as I have already ſhew'd) granted the people ſuch a liberty, thoſe who are over them ſhould, without any gain-ſaying, allow it them, let the iſſue be what it will. He fore-ſaw from the beginning, when he ſate in counſel about this liberty, the inconveniences as well as the conveniences that would attend it, which yet he look'd not upon as any ſufficient reaſon wherefore he ſhould with-hold it from them. And if he thought not the inconveniences which he fore-ſaw a ſufficient reaſon, wherefore he ſhould, before he had granted it, with-hold it from them; much leſs ſhould men, how great or eminent ſoever, think the inconveniences, which they find attending it, a ſufficient reaſon where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:107190:65"/>they ſhould withhold it, after he hath grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it to them. 3. Admit God had not granted this liberty, yet common prudence, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the inconveniences pretended, would have prompted the people to claim and exerciſe it. For where inconveniences do occurre on both ſides, the leſs are ſtill to be choſen; and ſure it's a far leſs evil for the people to labour under ſome diſputes, which God often-times over-rules for his Churches good, than that they ſhould follow their Teachers into error, hereſie and profaneneſs; nay, into Hell it ſelf, which they muſt needs expoſe themſelves to the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain danger of, unleſs they maintain and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe this liberty. But 4. If Implicit Faith be ſuch a notable Antidote againſt diviſions, how comes it to paſs, that our adverſaries, who urge it with ſo much ſeverity, have ſo many amongſt them, which all the <hi>Magick</hi> of the <hi>Papal</hi> Chair cannot conjure down? Whence is it that their Bells do in the hearing of all <hi>Chriſtendome,</hi> ring ſuch clamorous and angry diſcords? Whence came the difference betwixt the <hi>Dominicans</hi> and <hi>Franciſcans,</hi> about the <hi>immaculate</hi> Conception of the Virgin <hi>Mary;</hi> betwixt the <hi>Janſeniſts</hi> and <hi>Moliniſts</hi> about <hi>Grace;</hi> betwixt the <hi>Italian</hi> and <hi>French</hi> Papiſts about the <hi>head</hi> of the Church? If blinde obedience be ſuch a notable means to maintain unity, and ſecure the peace, how comes it thus to paſs, that they have ſuch diverſity of Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions amongſt them, agitated with ſo much heat and vehemency, that they are every day thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring out their <hi>Anathena's</hi> againſt each other? I know they perſwade their deluded followers,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:107190:65"/>that all the differences are amongſt the <hi>Proie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi> (which they tell them ariſe from our ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering the people to read the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> exerciſe this liberty of <hi>judging.</hi> and the like) but as for them there is nothing but unity and peace; there is not ſo much, as the <hi>noyſe</hi> of an <hi>hammer,</hi> or any jarring to be heard amongſt them. But this is ſo notoriouſly falſe, that there is not any ſave thoſe who are as ignorant as their people whom they keep in ſuch Lamentable dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and bondage, but they know the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> 5. If people may call in queſtion the definitions and concluſions of their Teachers, then they may <hi>judicare judices,</hi> judge their Judges, which is contrary to reaſon, and inconſiſtent with that Order God hath ſet up and eſtabliſhed in the World.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Though it be granted that their Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers may in ſome reſpects be termed their <hi>Judges,</hi> yet they may notwithſtanding, without offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any injury to Reaſon or Order, call in queſtion what they deliver to them. For the underſtanding whereof you muſt note, there is a twofold Judgement. 1. There is <hi>judicium fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See Voetius polit. eccl. p. <hi>1.</hi> l. <hi>2.</hi> tract. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi> p. <hi>897.</hi>
               </note> a publick Judgement, which belongs to thoſe who have Authority and Juriſdiction over others, by virtue whereof they may make Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions and Decrees for the directing and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulating of their practice. 2. There is <hi>judicium rationale,</hi> a private Judgement; and this belongs to every individual perſon, who is indued with a power of judging the Decrees of the higheſt Court on Earth, <hi>quantum ad ſe ſpectant,</hi> ſo far
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:107190:66"/>as they belong to him, and concern his own par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular duty. The difference betwixt theſe two Judgements lies in this; in the former a man iudges, <hi>propter alium,</hi> for the direction of others: in the latter <hi>propter ſe,</hi> for the ordering of his own duty. Now if the people ſhould take upon them the <hi>former</hi> of theſe, they would indeed do that which is contrary to the rules of <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Order,</hi> but their taking upon them the latter, is no more contrary thereunto, than is their opening of their eyes, that they amy ſee their way as they go in the ſtreets. In exerciſing this Judgement upon the Decrees of their Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours, if they find them according to the rule, they cloſe with them, if not, they decline them; yet withall ſubmit to the penalty of their diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience. And what is there in this contrary to Reaſon or Order?<note place="margin">Theſ. Salm. de ſum. Jud. ſect. <hi>49.</hi> p. <hi>120.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>this is not</hi> (as <hi>Cappellus</hi> ſhews) <hi>to overthrow good Order, or introduce into the Church any confuſion, but to maintain the right and liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty planted in the heart of man by Nature it ſelf, namely, that none be compelled to renounce his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and contrary to the dictate thereof by a blinde and brutiſh motion, to follow and embrace whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it ſhall pleaſe certain men out of meer humour to command, adverſus perfectiſſimam omnis ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri juſti, &amp; equi normam, againſt the moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect rule of truth, righteouſneſs and equity, namely the Word of God contained in the ſacred Scripture.</hi> This is certainly the courſe that the faithfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God have obſerved all along under the ſeveral powers they have had to do with; and if ever we mean to be found faithfull we muſt do the like.</p>
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:107190:66"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> 6. But in all well govern'd Commonwealths, it is thought fit, that Subjects ſhould ſubmit to the ſentence of the Magiſtrates that bear rule therein, without contradiction or cenſure; and if ſo, why ſhould not the peoplw in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſubmit to the ſentence of their Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is uſual with our adverſaries in this controverſie to confound publick and private Judgement; and hence it is that moſt of their arguments are nothing at all to the purpoſe. The Judgement we contend for, is a <hi>private, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional, diſcretive</hi> Judgement, allowed by God for the directing of every man in his own particular practice. That which they mainly diſpute a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, is a <hi>publick, miniſterial, authoritative</hi> Judgment ſerving to determine and limit others, which we never challeng'd to any priveate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, how well qualfied ſoever. And this they ſeem to underſtand when they ſay, that in all well ordered Common-wealths, it is thought fit that Subjects ſhould ſubmit to the ſentence of the Magiſtrate; elſe they ſpeak moſt falſly, and belye the World; for there is not any Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth therein, that is indeed well ordered, but they allow their Subjects to read, ſtudy, and judge of the ſenſe and equity of their Laws, for their own private uſe, and to do otherwiſe is to deal with them rather like Beaſts than Men. Beſides, it were abſurd for Magiſtrates to direct commands againſt thoſe actions of men which fall not under their obſervation and cognizance. Now the private judging of their ſentence is a thing of this Nature (for after they have done
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:107190:67"/>all they can, their ſubjects will judge of it as they ſhall finde it by the light of their own rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and they be never the wiſer) and therefore it ſeems not to be proper for them, to deliver commands againſt it. And thus I have given you an anſwer to the moſt material objections, our adverſaries urge againſt us in this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar. Some others they have, but what I have already alledg'd will ſupply with anſwers; and therefore I ſhall not ſpend more time in making particular returns to them.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Leſt any ſhould take occaſion from what hath been ſaid, to miſinterpret the Apoſtle, or conceive that to be meant by him which he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver intended, I ſhall here, before I enter upon the Uſes, propound ſomewhat by way of <hi>cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Though he thought it not convenient that we ſhould receive the Doctrinie of our Teachers, till we have firſt made proof of it, yet we muſt not think that this do's evacuate or make void their function. The imperfections and infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that attend them in their Miniſtrations, do not nullifie their Office, no more than thoſe that attend the Magiſtracy do nullifie it; but rather ſerve to ſet forth the wiſdom and power of God, that can by ſuch weak and deſpicable Inſtruments accompliſh ſuch high and eminent effects; that can by ſuch broken Veſſels convey the Oyl of Grace into the hearts of his choſen. Their calling and work determine not with every Error, they may through ignorance or inadvertency be guilty of, but are to continue throughout all Generations. They are entruſted
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:107190:67"/>and that ſolely (unleſs ſome <hi>extraordinary</hi> caſe occurre) with the diſpenſation of perpetual Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances;<note place="margin">Mal. 28. 20.</note> they are under perpetual Promiſes;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.26.</note> the Churches neceſſity of them will be perpetual;<note place="margin">Acts 8.30. Rev. 2.5.</note> the removal of them is threatned as one of the ſoreſt Judgements that can befall a people; all which, with many other particulars that might be mentioned, do plainly ſhew, it is the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and deſign of God that their Office ſhall be perpetual, that is, continue to the end of the World. However things go, yet Chriſt will keep up a Miniſtry in his Church,<note place="margin">Eph. 4.12. 1 Cor. 15.24.</note> that ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manin untill be have <hi>perfected</hi> his <hi>Saints,</hi> and ſhall <hi>deliver up the Kingdom to his Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Though he forbid us to reſt upon their au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority yet he would not have us to forſake them, and over-run their Miniſtry. Their being lyable to miſtakes do's not diſoblige us from <hi>at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending</hi> on them, and hearing them, but from <hi>confiding</hi> in them; and that in ſuch a degree, as to take whatever they ſay for truth, without enquiring any further. His admoniſhing us to prove what they deliver, do's not forbid the hearing them, but ſuppoſe it, nay, command and enjoyn it; for how could he think we ſhould be able or fit to bring their Doctrine to tryall, and pſs our Judgement upon it, unleſs we be preſent, and hear it? This I ſpeak of ſuch as are <hi>lawfull</hi> Miniſters of the Goſpel, and <hi>anſwer</hi> the end of their Calling; as for <hi>intruders</hi> and <hi>uſurpers</hi> that neither regard their <hi>own,</hi> nor <hi>others</hi> ſouls, I have nothing to ſay for them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Though he be againſt our making them Lords of our Faith, yet he would not have us
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:107190:68"/>to ſlight them, or carry our ſelves irreverently or contemptuouſly towards them. No, he will have us, (as you may ſee in the preceding verſes) <hi>to know them, and eſteem thim very highly in love for their works ſake.</hi> And he ſtill gives it in charge to thoſe to whom he either preaches or writes, that they be mindfull of their Teachers, look upon them as the Miniſters of the Goſopel, and yield them ſuch reſpect as may encourage tehm to the cheerfull diſcharge of their duty, and the laying out of themſelves for their good. Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit our Teachers be guilty of miſtakes in Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and miſcarriages in Life, yet we muſt remember they are the <hi>Ambaſſadors</hi> or Chriſt, whom he hath entruſted with the Miniſtry of <hi>reconciliation,</hi> and as ſuch we are both to receive and reſpect them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Though he call upon us to prove what they deliver, and ſatisfie our ſelves concerning the lawfulneſs of it, ere we entertain it, yet he do's not mean that we muſt take nothing at all upon truſt from them. In thoſe things where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we have no reaſon to ſuſpect them either of weakneſs or falſhood, or wherein we are alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether uncapable of making a Judgement our ſelves, we not only may but ought to truſt them, as the beſt ſecurity we have to reſt upon. Such as are wholly illiterate are to believe it is a Bible wherein the Miniſter reads, and that he reads true and not falſe; and ſuch as have at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd further, are to believe, that the Bible wherein he reads is rightly tranſlated out of the Originals; that the Copies were authentick out of which the Tranſlation was made; that
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:107190:68"/>(as credible Authors mention) there were ſuch things done in ages paſt, and ſuch cuſtoms and obſervations among the <hi>Jews,</hi> and other Nations, which do greatly ſerve to the clearing of many dark places of Scripture, nay, which are ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to be known, that without acquaintance with them, many places cannot be underſtood. Herein as we truſt our Lawyers and Phyſicians, ſo we mauſt them; not but that we may, if we have ability and opportunity, enquire into thoſe things our ſelves, or if we have reaſon to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpcet our own Teachers, conſult with others; but that in caſe we want ability and opportunity, or have no reaſon of ſuſpicion, we then may and ought to truſt them, as the beſt light and ſecurity we have. We muſt diſtinguiſh betwixt matters of <hi>doctrin,</hi> and matters of <hi>fact;</hi> or betwixt <hi>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrins,</hi> and ſuch things as are <hi>ſubſervient</hi> thereunto. To believe the <hi>former</hi> upon the credit of our Teachers, is to reſolve our faith into <hi>humane</hi> teſtimony; but to believe the <hi>latter,</hi> ſuch as the trueneſs of Copies or Tranſlations, upon their word, is no more a reſolving of our faith into <hi>humane</hi> teſtimony, than the Apoſtles believing what they ſaw with their eyes, reſolved their faith into <hi>ſenſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Though he enjoyns us to <hi>prove all things,</hi> yet he would not have us to run after every new light, or hear every one that of his own accord, without any juſt call, ſhall take upon him to preach to us: this he was ſo far from either commanding or allowing, that by the ſpirit of propheſie, foretelling the diſorders and miſcarriages ſome Chriſtians ſhould be guilty of
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:107190:69"/>in after ages, he mentions this one, that <hi>having itching ears,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.3.</note> 
               <hi>they ſhould heap to themſelves teachers:</hi> and what is the iſſue of it? why, for ſaking <hi>the truth,</hi> they <hi>turn unto fables.</hi> And what he fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told, we our ſelfves ſee abundantly accompliſhed in our days; for ſuch is the indiſcretion and le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity of people, that they are ready to go forth at the <hi>ſhaking</hi> of <hi>every reed,</hi> anſwer the call of every Bell, and ſit down at the feet of every one that hath the confidence to open his mouth to them. What is this but (as <hi>Calvin</hi> well notes upon the Text) <hi>ad omnes errorum ventos, ſe temerè exponere, raſhly to expoſe themſelves to all the winds of errors,</hi> which out of a due ſenſe of their own frailty they ſhould carefully ſhun and avoid. For a man to forſake his own Teacher, and the wholeſome food he is inured to, and hath by the bleſſing of God happily grown under, and run after ſtrangers, is no other than to tempt God to deliver him up to deluſions, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage Impoſtors in their work.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Though he would have us to try things ere we cloſe with them, yet he would not have us turn <hi>Academicks</hi> or <hi>Scepticks,</hi> call in queſtion received princ iples, and doubt of every thing which comes before us; that is to run from one extreme into another, diſſolve the very fabrick of Religion, and put an abſolute ſtop to the duty and ſervice we owe to God. As we muſt not <hi>believe</hi> all things, ſo neither muſt we <hi>douht</hi> of all things, but we muſt walk in a mean be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt theſe two extremes. As for <hi>new</hi> matters, we muſt firſt try them, and then if we ſee cauſe, maintain them; but for <hi>old, ſtanding, tried</hi>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:107190:69"/>points, that have clear foundation in Scripture, and which we have upon good grounds received long ago, we muſt rather maintain than try them. The Apoſtles advice is, that what is new and doubtful that we ſhould <hi>try;</hi> and what we have tried and found good, that we ſhould <hi>hold faſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. Having thus handled the <hi>doctrinal</hi> part of this diſcourſe, and therein ſhewed what is meant by <hi>proving, what</hi> is to be proved, <hi>who</hi> are to make this proof, what it is <hi>by</hi> which it muſt be made, after what <hi>manner</hi> it muſt be manag'd; given you ſome <hi>arguments</hi> for it, anſwered the <hi>objections</hi> againſt it, and propounded ſome <hi>cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions:</hi> I ſhall now paſs to the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes,</hi> and therein ſhew how far this point concerns the world at this day, and what improvement is to be made of it.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> And 1. If Chriſtians muſt <hi>prove all things,</hi> then it may ſerve for the <hi>confutation</hi> and <hi>conviction</hi> of all thoſe proud Maſters, who deny the people have any liberty allowed them by God to try the doctrines and preſcriptions of their Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours. Of this ſort are the Jewiſh <hi>Rabbies,</hi> the Mahometan <hi>Prieſts,</hi> the Popiſh <hi>Prelates,</hi> with ſome others, who think the people are ſo far in ſubjection to them, that they ought to receive their determinations, and impoſitions, let them be what they will, without any ſcruple or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception whatſoever. They take themſelves to be no leſs than abſolute Lords, and therefore as they look upon it as their work to teach and command, ſo they look upon it as the peoples work to believer and obey; and upon their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:107190:70"/>to do it, they preſently fall upon them and perſecute them, as rebellious againſt good order and government, and upon that account worthy of the greateſt ſeverity that can be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted on them. Now what horrible tyranny and cruelty is this?<note place="margin">1 Pet. 5.3.</note> what lording it is this <hi>over Gods heritage?</hi> how contrary to the light of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and common reaſon? how diſſonant to the doctrine of the Prophets and Apoſtles, and in particular to that of <hi>Paul</hi> in this place, <hi>prove all things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>2</label> 2. If Chriſtians muſt <hi>prove all things,</hi> then it may be uſeful by way of <hi>informaaation,</hi> to acquaint us, 1. what reſpect we are to ſhew to the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrins and precepts of ſuch as diſpenſe the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel to us. We muſt not look upon all their words as Oracles, proceeding from an infallible ſpirit; but we muſt receive them with ſuſpicion, as coming from thoſe that have darkneſs in them as well as light, and ſo may ſpeak error as well as truth.<note place="margin">Acts 12.22.</note> We muſt not, like <hi>Herod</hi>'s flattering hearers, as ſoon as they ſpeak, cry out, it is <hi>the voice of God and not of a man;</hi> but out of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect we bear, both to the truth and our own ſafety; we muſt take what they ſay to the rule, examine it hereby, and then judge of it accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the agreement it hath therewith. We muſt indeed be peaceable and charitable, yet we muſt not put out our eyes, or hood-wink our ſelves, and ſo like a company of blind fools and idiots, ſuffer men to lead us whither they pleaſe; but whiles we have eyes we muſt make uſe of them for our neceſſary direction and ſecurity. That we muſt reverence ſuch as are our Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:107190:70"/>is granted, yet we muſt not think that Chriſt is every where, he is ſaid to be; or that every one ſpeaks truth that pretends to it: but we muſt try, and then conclude as we find cauſe. The Apoſtle indeed diſcourſing of charity, ſaith, it <hi>believeth all things;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.7.</note> but we muſt not think his meaning is, that we ſhould be ſo charitable as to give credit to impoſtors, or aſſent to what ever is delivered to us; then we muſt believe the <hi>Jews,</hi> when they tell us, that the Goſpel, which he took ſo much pains in preaching, is a meer fable; but that we ſhould be ſo charitable as not to rejeet things out of prejudice, or ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs diſlike, or with-hold our aſſent when we have no cauſe or reaſon for it. If upon due ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination of thoſe points which are delivered to us we find they have no foundation in the Word, we may without any violating of charity, or falſifying the Apoſtles doctrin in the leaſt, not onely with-hold our aſſent from them, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject them with indignation and contempt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If Chriſtians muſt <hi>prove all things,</hi> then Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is no trivial buſineſs, but ſuch as calls for skill, care and diligence. Carnal men, that know little of the nature of it, look upon it as a plain, eaſie, homely thing, that hath little intricacy in it: but it is not ſo; it hath that in it that will find work for the ableſt parts and greateſty dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence. As it is a moſt deſirable and honourable, ſo it is a moſt ingenious and accurate thing to be a ſound, well principl'd, ſincere Chriſtian. There are in it many deep myſteries to be div'd into, many intricate caſes to be reſolved, many tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations both from within and without to be
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:107190:71"/>withſtood, which no ſuch things as ignorance, careleſneſs or ſlothfulneſs are ſit to encounter with. He that will be a right Chriſtian, and faithfully perform his Maſters work, muſt have a good eye, uſe circumſpection and take pains, elſe he will never attain the ends he aims at. The Diſciples gathered from the diſcourſe of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour concerning rich men,<note place="margin">Luke 18.26.</note> that it was an hard matter to be <hi>ſaved.</hi> And if it be an hard matter to be ſaved, then it muſt needs be an hard matter to be a Chriſtian, in as much as a man muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily be ſo ere he can be ſaed. But if all other things were ſilent, the point we have before us would evince it: for if a man, in order to his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Chriſtian, muſt prove all thoſe things he hath to do with in the buſineſs of Religion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he cloſe with them, and muſt accurately diſtinguiſh bewixt good and bad, taking the one and leaving the other, (as you have heard he muſt) then it muſt needs be an hard thing to be a Chriſtian.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>3</label> 3. If Chriſtians muſt <hi>prove all things,</hi> then it may ſerve for <hi>reproof</hi> to two ſorts of perſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To all ſuch as are <hi>Teachers,</hi> more eſpecially Popiſh <hi>Prelates,</hi> with ſuch as comply with them, and do not allow the people this liberty, but urge doctrings and precepts upon them with as much peremptorineſs and ſeverity, as if they thought their bare word were ſufficient to ſatisfie their peoples conſciences, and legitimate whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they ſhall judge meet to offer to them. <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> makes mention of one <hi>Abbot,</hi>
               <note place="margin">t. <hi>2.</hi> l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>21.</hi> p. <hi>166.</hi>
               </note> that enjoyn'd a <hi>Monk</hi> at his command to enter into a <hi>flaming furnace;</hi> and of another that enjoyn'd a <hi>Monk</hi> at
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:107190:71"/>his command to caſt himſelf upon <hi>the waters.</hi> And there are multitudes ſurviving of the ſame ſpirit, who impoſe what they pleaſe upon the people over whom they are, without allowing them liberty to make proof thereof, though it be but in order to the directing of their own par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular practice. Now, <hi>Sirs,</hi> what mean you thus to afflict the heritage of the Lord, vex your poor people, and trample them under your feet? Wherefore do you thus blind-fold and enthrall them, not ſuffering them to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe the power and freedom belonging to them, when as it is ſo evident, that it is the pleaſure of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> who knows better how to teach and govern his Church, than either men or An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels can tell him that they ſhould do? Is this to imitate your Lord and Maſter, who exerciſed ſo much mildneſs and tenderneſs towards the people he had to deal with, who was ſo ready upon all occaſions to diſpenſe with their infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, comply with their weakneſſes, reſolve their doubts, ſatisfie their ſcruples, and clear up his truth to them? Is this to <hi>gather the Lambs in</hi> your <hi>arms, carry them in</hi> your <hi>boſom,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 10.12.</note> 
               <hi>and deal gently with thoſe that are with young?</hi> Is this, with the Apoſtles, to be <hi>gentle among them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 2.7.</note> 
               <hi>even as a nurſe cheriſheth her children?</hi> Is this the way to make them thrive in knowledge, grace and holineſs?<note place="margin">Iſa. 52.7.</note> Is this the way to render your <hi>feet beautiful,</hi> and make thoſe over whom you are in love with you? Or is it not rather the way to make them weary both of you and your Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, and cauſe them with the reſt of the Creation to <hi>groan</hi> and <hi>travel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.21, 22.</note> that they may be delivered
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:107190:72"/>from the bondage wherein they are, into the <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty</hi> of the children of God? For this very thing (as <hi>Luther</hi> told you long ago) you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve <hi>tanquam lupi &amp; tyranni,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Oper. t. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>375.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>as wolves and ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants to be driven out of the Church of God.</hi> But I ſhall ſum up what I have to ſay to you, into a few <hi>Queries,</hi> which I ſhall offer to your conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. 1. Hath God any where given you power to exerciſe this rigour thwards your people? If you think he hath, tell us where and how to reconcile it, with that liberty which he hath, as I have ſhewed, granted to them. If he hath not, how dare you claim it, or make uſe of it? Do you not acknowledge your ſelves to be under his dominion? muſt you not be account able for all to him? How dare you then do that which you have not warrant for from him? 2. Whether do you take your ſelves to be nfallible? If you do, let us know upon what ground you do it, and how you came to be ſo. The whole world ſighes and groans under crrours and miſtakes, and therefore you muſt not think it much if we look for good evidence from you, ere we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge you to have any ſuch priviledge. If you do not, then how dare you be ſo confident of your own opinions, as to urge them with ſuch ſeverity upon others, who perhaps have as much, if not more reaſon, to be as confident of their own? 3. Whether do you think you may juſtle up your Maker, and challenge the ſame power over your people that he himſelf does? If you may, communicate your reaſons, and ſhew how it comes about that you may do that which Angels tremble at the thoughts of. If not, then
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:107190:72"/>with what Juſtice can you require your people to yield you abſolute aſſent and obedience, and puniſh them for refuſing? What can God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf do more, than require them to believe and obey him upon the authority of his bare word? and what do you in this your rigid behaviour towards them, leſs? 4. Whether may you fall in with <hi>Antichriſt</hi> and do his work? If you may, then wherefore do you pretend to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>own him and be againſt him? If not, how will you ever defend this your imperious deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the people? Certainly, if there be any thing in the World, that incroaches upon the Prerogatives and rights of the Son of God,<note place="margin">See <hi>Ames Bell. Enerv.</hi> l. 1. p. 241.</note> and breaths forth down right <hi>Antichriſtianiſm,</hi> this is it. 5. Whether are you to rule your People as you rule Beaſts, and expect obedience upon the ſame terms, from the one, as you do from the other? If you are, then tell us for what end God en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued them with reaſonable ſouls, and placed them ſo near the Angels? If not, then where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore do you require obedience, without allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to judge of the nature and equity of that you demand from them? wherein do you deal worſe with Beaſts? 6. Whether would you be content that others ſhould deal with you, as you deal with them? If you would, then before you appear any more in the World, go and learn to be men. If not, then wherefore do you exerciſe ſuch ſeverity towards the people, ſince the very light of Nature teaches you not to do unto <hi>others,</hi> what you would not have them to do unto <hi>you?</hi> What is this but to tempt us to think you <hi>are</hi> of the race of the <hi>Scribes</hi>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:107190:73"/>and <hi>Phariſees,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 23.4.</note> who laid thoſe <hi>burdens</hi> upon <hi>others</hi> that they would not endure to bear any part of <hi>themſelves?</hi> Let the conſideration of theſe things ſoften your hearts towards your people, and prevail with you to allow them the liberty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to them. But if you refuſe notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all that can be ſaid, to do it, know that he who is the Protector of the Innocent, will in time deliver them out of the hands of ſuch Oppreſſors.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If may be likewiſe uſefull by way of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof to ſuch among the <hi>people</hi> as take all upon truſt from their Teachers, believe all they ſay, and do all they require. There are many who inſtead of ſtanding up for and maintaining their undoubted and neceſſary liberty, do out of an unmanly, ſervile fear, bow down before them, and inſlave their Reaſon, Judgement, Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and all to them. Now, Sirs, wherefore do you thus deſpiſe the bounty of God, and ſlight the rich purchaſe of <hi>Jeſus</hi> Chriſt your Saviour? Wherefore do you thus let go the liberty he hath required you to ſtand faſt in, and give up your ſelves to the wills of unreaſonable men? what is this but to intitle your ſelves to the doom of <hi>Iſſachar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 49.14.</note> and like ſo many Aſſes <hi>couch down</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your <hi>burdens?</hi> What is this but to tell the World that you are neither Men, nor expect the Priviledges belonging to them, but that you are Beaſts, and are content to be taught, govern'd and dealt with accordingly, than which what can be more unbecoming your reaſonable Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, or the Goſpel which you do profeſs? But in complyance with the method of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:107190:73"/>Branch of this Uſe, I ſhall ſum up what I have to ſay to you in a few Queries. 1. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do you in good earneſt think that the bare word of your Teachers is a ſufficient bottom for you to ground your Faith upon, and ſuch as you may with chearfulneſs and ſatisfaction ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieſce in? If you do, ſhew us what grounds you have for it. Both Scripture and Experience tell us, they labour under much darkneſs and ignorance, and are ſubject to errors and miſtakes. If you do not, wherefore do you lay ſuch ſtreſs upon it, as to venture the glory of God, and the peace and happineſs of your Souls thereon? Theſe are things of ſuch importance, that you ſhould provide better ſecurity for them than the word of any mortal man can be. 2. Whether do you think Chriſt will look upon this your believing and doing all that your Teachers would have you, without any examination and tryall, as a due anſwer to all thoſe Cautions and Warnings he hath given you to beware of letting men <hi>deceive you?</hi> If you do, then tell us what it is to be credulous, ſecure and negligent; wherein it conſiſts, who they be that are guilty of it, and when it is that men expoſe themſelves to the danger of being deceived. If you do not, then why do you not awake and reform, and by due examination and tryall of things pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide better for your own ſafety? 3. Whether may you take to your ſelves other Maſters be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides Chriſt, become their ſervants, and pay ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage and obedience to them? If you may, then ſhew us what the Scripture means, when it ſaith, <hi>One is your Maſter, even Chriſt, and all
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:107190:74"/>ye are Brethren.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 2 38. 1 Cor. 7.23.</note> And, <hi>be not ye the ſervants of men.</hi> If you may not, then wherefore do you grant ſuch Magiſterial power to your Teachers, ſuffer them to give Laws to your Conſciences, and receive their Aſſertions as the very Dictates of Chriſt himſelf? What is it for one to make a man his Maſter, but (as <hi>Pythagoras</hi> his Scholars dealt with him) to receive his Documents meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon the credit and authority of his word; whithout enquiring any further? And when you give up your ſelves to the command of your Teachers, and look upon all they ſay as truth, and all they command as duty, without ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king any proof or tryall, what do you leſs? 4. Whether is it wiſdom to be at an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty in the buſineſs of Religion? If it be, wherefore do's the Holy Ghoſt ſpend ſo many words in exhorting us to make things <hi>ſure?</hi> If it be not, then wherefore do you build upon the ſandy foundation of the doctrines and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments of men, for whom it is as ordinary to erre, as it is for the Starrs to twinckle, or the Clocks to miſs the hour of the day? 5. Whether do you mean to hold out in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion? If you do not, wherefore do you make a profeſſion of it? do you think it worth the while to mock God, and diſhonour the Goſpel? If you do, then wherefore do not you ſatisfie your ſelves better concerning the truth of it, than by taking the Word of men? you know Religion hath ever met with oppoſition, and ſo it is like to do ſtill, and therefore if you mean to hold out, you had beſt get better evidence for the truth of it, than the word of a frail man
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:107190:74"/>can be. So long as the voice of the Countrey goes for it, there's no great danger of forſaking it, but what will you do when all are againſt it, nay, when you ſhall ſee more againſt it than ever you ſaw for it? Now the great and learned, and all the people are for it, which perhaps is the ground whereon you have clos'd with it, but what will you ſay, if you ſee them all againſt it, nay and carried forth with greater zeal againſt it, than ever they were for it? It may be Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion for the preſent is your Intereſt, but what will you ſay to it when it will be your undoing, when it will lead you <hi>to priſon and to death?</hi> Do you think the bare word of your Teachers that perhaps diſclaim all that ever they ſaid before, will bear you up? Do not perſwade your ſelves it will. It may be even now upon your meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with ſome ſmall tryalls, you begin to ſtag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and ſhake, what then will you do, when you ſhall come to encounter with Gibbets and Flames? If you <hi>run with the Foot,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 12.50.</note> 
               <hi>and they weary</hi> you, <hi>how will you contend with horſes?</hi> and if you are not able to abide the ſtill-flowing ſtreams, what will you do with <hi>the ſwellings of Jordan?</hi> 6. Whether do you think, if out of obſervance to your Teachers you follow them into Error, they ſhall anſwer for you? If you do, you lie under a groſs miſtake, for the Apoſtle tells us in plain terms,<note place="margin">Rem. 12.12.</note> that <hi>every on of us ſhall give ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of himſelf to God.</hi> Its true, they ſhall in a ſort anſwer for you, but not with any advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to you. Their being acceſſory to your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion and ruine will implead themſelves, but not excuſe you, who were warn'd to prove what
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:107190:75"/>they ſhould deliver to you, and follow them no further than they ſhould bear the light of the Word before them, which if you had done you had been ſafe, but doing otherwiſe you muſt look to periſh. If you think they muſt not anſwer for you, then wherefore do you make their will your rule, and proſtitute your Faith and Obedience to their pleaſure? Wherefore do you follow them with ſo much boldneſs and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity? Do you think it a ſmall matter to run your ſelves into ſnares, and arm divine Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance againſt you? Have a care what you do, and be not ſo mercileſs and injurious to your Souls. And thus I have given you the Queryes I thought fit to offer to you, which if upon due conſideration you finde weight in, you may im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove them for your direction; if otherwiſe, enjoy your thoughts, but withall be ware, leſt you be found <hi>rebelious againſt the light,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 24.13.</note> and ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to your own ſafety.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>4</label> If Chriſtians muſt <hi>prove all things,</hi> then it may likewiſe be uſefull by way of <hi>Exhortation</hi> to all you who are private Chriſtians, to ſet upon the practice of it. As ever you will endeavour your own welfare, improve the liberty Chriſt hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed on you, and evidence your ſelves to be men, receive not things upon truſt, but by pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and ſerious enquiry, inform your ſelves of the nature, equity and ſoundneſs of them e're you cloſe with them. Take heed of being drawn into the Error ſo expreſly condemned by the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">Jud. <hi>v.</hi> 16.</note> of <hi>having mens perſons in admiration,</hi> or ſuffering your ſelves to be ſwayed and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruled by them. Let them be what they will,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:107190:75"/>in reſpect of birth, parts, place, wealth, honour, power, intereſt, or any ſuch like worldly advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages, yet do not captivate your Faith, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences or Reaſon to them, but by your own perſonal enquiry, ſatisfie your ſelves in whatever you undertake or do, preferring Truth from the meaneſt before Error from the greateſt. Such was the integrity of <hi>Panormitan,</hi> a famous <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer,</hi> who lived about 230 years ago, that he ſaid,<note place="margin">Tit. de elect. C. ſignificat.</note> 
               <hi>Laico verum dicenti cum Evangelio magis cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendum, quàm conſilio falſum dicenti contra Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelium, a Lay man ſpeaking truth with the Goſpel, is to be believed before a whole Council, ſpeaking falſe againſt it.</hi> You muſt not meaſure Doctrines and Opinions, by the quality of the perſons de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livering them, but by the evidence accompany<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them. It is not worldly greatneſs that can make Error Truth, or Worldly meaneſs that can make Truth Error, but when all is done, Error will be Error, and Truth will be Truth. And therefore let not the pompous and ſplendid condition, wherein at any time you finde Error, cauſe you to eſteem or embrace it as Truth; nor the deſpicable and low condition wherein you finde Truth, cauſe you to diſlike or decline it as Error, but waving all ſuch outward conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, give both the one and the other the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect belonging to them. A Pearl though lying in the dirt, is of far more value, than a Pebble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone in the richeſt Cabinet: And the like is to be ſaid concerning Truth; it is of more worth in the plaineſt and homelieſt dreſs, than Error in all its paint and garniſh. The head of Truth is worthier your reſpect under a <hi>Crown of thorns,</hi>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:107190:76"/>than the head of Error under a Crown of Gold. And therefore notwithſtanding all the ignominy and contempt that fooliſh and ungodly men may caſt upon it, ſuffer not your ſelves to be wrought out of conceit with it, but yield unto it its de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved eſteem.</p>
            <p>Now that you may manage this tryall of things, with more advantage and ſucceſs, and be the better able to diſtinguiſh betwixt Truth and Error, and paſs a juſt ſentence, forbearing to uſe any more words to preſs you to the work, I ſhall in the next place propound ſome <hi>rules</hi> to direct you in it. And here I ſhall not inſiſt upon thoſe which our Writers preſeribe in order to the due Interpretation of the Scripture, ſuch as the <hi>conſulting</hi> the ſcope of the Text,<note place="margin">Whitak. part <hi>1.</hi> cont. <hi>1.</hi> q. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi> p. <hi>361.</hi> Rainolds Conf. ch. <hi>2.</hi> div. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>45.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>comparing</hi> one place with another, <hi>adhering</hi> to the Analo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy of Faith laid down in the Creeds and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions of the Churches, with ſuch like, which yet are very worthy your obſervation, but ſhall pitch upon ſuch as are more particular, and as I conceive more ſuitable to the preſent ſubject.</p>
            <p n="1">1. While you are managing this Tryall, be ſure you beware of ſuch Doctrines as interfere and claſh with the greatneſs, ſoveraignty and majeſty of God, and tend to the diminiſhing of the honour and ſervice due to him. The <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts</hi> as if they envyed the preheminence of God, and were minded to jumble Heaven and Earth together, and level all into a common equality, make many inſolent, and ſtrange diviſions. They divide <hi>adoration</hi> betwixt him and Images; <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation</hi> betwixt him and Saints; and abſolute <hi>obedience</hi> betwixt him and the Church. Now
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:107190:76"/>what groſs and horrible Sacriledge is this? what is this but to deveſt him of his Royalty, and give his Glory unto another, which yet is a ſin ſo great and hainous, that one would think they ſhould tremble at the thoughts of it? Beware how you fall in with theſe men; keep up the honour of God intire, and reject all Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines that tend either to alienate or diminiſh it. It is he that made this ſtupendious Fabrick of the World, ſet it upon its Pillars, upholds it in its place, and by his ſupream direction, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence and conduct, orders and diſpoſes of all perſons, actions and events that are therein. It is he only that hath abſolute ſoveraignty, glory, and wiſdome, and therefore it is he only that you muſt religiouſly adore, invocate and obey.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Beware of ſuch Doctrines as tend in the leaſt to diſparage the Scripture, or bring it into contempt with you. It is the <hi>candle of the Lord,</hi> the Guide of the Soul, and the Rule and Judge of all Controverſies in Religion whatſoever; and therefore ſuffer it by no means to go out of eſteem with you. Such Doctrines as tend to honour and credit it, cloſe with them; but as for thoſe which tend to diſparage and diſgrace it, reject them as pernicious and dangerous blaſphemies. The <hi>Papiſts,</hi> becauſe it never ſpeaks well of them, and that they may the better bring it into diſeſteem, ſay almoſt all manner of evil againſt it. They teach that the authority of it depends upon the Church, that it is obſcure and imperfect, that the <hi>Apocryphal</hi> Books and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane <hi>Traditions,</hi> deſerve as much reverence as it. And what is this but to reproach the wiſdom
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:107190:77"/>of God, and requite all the care and love he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſts to us in his Word with ingratitude and contempt. When you meet with any that preach ſuch doctrine, if you cannot convince them, avoid them as the Agents of <hi>Satan,</hi> and ſuch as ſeek to ſubvert and undo you.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Beware of ſuch doctrins as tend to the dethroning of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the diſparaging of his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings and performances, or the diminiſhing any way of the honour and praiſe belonging to him. The <hi>Papiſts</hi> not thinking it ſufficient to rob God, do likewiſe rob him, taking from him, and leaving with him what they think fit. They divide his Soveraignty and Headſhip betwixt him and the Pope, Satisfaction and Merits be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt him and Saints; Invocation and Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion betwixt him and dAngels. And what is this but to tell him, he ſhall not reign over them, nor have the honour belonging to him? Take heed how you joyn with them in any ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings. As he is the undoubted Lord and King of his Church, ſo he hath undertaken the reconciling of God and Man, and the making of attonement betwixt them; and in order thereunto, he did in his death offer a valuable conſideration unto Juſtice for the offence done, which he now pleads in Heaven, (where he ſits at his Father's right hand interceding for us) and that ſo effectually, that to bring in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances of any of his creatures, is to light a candle before the <hi>Sun,</hi> and carry water to the <hi>Ocean.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Beware of ſuch doctrins as tend to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenuating of God's free grace, and the exalting
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:107190:77"/>of mans free will. To exalt the former, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenuate the latter, is to give unto God the things that are Gods, and into man the things that are mans; but to extenuate the former and exalt the latter, is to give unto God the things that are mans, and unto man the things that are Gods. Notwithſtanding the <hi>Papiſts</hi> divide the work of converſion betwixt the grace of God, and the will of man, making them partners in the effecting of it. And what is this but to take away the praiſe due unto God, and aſcribe it to a ſilly impotent creature, that is as far from having power to convert himſelf, as he was from having power to make himſelf when he had no exiſtence, or redeem himſelf when he was fallen. Be not you thus injurious to the grace of God, but ſeek unto him to work your converſion; and when he hath done it, give him all the praiſe. If you do erre, let it be on the right hand; do it rather in giving grace too much, than too little.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Beware of ſuch doctrines as are againſt the power of godlineſs, and tend either to profane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or lukewarmneſs. Acquaint your ſelves with, and yield obedience to all Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments; ſerve him not onely with the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, but the inward man. What ever ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance or duty you undertake, beſure you ingage the ſoul in it. The <hi>Papiſts</hi> (at leaſt many of them) that they may at the laſt ſtab Religion to the heart, and fill up the meaſure of their ſins, divide man into ſoul and body; and then ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their wonted juſtice, ſpeak, as if the one, and worſer part thereof, were enough for
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:107190:78"/>God. He himſelf does every where in Scripture call upon us to manage his work with affection, ſeriouſneſs, diligence, nay, with all our might; but they ſay, all this is not needful, perſuading their credulous people, that the <hi>opus operatum</hi> is enough, that the celebrating of certain offices and rites, which they themſelves have thought fit to preſcribe, and the performing of ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal trivial ſolemnities will ſerve the turn, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any more ado. And thus as they divide Faith betwixt Scripture and Tradition; Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip betwixt God and Images, Reconciliation betwixt Chriſt and Saints; Converſion betwixt Free-grace and Free-will: ſo likewiſe they di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide Man into two parts, Soul and Body; and when they have done, they order God onely ſome ſuperficial ſervice, conſiſting in a company of empty childiſh Rites, from the latter, leaving us in the mean time to employ the former as our own prudence or inclinations ſhall direct us. And hereby we ſee, notwithſtanding the flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes and pretences that theſe men ſometimes make to Religion, what friends they are to it. As if they thought it not ſufficient injury unto God to detract from the authority of his Word, Worſhip, the performances of his Son, his free grace, they have at the laſt adventured to take from him the far better part of his creature, without the concurrence of which, the ſervices of the other, how ſplendid and coſtly ſoever, are no more pleaſing to him, than the noiſome eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porations of a ſtinking carcaſe are to us. Have a care how you entertain ſuch doctrins, or have to do with ſuch men. Maintain and keep up the
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:107190:78"/>ſoveraignty of God, the authority of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, the offices of Chriſt, the workings of divine grace, with the practice of godlineſs in their higheſt ſtrength and glory, ſhunning all thoſe as the enemies of God and true Religion that are adverſaries thereunto.</p>
            <p>Now becauſe the non-performance of this duty of Chriſtian trial proceeds from certain <hi>impediments</hi> that lie in the way. I ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the next place mention ſome of them, that ſo being acquainted with them, you may avoid the influence and danger of them. And the</p>
            <p n="1">1. Is a vain credulity or proneneſs that is in men, to credit what ever is propounded and tendred to them, eſpecially if it come from ſuch as they bear reverence and reſpect to. Such is the confidence that the generality of children have in their parents, ſervants in their maſters, people in their Teachers, and one relation and friend in another, that they are ready, without any ſcruple or enquiry, to ſubſcribe to what ever they deliver to them. The <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> obſerv'd in his time, that though the principles and courſes of anceſtors were never ſo abſurd and fooliſh, yet their credulous ſucceſſors, out of the indiſcreet reverence they bore to them approv'd of them; <hi>This their way</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is their folly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 49.13.</note> 
               <hi>yet their poſterity approve their ſayings.</hi> They did not weigh things as they ought to have done, and as wiſe men would have done, but looking upon the credit of their anceſtors as a ſufficient foundation to their faith and confidence, they aſſented to what ever they held or practiſed as ſound and good. Now this is a dangerous courſe,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:107190:79"/>and leads to no other than deluſion and miſery. And therefore let men be what they will as to their places, abilities or pretences, take not every thing for truth that they deliver, but uſe your eyes, and ſatisfie your ſelves before you give your aſſent. This God himſelf does in expreſs terms require;<note place="margin">Jer. 12.6.</note> 
               <hi>Even thy brethren</hi> (ſaith the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet</hi>) <hi>and the houſe of thy father, even they have dealt treacherouſly with thee, yea, they have called a multitude after thee, believe them not, though they ſpeak fair words unto thee.</hi> Here he diſſuades the <hi>Jews</hi> from the credulity he ſaw them addicted to, admoniſhing them, that though the perſons they had to deal with were never ſo near and dear to them, though they were their brethren and kinsfolk, though their pretences were never ſo ſpecious and plauſible, yet they ſhould not without better evidence than their own word confide in them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Is an unadviſed preſuming upon their own ſudden apprehenſions of what comes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, as if they could by the caſt of an eye fathom the depth of it, and paſs a right judgment upon it. There is ſcarcely any man ſo illiterate or unskilful in Religion, but he thinks he may judge of things according to what at the firſt proſpect or view they appear to him, and ſo looks upon all further enquiry as ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous and needleſs; which is a dangerous as well as a groundleſs conceit, and may no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter conſiſt with our ſafety, than it may with thoſe humbling and abaſing thoughts, we ought to have of our ſelves. Had we retain'd our primitive light and innocency, we might
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:107190:79"/>better have lean'd upon our own wiſdom, and confided in ſudden apprehenſions; but alas, its far otherwiſe with us. The higheſt Angels in the Church have in them ſome <hi>folly,</hi> and thoſe whom God hath bleſſed with profoundeſt wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, know but <hi>in part.</hi> Their ſight in the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of ſalvation, is even like his who ſaw men <hi>walking like trees.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mar. 8.24.</note> What then ſhall we ſay of the common people, who fall almoſt as far ſhort of them, as they do of perfection? May it then ſtand with their ſafety to truſt to the firſt view of things? what is it elſe but to venture all (as it were) upon a die, and with the <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites, aleae luſu contendere, caſt lots</hi> whether they ſhall do their duty or not,<note place="margin">Vid. Ames Bell: Ener. t. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>234.</hi>
               </note> and conſequently whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they ſhall be ſaved or damned?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Is careleſneſs and regardleſneſs of truth, which they are ſo far from eſteeming and thirſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after as they ſhould, that they do not much matter whether they have it or not. So they can but ſecure their worldly happineſs, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy their honour, wealth and pleaſure, they matter not whether they are in the right or wrong, or what kind of Religion takes place. Such a one was <hi>Gallio</hi> the <hi>Proconſul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 18.17.</note> or Deputy of <hi>Achaia,</hi> who though he ſaw the Goſpel per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted, and the ſervants of Chriſt trodden un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der foot, yet he <hi>cared</hi> not. And this is the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the generality of people; ſo they can but dwell in their <hi>cieled houſes,</hi> and ſit under <hi>their own vines and fig-trees,</hi> they regard not the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God, nor care what becomes of his cauſe and truth.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Is lazineſs and ſlothſulneſs in the buſineſs
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:107190:80"/>of Religion, which indiſpoſes them for all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes and duties of this nature. Such is the temper of moſt, that though they are convinced the work is neceſſary, and ought by all means to be done, yet rather than they will be at the pains of it, they let it alone, and expoſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the danger that unavoidably attends the neglect of it. Though they can ſpeak well of it, and wiſh it were done, yet out of meer ſloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, inſtead of falling upon it, and managing it with life and vigour, as they ought, they lie ſtretching themſelves upon their beds, ſaying with <hi>Solomon</hi>'s ſluggard,<note place="margin">Prov. 6.10.</note> 
               <hi>Yet a little ſleep, a little ſlumber, a little folding of the hands to ſleep.</hi> And what is the iſſue of it? why, their <hi>poverty comes as one that travelleth, and their want as an armed man.</hi> As corporal ſlothfulneſs brings poverty and want upon the body, ſo ſpiritual ſlothfulneſs brings it upon the ſoul.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Is multitude of worldly buſineſſes, which wholly take up their thoughts, cares and parts, and engage them to ſuch attendance on them, that they cannot ſpare time to look after things of a ſpiritual nature.<note place="margin">Acts 24.25.</note> 
               <hi>Felix</hi> might have convers'd with <hi>Paul,</hi> and have had the truth, which he was a ſtranger to, from him; but his hands were ſo full of other matters, that he could not be at leiſure to do it. The ſtory of <hi>Antipater</hi> King of <hi>Macedon</hi> is well known; when one preſented a book to him treating of <hi>happineſs,</hi> his anſwer was, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>I am not at leiſure.</hi> And ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe is that of the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Alva,</hi> who when <hi>Henry</hi> the 4. of <hi>France</hi> asked him whether he had obſerved the Eclipſes, he anſwered, No;
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:107190:80"/>withall adding, That he had ſo much to do upon <hi>Earth,</hi> that he had not leiſure to look up to <hi>Heaven.</hi> And the reaſon wherefore many thouſands omit to enquire after the truth, is, becauſe they have already filled their hands ſo full of other matters, that they cannot without the neglect of them (which of all things they are loth to be guilty of) be at leiſure to do it.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Is a deſperate unmovable reſolution to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed and go forward in the ways wherein they are, let them be good or bad. Though they can render no reaſon at all for it, yet they like them ſo well, and are ſo in love with them, that they reſolve to continue in them, let the iſſue be what it will. Thus the <hi>Jews</hi> in <hi>Jeremy</hi>'s time carri'd themſelves; let God and his Prophets ſay what they would, they were reſolved to do what was good in their own eyes, and perſiſt in the way they had propunded to themſelves to walk in: <hi>We will certainly</hi> (ſay they) <hi>do whatſoever thing goeth out of our own mouth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 44.17.</note> 
               <hi>to burn incenſe to the queen of heaven, and to pour out drink-offerings unto her,</hi> &amp;c. They reſolve not to do that which comes out of the mouth of the Lord, as once they pretended to do, when they ſaid to <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 5.27.</note> 
               <hi>Speak unto us all that the Lord our God ſhall ſpeak unto thee, and we will hear and do it;</hi> no, but to do that which comes out of their <hi>own mouth.</hi> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do they do it with neceſſary limitations and reſtrictions, but with greateſt abſoluteneſs and peremptorineſs, as thoſe that had none to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trol or queſtion them for it. And what is that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular thing that they thus reſolve to do? why, to worſhip the Moon, here called (as divers
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:107190:81"/>Expoſitors think) <hi>the Queen of Heaven.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vid. A Lapid. com. in <hi>Jer. 7.18.</hi>
               </note> Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the many high, and eminent obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that they lay under, to worſhip the true God, and him only, yet they reſolve, and that with greateſt peremptorineſs, without rendring any good reaſon for it, that they will do other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. Their words imply as much as if they had ſaid, notwithſtanding all that we have heard and ſeen of God, and the many and various tyes that lye upon us to adhere and cleave to him, yet it is come into our minds to go after other Gods, and let what will be ſaid to the contrary, we are reſolv'd to do it. And after this manner the rude multitude carryed themſelves towards Chriſt. Though they had nothing to alledge againſt him,<note place="margin">Luk. 23.14.</note> yet they cry out, <hi>Let him be cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</hi> Though, after all the advantagious hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Pilate</hi> could afford them, they could urge no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing where of they might accuſe him, yet they cry out, <hi>Let him be crucified.</hi> Nay, though <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late</hi> told them in plain terms that neither he nor <hi>Herod</hi> could finde any fault or cauſe of death in him, yet they ſtill cry out, <hi>Let him be cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. q.d.</hi> Whether he be guilty, or not guilty, faulty, or not faulty, we are reſolved to have his Life, and therefore ſtand no longer reaſoning with us, but <hi>let him be crucified.</hi> So we read how above forty impious and bloody Wretches <hi>bound themſelves under a Curſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 23.12.</note> 
               <hi>that they would neither eat nor drink till they had killed Paul.</hi> Though he was one that had lived in all good Conſcience amongſt them, ſo that they had no juſt action in the World againſt him, yet having taken up a malicious prejudice towards. him,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:107190:81"/>they ſtand no longer to conſult Juſtice, or Equity, but reſolve to be his death. And thus it is with many in our dayes; having taken up (they know not how) a diſlike of ſuch a way, they are reſolv'd to be againſt it, though evidence for it be never ſo plain and full. The reaſon wherefore divers will not be <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they have taken up a Purpoſe againſt it; and having done that, they think it may not conſiſt with their honour to comply and fall in with them. And when men are once got to this, they are ſo far from being perſwaded to bring things to tryall, that they do but deſpiſe all motions leading thereunto.</p>
            <p>And thus I have laid before you ſome of the <hi>impediments</hi> that tend to hinder you from the duty I have in this Diſcourſe cleared up and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended to you. Let it now be your care to break through them, and overcome them. Give your ſelves no reſt till you have found out what it is that God would have you to believe and do.<note place="margin">2 Sam. 23.16.</note> Even as <hi>Davids</hi> three mighty men broke through the Hoſt of the <hi>Philiſtims</hi> to get to the Well of <hi>Bethlehem;</hi> ſo do you break through theſe and other impediments and diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties that lie in your way, that ſo at laſt arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving at the Well of Truth, you may drink of the pleaſant and wholſome ſtreams that flow therefrom, and be for ever ſatisfied.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
